<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0034-7329</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista Brasileira de Política Internacional]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. bras. polít. int.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0034-7329</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Instituto Brasileiro de Relações Internacionais]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0034-73292010000200009</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0034-73292010000200009</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Never before seen in Brazil: Luis Inácio Lula da Silva's grand diplomacy]]></article-title>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Nunca antes visto no Brasil: a grande diplomacia de Lula]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Almeida]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Paulo Roberto de]]></given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A">
<institution><![CDATA[,  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>53</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<fpage>160</fpage>
<lpage>177</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0034-73292010000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0034-73292010000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0034-73292010000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Critical assessment of Luis Inácio Lula da Silva's diplomacy, which departed from the previous patterns of the Brazilian Foreign Service, to align itself with the political conceptions of the Workers' Party. This diplomacy has neither consolidated the position of Brazil as a regional leader, nor attained its declared goal of inserting Brazil into the United Nations Security Council, although it has reinforced Brazil's image in the international scenarios; but this was achieved much more through the personal activism of the President himself, than through normal diplomatic work.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Avaliação crítica da diplomacia do governo Lula, que abandonou os padrões tradicionais do Itamaraty para alinhar-se com as concepções políticas do Partido dos Trabalhadores. Essa diplomacia não conseguiu consolidar a posição do Brasil como líder regional, nem logrou o objetivo declarado de colocar o país no Conselho de Segurança das Nações Unidas, muito embora tenha reforçado a imagem do Brasil no cenário internacional; mas isso foi alcançado mais por meio do ativismo do próprio presidente, do que pelo trabalho diplomático normal.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Brazil]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[diplomacy]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Lula government]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[regional leadership]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[global presence]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Brasil]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[diplomacia]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[governo Lula]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[liderança regional]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[presença global]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>ARTIGO</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="top"></a><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><b>Never    Before Seen in Brazil: Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's grand diplomacy</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Nunca antes    visto no Brasil: a grande diplomacia de Lula</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Paulo Roberto    de Almeida</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Phd in Social Sciences    and Brazilian career diplomat (<a href="mailto:pralmeida@mc.com">pralmeida@mc.com</a>)</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Critical assessment    of Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's diplomacy, which departed from the previous    patterns of the Brazilian Foreign Service, to align itself with the political    conceptions of the Workers' Party. This diplomacy has neither consolidated the    position of Brazil as a regional leader, nor attained its declared goal of inserting    Brazil into the United Nations Security Council, although it has reinforced    Brazil's image in the international scenarios; but this was achieved much more    through the personal activism of the President himself, than through normal    diplomatic work.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Key-words:</b>    Brazil, diplomacy, Lula government, regional leadership, global presence.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o    cr&iacute;tica da diplomacia do governo Lula, que abandonou os padr&otilde;es    tradicionais do Itamaraty para alinhar-se com as concep&ccedil;&otilde;es pol&iacute;ticas    do Partido dos Trabalhadores. Essa diplomacia n&atilde;o conseguiu consolidar    a posi&ccedil;&atilde;o do Brasil como l&iacute;der regional, nem logrou o objetivo    declarado de colocar o pa&iacute;s no Conselho de Seguran&ccedil;a das Na&ccedil;&otilde;es    Unidas, muito embora tenha refor&ccedil;ado a imagem do Brasil no cen&aacute;rio    internacional; mas isso foi alcan&ccedil;ado mais por meio do ativismo do pr&oacute;prio    presidente, do que pelo trabalho diplom&aacute;tico normal.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Palavras-chave:</b>    Brasil, diplomacia, governo Lula, lideran&ccedil;a regional, presen&ccedil;a    global.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>South America    was not enough: Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva goes out into the world</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Has Brazil already    attained the status of a global power, as sought by Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva's diplomacy? Or, despite all his efforts, does it remain a mere regional    power? Those two questions were, almost obsessively, at the center of Lula's    entrepreneurial diplomacy, for the whole duration of his administration (2003-2010).    The questions are still open.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Global power status,    as is well known, is not a matter of national choice, or an issue subjected    only to the political will of the actors involved in what is a complex and interrelated    equation. It depends on a complete set of objective factors - connected with    economic strength, technological endowments and military capabilities - as well    as on a clear recognition of that status by other actors, first of all by the    general consensus of the international community, but especially by the great    powers.<a name="top1"></a><a href="#back1"><sup>1</sup></a> This recognition    is usually linked to primary sources of power - Russia and China clearly fit    the pattern - but it can also be associated with other attributions and types    of participation in world affairs - cooperation, defense of human rights and    democracy, etc.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">According to those    criteria, Brazil cannot be recognized, yet, as a global power, as it lacks some    of the capabilities linked to those pre-conditions, with an emphasis on financial    and military capabilities. Neither is it acknowledged as such by the world community.    Much of the talk about Brazil's new role is due to its active diplomacy under    Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva, together with the deployment of external cooperation    towards poor countries in Africa and Latin America (efforts labeled, by the    President himself, as the 'diplomacy of generosity'). But, Brazil's association    with some less commendable actors - such as Iran or Cuba - as well as its poor    record on human rights questions, an issue which clearly diminished in importance    in Lula's time, has weakened its credentials in terms of the expectations of    public opinion.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">But even on a more    limited regional basis, it is also probably an exaggeration to count Brazil    as a South American 'natural leader', for reasons other than a desire for 'grandeur'.    Notwithstanding the fact that it fills almost completely the objective criteria    to be recognized as such - territorial, economic and demographic dimensions;    size of internal markets; presence in external markets; concentration and diversification    of investments; level of industrial development; the most advanced technological    basis on the continent; its already large direct investment flows in neighboring    countries; and, of course, military capabilities - Brazil does not yet enjoy    some of the 'subjective' criteria linked to that status, the most important    of those being the willing acceptance by the neighboring countries of such a    role. Not only Argentina and Colombia, the two other middle-level powers in    South America, but also the smaller countries, are not yet ready to accept Brazil    as their regional representative or want it to act as a kind of an unelected    speaker on their behalf. Unfortunately, big countries are seldom appreciated    in their regions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This lack of natural    leadership derives not only from historical reasons - the fact that Brazil is    the sole Portuguese-speaking country within a Spanish environment, and that    it emerged as a monarchy in the 19<sup>th</sup> century, in a republican continent    - but also from negative contemporary factors, such as the traditional links    it has maintained with developed countries in Europe and North America at the    expense of its interactions with South American neighbors. Huge Brazilian direct    investments and many diplomatic initiatives have been undertaken in recent years    in practically all South American countries, but this has not been enough to    change the lack of enthusiasm for Brazil's role as a leader.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Notwithstanding    its importance in the regional context and its growing role and presence in    some questions on the international agenda - especially in multilateral trade    policies and WTO negotiations, and environmental affairs, among others - it    would be a little premature to count Brazil among the major powers in the world.    An objective evaluation of Brazil's current limited capabilities also has to    recognize brilliant prospects for the medium term: Brazil is already an 'emerged'    country, but still an 'emerging' economy and a power broker. The fact of the    general discussion about its greater role on the world diplomatic agenda should    be acknowledged as a real accomplishment for President Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Any assessment    of his diplomacy has to start from the fact - and this is its distinctive character    - that it does not follow the traditional patterns of professional diplomatic    practices, but rather its own Workers' Party, the PT's, ideological choices    and political inputs. Those party preferences have left their marks heavily    in the foreign policy of Brazil in a manner never seen before 2003. Accordingly,    we shall first review the said 'innovation' in Brazilian foreign policy, both    in terms of doctrine and of political orientation, and then move to the main    issues of the diplomatic agenda. Lula's diplomacy was not only conceived and    applied more in line with party politics than with State considerations, but    it has also served much more his own motivations for personal aggrandizement    in world scenarios than Brazil's national interests.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Shoes and sovereignty:    the rhetoric of a sectarian Party diplomacy</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">For the first time    in decades, or ever, Brazilian foreign policy was conceived and conducted under    the overriding influence of non-professional diplomats. The PT's 'foreign policy'    was the dominant element in Brazilian foreign policy since the beginning of    the da Silva government, but not in a structured manner, as the PT never 'produced'    a structured or a complete set of conceptions and solutions for Brazil's international    relations. The party always had a poor theoretical structure, simply relying    on 'Gramscian' figures from academia for the preparation of more sophisticated    papers and proposals relating to economics and political life. But the core    of its 'thinking' - if one can indulge it with such a description - is a confused    mixture of typical (and stereotypical) Latin-American leftism with old-style    nationalism and anti-imperialism, with brushes of Castroism, Stalinism, Trotskyism,    and Liberation Theology beliefs.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">From the standpoint    of its organizational structures, the PT is a quasi-Bolshevik party, albeit    without the old apparatchik apparatus of a Soviet-style Communist party. In    the beginning, its core staff was formed mainly by: (a) 'alternative' trade-unionists,    who started by rejecting the traditional trade-unions linked to the Ministry    of Labor, but who have quickly adapted to the flow of easy money provided by    the compulsory labor tax (the act of creating new trade unions is a prosperous    'industry', and the practice has enormously prospered under Lula); (b) old guerrilla-fighters,    or semi-professional revolutionaries, 'recycled' into party politics (albeit    keeping some old habits from their previous clandestine life, and liaisons with    Cuba in particular); and, (c) religious movements, such as the leftist Liberation    Theology and 'ecclesial communities'.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The PT's 'ideology'    is a mixture of old style socialist credo, prior to the fall of Berlin wall,    and of social-democratic economic beliefs (mostly of a purely redistributive    character). In fact, many of the sects that make up PT are still true believers    in socialism, and are die-hard statists who still trust in the merits of a planned    economy. For all purposes, they are anti-capitalists, anti-imperialists, and    naturally, anti-Americans, as almost all of the leftist Latin-American parties    are. Some of the PT apparatchiks were trained and instructed by Cuban intelligence    officers, which can explain their loyalty to Cuba's goals in Latin America,    such as the organization of the S&atilde;o Paulo Forum (the FSP), a Cuban-sponsored    coordinating mechanism for all leftist parties in the region which until 2005    included members of the Colombian FARC.<a name="top2"></a><a href="#back2"><sup>2</sup></a></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The PT's main guidelines    in foreign policy were established by those involved in its 'international relations',    starting with the who had apparatchiks that lived in exile during the military    regime (1964-1985). Some of them happened to enjoy the confidence of their Cuban    mentors, a fact that exerted some influence in the definition and implementation    of 'their' foreign policy, when the time arrived. The future President himself    - who, as a trade unionist and leader of metalworkers, developed links with    counterparts in Cuba, in the USA, and in Europe - came to understand better    the intricacies of international politics; his qualitative leap, the one that    was decisive for his own personal life and for the political itinerary of Brazil,    was to create in 1980, with the help of former guerrilla fighters, a political    party that was to represent a departure from traditional politics and trade-unionism    in Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nevertheless, the    PT always was, and continues to be, a consortium of leftists, engaged actively    in the party's cause, which is not exactly a national cause according to the    normal lines of a parliamentary or even a presidential democracy. The PT has    always relied on mass politics or popular organizations, like students' associations,    labor unions or peasant movements, which it controlled. Its concept of democracy    is merely instrumental: everything that serves the major objective of holding    power for the party fits its "philosophy" and practices. Adhering to a 'Cuban'    agenda, it is not surprising if human rights or democracy do not occupy higher    levels in this kind of diplomacy. This feature has to be considered as the major    political component of Brazilian foreign policy during Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva's government.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Bizarre friendships    and 'new trade geography': Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's international    policy</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Two main objectives    have marked, in a somewhat contradictory manner, Brazilian foreign policy under    Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva: the preservation of national sovereignty and    the strengthening of regional integration in South America, the latter being    a continuation of policies already implemented by previous governments. The    former, that is, the sovereign presence of Brazil in the world, would have to    be decreased if the latter is to be reinforced, as exclusively national policies    - in sectors such as industry, agriculture, or even trade policy - have to accommodate    the choices being made in favor of regional integration. Its priorities were    established in three main areas: the reform of the United Nations Charter and    Brazil's accession to a permanent seat on its Security Council; the finalization    of multilateral trade negotiations, with a preferential option for the relationship    with the European Union, instead of the conclusion of the American project of    a hemispheric free trade area (FTAA), strongly opposed by the PT and other leftist    movements; the reinforcement of Mercosur and its extension to other countries    in South America, starting with Chile and other Southern Cone countries, such    as Bolivia. Other priorities comprised the establishment of a strong relationship    with selected 'strategic allies', designated as being 'non-hegemonic countries',    namely China, Russia, India, and South Africa, the last two forming part of    the IBSA forum, the first three organized along the lines proposed in the Goldman    Sachs study on the BRIC countries.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">All these moves    followed the so-called 'South-South' diplomacy and the desire to create a 'new    geography of world trade' and strengthen the 'democratization of international    relations', without 'imperial arrogance' and 'hegemonic unilateralism'. In terms    of 'tools' to accomplish those objectives, it is not difficult to recognize    the high quality of Brazilian professional diplomacy. Brazil's 'diplomatic GDP'    is greater than its economic GDP, and the latter is certainly greater than its    'military GDP', in other words, its capacity for projecting power abroad. Indeed,    Brazil's influence in diplomatic negotiations is more important than its actual    presence in the world, as compared, for instance, to its participation in trade    and financial flows (as a recipient of foreign capital and know-how, and a modest    investor abroad). Brazil's professional diplomatic skills make it a relevant    actor and sometimes a broker in important multilateral trade negotiations (despite    its minor role in financial or trade areas).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nevertheless, Brazil's    influence in the new global interdependence is being handicapped by its mixed    feelings toward globalization, and this is reinforced by the PT's leading role    in its diplomacy, as the party combines an old-style nationalism with defensive    policies in the industrial and investment sectors, including trade protectionism    and the promotion of substitutive industrialization. For many of its political    leaders - and obviously for all the leftists in the da Silva government - globalization    is just another name for Americanization, which they reject and even despise    because of their superficial nationalism and instinctive protectionism. It is    true that Brazil, in promoting Mercosur, has abandoned the worst aspects of    its hard-core protectionism from the 1950s up to the 1980s, but entrepreneurs    and the political elite maintain the same old feelings of the 'dependency school',    a mixture of developmental Keynesianism and a vague Third World ideology demanding    a 'new international economic order'.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Policy reforms,    in line with the Washington Consensus of the 1990s, and the Cardoso administration's    more receptive attitude toward globalization, brought Brazil more in line with    mainstream economics, promoting economic opening and trade liberalization. But,    starting with Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's government, those policies    were somewhat reversed, if not taken back to the old days of Latin American    'Structuralism', identified with Raul Prebisch and Celso Furtado, former guardians    of this 'heterodox' school. This reversal in diplomatic guidelines was presented    as a renewal with the 'Independent Foreign Policy' of the early 1960s, when    it was in fact only the result of nostalgia for old times.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Many of the new    manifestations of this 'sovereign diplomacy' have been focused in consolidating    alliances with a few selected partners in the Third World, mainly large emerging    countries, notably India, South Africa and China, with the addition of Russia    to the process, as it is considered to be an 'anti-hegemonic' counter-power.    Great efforts have been made to achieve the goal of inserting Brazil into the    <i>inner sanctum</i> of the UN Security Council, an initiative that served to    arouse the opposition of Argentina and other competitors. Another goal, that    of strengthening and expanding Mercosur, with the inclusion of new partners    in South America has, in fact, resulted in the dilution of its trade rules and    in an overextension of 'social pacts', which have little meaning for real integration.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In parallel with    the so-called 'diplomacy of generosity' in Latin America - to consolidate a    self-ascribed 'Brazilian leadership' in the region, a role always rejected by    professional diplomacy, mindful of its negative tones - the PT government took    initiatives to isolate United States in the region and enlarge the sphere of    self-coordination among Latin American or South American countries. It started    by refusing - in fact sabotaging - the FTAA initiative, proposed by President    Clinton in 1994, an act undertaken by a joint action by Argentina, Brazil and    Venezuela. This policy was also pursued through a series of proposals for the    establishment of new bodies uniting exclusively South or Latin American countries.    One of them was aimed at submitting the Colombian-US agreement for cooperation    against the narco-guerrillas to a detailed scrutiny by a new consultation mechanism    proposed by Brazil: the South American Defense Council, itself part of a larger    structure, the Union of South American Nations (Unasur).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In February 2010,    for instance, with total support from Brazil, a Latin American 'unity' Summit    decided the double establishment of the new Community of Latin American and    Caribbean States, which replaced the former Rio Group (1986), and of a Latin    American Summit on Integration and Development, also created by a Brazilian    initiative in December 2008. "For the first time in 200 years", it was said,    Latin American countries were meeting "without any kind of guardianship", that    is, exempt from any influence from the 'empire' and fully integrating Cuba into    the coordinating and consultation mechanisms. The exclusion of the 'empire'    was presented as a "success", a <i>'</i>first' in Latin American history, as    Brazilian diplomacy acquired the capacity to "say no".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The anti-American    orientation of those actions was very clear, not only for ideological reasons,    a feature which might be normally expected from a typical leftist Latin American    party, such as PT, still proud of its Cuban links and its solidarity with 'liberation    movements'. It was also welcomed as a misguided feeling that integration under    the aegis of "imperialism of free-trade" (as the American initiatives were labeled)    would rather correspond to a project of 'annexation', instead of a symmetrical    integration. It was on behalf of that creed that many other initiatives were    taken, including the deliberate sinking of the regional negotiations for a hemispheric    free trade area and the frustrated proposal for a South American free trade    area (which did not prevent some countries from signing bilateral trade agreements    with the US).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Paradoxically,    Brazil was accused of being 'imperialist', and has been asked, in consequence,    to pay the costs of the 'asymmetrical situation' created by its very huge presence.    Bolivia, Paraguay, Uruguay, other countries - even Argentina - forced Brazil    to accept new and very generous terms for the reinforcement of their relationship:    Bolivia nationalized oil and gas resources exploited by the Brazilian state    company Petrobras; Paraguay required additional payments for its share of electricity    generated by the bi-national hydro-electric plant at Itaipu; Argentina unilaterally    imposed safeguards and other defensive trade restrictions on a number of Brazilian    manufactured goods that would be normally exported through the free-trade area    of Mercosur; Uruguay and other countries, including Venezuela wanted investments    or financing from Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">During previous    administrations, professional diplomacy conducted bilateral relations with the    United States under normal assumptions of cooperation and consultation without    any ideological misconceptions about what is usually called 'American hegemonic    pretensions'. The PT's diplomacy reverted to the 'normal' anti-imperialism (together    with some anti-Americanism) of the old Latin American left. Dealing cautiously    with American interests in the world and in the region during its first mandate,    the da Silva government exhibited a more assertive 'anti-hegemonic' stance in    its second mandate, developing (at least rhetorically) some confrontational    positions in relation to American interests in the global scenario; political    conflicts over specific issues were always avoided and direct opposition never    allowed to arise, but a more assertive behavior, connecting Brazil with other    'non-hegemonic' emerging powers, was allowed to develop (in fact, was explicitly    promoted).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Too much transpiration,    less inspiration: Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's diplomacy in action</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Intentions and    proclamations aside, diplomacy under Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva has to    be evaluated according to its concrete results - or lack thereof - in the many    subjects that mobilized the attention of the professional staff of the Foreign    Service, under the triple guidance of the Presidential Assistant, the Minister    and his Secretary-General, with the clear approval and the appreciation of the    President himself. Among those issues, the following protracted the most attention    from all these actors during the period under consideration: the UN Security    Council; alliances with strategic partners; Mercosur and related issues of regional    integration; the relationship with Argentina; Brazil's leadership in South America    and regional blocs; the WTO and multilateral trade negotiations; relations with    other emerging powers and the international role of Brazil. For some of these    issues, the PT already had its own 'policies'; for others, it followed the official    diplomatic line, distorting it for its own purposes.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>The United    Nations Security Council: a long-standing obsession</i></b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Despite a vague    mention related to the "reform of international organizations", the issue was    never a priority in the PT's guidelines on Foreign Policy but it was a pet subject    for the Foreign Minister, who had a long career in multilateral forums and a    personal attraction for international security matters; he transmitted this    interest to the President, who promptly excepted the idea that Brazil was ready    to enter the <i>inner sanctum</i> of the United Nations. This issue is notoriously    difficult, and Brazil engaged vast resources - human, diplomatic, financial    - in lobbying other countries for the purpose of reforming the UN Charter and    enlarging its Security Council. The remarkable degree of acceptance of Luis    In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva by the international media and other world leaders    - all of whom, with the exception of George Bush, invited him to the annual    G8 meetings - convinced the President that the idea was not only feasible but    attainable, despite some opposition from regional partners (most vociferously,    Argentina and Mexico).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Brazilian initiatives    took various forms. With other developing countries, bilateral debt write-offs    were offered to the poorest countries, but sometimes even to oil exporters like    Gabon. With the other candidates (Japan, Germany, and India), a G4 was created    to support one of the proposals put forward by former UN Secretary General Kofi    Annan. Brazil never reached an agreement with two key actors in this process,    USA and China, who continuously opposed any substantial reform of the international    body. For the sake of its great objective, Brazil assumed a commanding role    in the pacification process of Haiti, engaging considerable resources in the    task of nation-building that went clearly beyond the country's traditional participation    in peacekeeping missions. Also, to enhance Brazil's international presence,    the President ordered the opening of permanent embassies in almost all African    countries and in all the Latin American states, even in the smallest islands    of the Caribbean, all with very limited results in practice. Despite rhetorical    support for his pretention, expressed in many bilateral communiqu&eacute;s along    his mandate, the President was continuously frustrated.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>Alliances    with strategic partners (Argentina, China, India, South Africa)</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Luis In&aacute;cio    Lula da Silva's diplomacy believed that countries such as Brazil, Argentina,    China, South Africa and India not only share common values and the same objectives    in the world system, but also have relatively similar social and economic characteristics,    making them ready to sustain joint projects and efforts at cooperation. IBSA,    or the G-3, for instance, was presented as one example of creativity and shared    vision between three great multiracial democracies, Brazil, India and South    Africa. Having decided to form the group, the three countries struggled hard    to find common problems and to establish a list of 'shared solutions', installing    as many working groups as possible without regard for the actual differences    among. Official rhetoric refers to IBSA as a 'success story', although concrete    results, objectively assessed, remain below expectations, providing more promises    than real accomplishments.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Argentina is another    kind of 'strategic partnership': it was the co-founder of the Southern Cone    integration process, with Mercosur at its core, the consolidation of which would    require that the co-ordination of macroeconomic policies between the two big    associates, as well as a set of joint measures to strengthen the regional bloc,    be placed at the center of that endeavor. Instead, Argentina's behavior in Mercosur    became a hindrance for Brazilian industrialists, as their exports were subjected    to many protectionist restrictions adopted by the Buenos Aires Government, which    was still committed to old national practices in trade and industrial policies.    The da Silva Government not only tolerated such abuses - contrary to the spirit    and to the letter of Mercosur agreements, as well as to WTO-GATT dispositions    on safeguards - but also managed to contain the dissatisfaction of Brazilian    exporters.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">China, for its    part, was previously (and uncritically) selected by the President and the PT    as a strategic ally, and began to benefit from this position by the declaration,    by Brazil, that it filled the requirements of a "market economy", as defined    by WTO rules (and thus able to enjoy the bonuses of this recognition in its    bilateral trade with Brazil). Brazilian diplomacy misread completely the real    will of China in terms of accepting the reform of the UN Charter and the elevation    of Brazil to its long sought ambition to become a permanent member of the Security    Council. Neither were the Chinese ready to make the huge investments in Brazilian    infra-structure that were expected by Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva, as they    actually regarded Brazil as one more commodity provider among many others.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>The dismantling    of Mercosur as an unintended consequence</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The 'restructuring',    institutional consolidation and enlargement of Mercosur were on Lula's diplomatic    menu, as had been explicitly announced since the beginning. According to this    priority, total dedication was devoted to the attraction of new partners - Bolivia,    Chile, Venezuela, and Ecuador - and facilitating their integration into the    bloc (including a waiver on the application of the Common External Tariff, a    clear circumvention of the normal discipline inside a customs union, which is    what Mercosur pretends to be). Besides the creation of a Mercosur Parliament    - without real functions, to be precise - there was no real progresses in the    fields of trade liberalization and economic opening among member countries.    From the designated group of 'candidates', only Hugo Ch&aacute;vez's Venezuela    decided to join the bloc, to the consternation of the real democrats and the    concerns of the business world. Despite a strong lobby exerted by the da Silva    Government in favor of Ch&aacute;vez, the documentation has not yet been concluded,    as Paraguay has still to endorse it.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Irrespective of    the real setbacks in the commercial areas of Mercosur, it is a fact that Brazil    has invested heavily in the project of a stronger Mercosur and its expansion    throughout the region. For instance, Brazil proposed, created and financed,    at 70% of its cost, a fund to "correct the imbalances" in the region, a financial    scheme equivalent to only a small part, 1%, approximately, of the combined Mercosur    member countries' GDPs and that, in fact, duplicates the work of the multilateral    banks already operating in the region - the World Bank, the Inter-American Bank    and other bodies. Instead of reducing imbalances in the region by market-friendly    mechanisms, in line with each country's comparative advantages, governments    allocate money to a vast array of projects poorly managed by bureaucrats and    incapable of correcting any imbalance between them.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As well as an emphasis    on its social and political agenda, Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's big push    towards Mercosur's enlargement was to offer it to whichever countries in South    America would be willing to join, even at the price of overlooking some of its    requirements, simply to accommodate specific countries with strong political    motivations. Bolivia, for instance, was offered the chance to enter Mercosur    without being liable to the Common External Tariff (which was considered an    exaggerated concession by Argentina). Ecuador, along with Bolivia, a member    of the Andean Community of Nations (CAN), was also approached, but preferred    not to be entangled in any new commercial compromise. Chile, bound to a single    tariff, as consolidated in the GATT system, declined from the start to become    a full member of Mercosur, taking into account that it benefits from free-trade    agreements concluded with each of its hemispheric partners. Colombia and Peru,    too, setting aside their CAN membership, opted for free-trade agreements with    the United States, a move that pushed Venezuela's Hugo Ch&aacute;vez to denounce    the country's membership of CAN and to make a pledge to join Mercosur.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">There are two problems    with Ch&aacute;vez's political decision to become a full member of Mercosur:    on the one hand, since 2006, when that option was chosen, he signed, at the    same time, a trilateral pact, with Cuba and Bolivia, creating ALBA, the Bolivarian    Alliance of the Americas, a bizarre integration scheme built around state trading,    managed cooperation and no free trade at all. On the other hand, Venezuela has    never complied with the requirements of Mercosur's customs union - that is,    the Common External Tariff and all other regulations to that effect - declaring    instead that it's intention was to transform Mercosur from its 'neoliberal'    rules to a new political bloc, animated by its own proposals concerning '21st-century    socialism'. Even accounting for the political empathy demonstrated by the two    biggest associates towards Venezuela - in the case of Argentina compounded by    the fact that Hugo Ch&aacute;vez was its sole financier after the 2002 moratorium    - that was a little too far from the modest capitalist, albeit <i>dirigiste</i>,    integration scheme devised by Brazil and Argentina.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>Sleeping    with a restive neighbor: relations with Argentina</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The most sensible,    and relevant, of all bilateral Brazilian relationships, the diplomatic interaction    with Argentina, remains in a delicate situation, despite the benign propensity    of the da Silva Government to accept almost all restrictions and limitations    unilaterally imposed by Buenos Aires on the trade exchanges and reciprocal economic    flows. At the beginning the da Silva and Kirchner mandates, in 2003, the excuse    for many defensive measures was the profound crisis created by the end of the    convertibility exchange regime and the external debt moratorium, followed by    a complete standstill in foreign financing for Argentina. In a second stage,    bruised by the excessive number of initiatives the Brazilian President was taking    to assert Brazil's leadership in the region, Nestor Kirchner hardened Argentinean    positions in many negotiating situations, either in Mercosur or in regional    matters, and even in multilateral situations, such as Brazilian candidacies    in some international organizations (IADB, WTO, and others).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Ego disputes aside,    the most important problem was a special safeguards regime that Argentina sought    to impose on bilateral trade with Brazil, invoking "structural imbalances" arising    from the Brazilian exchange flotation or hidden subsidies on Brazilian exports;    "involuntary" export restrictions and other market arrangements were put in    place, even against Mercosur rules and WTO dispositions, which the Brazilian    President accepted as part of his "diplomacy of generosity" (to the great displeasure    of Brazilian industrialists). In other contexts, Brazil was unable (or was not    accepted) to mediate the conflict between Argentina and Uruguay over the cellulose    plants next to the border. Favorable diplomatic rhetoric apart, Argentina was    never very enthusiastic about Brazilian initiatives in the region: the South    American Community of Nations, the two inter-regional summits - with Arab and    African Countries - the South American Defense Council within Unasur, the Latin    American and Caribbean meetings, and some other initiatives. Above all, though,    the most contentious issue was Brazil's candidacy to the UNSC seat, followed    by its implicit posture as regional leader - two endeavors that affected Argentina    self-esteem and moved her to an openly active opposition.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>Tropical    Man's Burden: Brazil's regional leadership</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">One of the most    important of Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's diplomatic initiatives, along    with the Brazilian candidacy to a permanent seat in the UNSC, is the union of    South America as a political entity, free from any interference from the "American    empire", and this has always corresponded to a permanent project for his party,    obviously supported by its Cuban and other Latin American leftist allies. The    core of Brazilian regional diplomacy, under the direct inspiration of Itamaraty's    Secretary-General, was strongly directed towards this ambitious objective, with    partial successes in various aspects.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The economic aspect    of the project - the political implosion of the American proposal of a FTAA,    followed by the creation of a South American Free Trade Area - was only half-achieved:    the abandonment of a hemispheric trade liberalization scheme. Brazilian initiatives    towards creating its own economic space in the region were downsized to a mosaic    of bilateral agreements within the framework of a Latin American Integration    Association that failed to promote expanded exchanges or to effectively integrate    the economies of the countries. The modest opening of the Brazilian economy    in favor of its neighbors curtailed the Brazilian's grand vision for the continent.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The political components    of the project remained too vague to really unite ten South American States    that harbor different conceptions, sometimes opposed to each other, about political    and economic integration. Unhappily for the Brazilian project, the fact is that    South America became less, not more, integrated during Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva's tenure, and the reason has little to do with external crises or military    dictatorship. Indeed, democracy has progressed in the region, but political    instability remains a crucial factor that explains the differing concepts of    integration, and some of the regional crises. By most accounts, Bolivarianism    and indigenism, arising in Andean countries, have rendered those polities more    instable, socially and politically, and prone to old conceptions of integration,    marked by State-led economic policies, nationalization and a less relevant role    for trade and finance, compared to social and political issues, all of which    was completely at odds with a market-led integration, such as that practiced    in Mercosur.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In addition, the    exercise in 'regional leadership', as tentatively tried by Luis In&aacute;cio    Lula da Silva's diplomacy, was not well received; in fact, it had never been    welcomed in the past, one more reason for professional diplomacy making a taboo    of this difficult concept. Tempted by his warm reception in the world press    and among many political leaders, Lula believed that the time was ripe for Brazil    to assume a more assertive posture based on political dialogue, Brazilian financing    of development projects and a tentative measure to coordinate positions in regional    or multilateral negotiations.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Being the largest    economy in the region, Brazil exerts a natural attraction on neighboring countries,    but that has not been enough to overcome old suspicions about its quasi-imperialistic    behavior in South America, or its supposed desire to impose its own domination    over other countries, replicating, albeit in a less arrogant manner, American    imperial tutelage. In fact, Brazil has never exerted any guardianship over the    region, but the multiplication of initiatives could be seen as devoid of vested    interests. That could be one of the reasons for Andean countries not accepting    the offer by Brazilian diplomacy to set up a secretariat for the newly-created    South American Community of Nations, an entity that was replaced, one year later    by the Hugo Ch&aacute;vez-sponsored Union of the Nations of South America (Unasur),    with its headquarters in Quito.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The da Silva Government    also failed to provide an adequate substitute to a scheme devised by Cardoso's    administration for the infrastructure projects in South America. The Initiative    for the Integration of South America (IIRSA), created in 2000, never advanced    from its stage of portfolio projects - prepared by the INTAL-IADB - to transform    them into concrete undertakings capable of mobilizing private and official financial    resources to deal with the multiple needs in the region in terms of energy,    communications, and major engineering projects (notably in transport). As regards    investments and other market opportunities, the successful implosion of the    FTAA by Brazilian diplomacy (with a little help from Argentina and Venezuela)    may have thrown some countries into the arms of the USA, as Brazil is not really    a powerful replacement solution for economies looking for big flows of direct    investment and access to larger markets, at least not those of the size of the    United States; in the same move, Brazil ended up with less market access and    reduced preferences in its neighbors' markets.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>A bridge    too far: multilateral and regional trade negotiations</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Access to new markets    through multilateral trade negotiations, with small concessions in new areas    - like investments, intellectual property and services - but also in industrial    tariffs, have always been a <i>chasse gard&eacute;e</i> for Itamaraty, preserved    from intrusions by other government agencies. This domestic hegemony was somewhat    contested during Lula's government - especially by Brazilian agricultural producers    competing in world markets, but also other sectors - because of the extreme    politicization of those economic issues practiced since the beginning. Under    the slogan of creating a 'new geography for world trade', Itamaraty aligned    Brazil with other developing countries - always with the aim of presenting a    united front against rich countries - disregarding the fact that some of those    countries (including China and India, two of its strongest 'allies') possessed    in reality interests directly opposed to Brazil's aim in dismantling agriculture    protectionism and high subsidies in the area.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Commercial    G20, created at the Cancun ministerial meeting of the WTO (2003), was presented    as a strong expression of Brazilian leadership in trade negotiations, and as    an 'alternative' to old negotiating schemes, but its internal contradictions    quickly became apparent in subsequent phases and the group was not capable of    overcoming different interests among its members to present a united front in    some crucial issues related to it. For all practical purposes, the offensive    stance of Brazil in those matters was rendered as defensive as the Chinese or    Indian positions, including in non-agricultural market access (NAMA) and in    services, in a time when Brazilian farmers, and even many industrialists, were    disposed to advance further.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In the same areas,    and in other negotiating instances - such as in the framework of trade talks    between Mercosur and the EU - less ambitious positions or a limited disposition    to make concessions in industrial tariffs from partners like Argentina (but    the same applies to India and some other developing countries) curtailed the    possibility for Brazil to reach an acceptable agreement with other developing    countries, thus opening new markets for Brazilian products. The preferential    alliances devised by Itamaraty with other developing countries - which included    'social concerns' and 'interests of less competitive agriculture', or 'family    farms' - added to the hindrances that had been self-inflicted for political    reasons, in addition to the fact that the great expansion for Brazilian exports    in the farming sector is essentially concentrated in the emerging markets, not    in rich countries. In this sense, the 'South-South' policy and the 'new geography    of trade', with all their political bias, were in contradiction to Brazilian    national interests and the country's natural competitive advantages. Asian countries,    for instance, have for a long time been practicing the 'new geography' in expanding    their exports to rich countries in the West.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>Dragons,    elephants and other fauna: Brazil's presence in the world</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">China was designated    an 'ally', or 'strategic partner' even before Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's    coming to power, as he made a political visit to that country in 2001, and was    received with the honors due to an important political leader. At that time,    many of the PT leaders still held the erroneous belief that China was a socialist    economy and a country interested in constituting a 'common front' against the    arrogant rich countries and Western 'imperialism'. When he came to power, Luis    In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva started to put in practice his unilaterally conceived    'Chinese policy', which consisted of great expectations concerning major investments    in Brazil and, especially, a strong political relationship by which both countries    were to influence a big change in world power, reducing the spaces for 'hegemony'    in international politics - a concept used by the Chinese, by the way.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Brazilian's    diplomacy imagined that, by conceding to China the status of a 'market economy',    as requested by the Chinese leadership, it would be possible to capture large-scale    investments and technological cooperation, as well as the most prized reward    sought by the president: China's support for the Brazilian aspiration to a seat    in the UNSC. In other occasions - during reciprocal state visits - the President    even considered the idea of a free-trade agreement between China and Mercosur,    and offered the possibility of replace the payment system in bilateral trade,    starting to use local currencies instead of dollars. Both measures were clearly    in favor of Chinese interests and, thanks to the opposition from entrepreneurs    - alarmed by the destructive potential of low-cost Chinese competition - and    from some more vigilant bureaucrats in the Central Bank, they were not implemented    at all, despite being proposed by the President himself (probably out of <i>na&iuml;vet&eacute;</i>    or simple ignorance of economic matters).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">China never committed    itself to supporting Brazil in its quest for the UNSC seat and has always acted    in its own self-interest, even on strictly bilateral matters; it did not hesitate,    for instance, to impose a trade embargo on the arrival of a Brazilian cargo    of soy beans invoking sanitary measures, when it was simply pushing down the    prices, and this on the eve of one of Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's official    visits to China. In other contexts China makes very clear that it wants to keep    for itself the decision on the desirable pattern for bilateral relations, including    matters pertaining to private investment and a common multilateral agenda (either    in BRIC meetings, or elsewhere).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The creation of    the informal group called BRIC, comprising Brazil, China, India and Russia,    has the latter country as the main partner with Brazil in the endeavor that    looks more at political aims than economic objectives, despite the fact that    the proposal by an investment economist takes its legitimacy from their economic    importance for the future world economy. The new acronym has attracted a lot    of publicity but it remains to be seen if the group has, effectively, coherent,    sound and feasible proposals for global governance, justifying its claim to    be an alternative to the traditional G7-G8 group. In the same way, the decision    to strengthen links with new and old partners, in other continents, fits Luis    In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's intention to diversify the options available for    Brazilian exports, other sources for sophisticated technology - with France,    for instance - and to achieve a balance of commercial objectives and attain    a leading political role for the country in the world (as in the summits organized    with Arab and African countries together with South American neighbors of Brazil).</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">A resident diplomatic    representation was established in Ramallah and Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva    tried to insert himself in the complicated chessboard of Middle East conflicts,    offering to mediate a 'peace' between Israelis and Palestinians on the basis    of 'sincere dialogue', which, of course, arrived at nothing. New attempts at    <i>bona fide</i> diplomacy were made in connection with the troubled negotiations    between the great powers and Iran, over that country's covert activities regarding    its nuclear program, only to characterize Brazil's President as a friend of    the controversial figure of Ahmadinejad. Brazil's too lenient posture regarding    human rights violations around the world, together with Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva's indulgence towards dictators like Fidel Castro, have tarnished the    good record previously held by Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">There is no doubt    that Brazil has become an important broker in many instances on the international    agenda, even if some ambiguities remain over specific points of the political    aspect of the PT's external policy (human rights and democracy being the most    visible, but also non-proliferation and environment). Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva had the opportunity to engage in dialogue at the same time with capitalists    in Davos and the dreamers of the World Social Forum, but many in his immediate    surroundings exhibited a clear anti-American stance, as was revealed, for instance,    in the cases of Honduras and Venezuela. The President's negative appraisals    of 'neoliberalism' and 'Wall Street speculators' have more to do with old-fashioned    leftist postures than with the diplomatic seriousness required from an aspiring    emerging power. At the beginning of his mandate, Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da    Silva attempted to 'sell' to other Latin American countries a replacement of    the 'Washington Consensus', by means of a so-called 'Buenos Aires Consensus',    a fragile set of fragile rules about welfare policies. At the end of his mandate,    had become a strong critic of the current international system, probably frustrated    by the unwillingness of great powers to reform the UNO Charter and accept Brazil    as one of the 'more equals'.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Luis In&aacute;cio    Lula da Silva's heritage: Brazilian diplomacy's new clothes</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The October 2010    presidential elections in Brazil provide the opportunity to change many things    in foreign policy, if there is a social-democratic victory - probably more in    the region, and specifically in connection with Mercosur, than in Brazil's world    role - or, otherwise, a new government can maintain, roughly speaking, the same    lines in diplomacy as followed during the last eight years of the da Silva administration.    Indeed, the PT's foreign policy, though not consensual, is widely accepted by    many sectors of public opinion, mainly in academia and left-wing parties and    movements. It would be more of the same, except for the lack of a colorful president,    who has represented Brazil abroad in a lively manner in times of great changes    in world scenarios.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Some positions    will probably not change, of course: the self-characterization of Brazil as    a developing country, its pretension to be a speaker on behalf of other poor    countries seeking a new economic order, with more justice and fairness being    shown towards those countries, the reduction of the inequalities and imbalances    that still divide the world, the democratization of international politics -    with Brazil standing yet again as a candidate for a permanent seat on the UNSC    - and many other requests of this nature. Strong action against hunger, poverty    and injustices will continue to be high in the agenda, as well as the defense    of sovereignty and states' policies directed to social development.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">South America -    and with the PT, Latin America - will be maintained as the most relevant priority    of Brazilian foreign policy, but in the case of a social-democratic win, exclusive    'South-South' policies will probably be scaled down within the ranks of Itamaraty,    in favor of a more balanced view of cooperation and a more pragmatic position    regarding commercial policies and human rights issues. Multilateralism in economic    and political careers will keep the same importance as always and Itamaraty    will regain some of the spaces it lost to a very activist presidential palace    in the last eight years. There will probably be less presidential diplomacy,    and more 'normal', professional diplomacy, with less travel and visits both    abroad and to Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Changes in or of    style and different emphases apart, Brazil will undoubtedly retain the growing    economic and political importance it attained during Luis In&aacute;cio Lula    da Silva's administration. The new view of Brazil held by foreign countries    has objective grounds: the preservation of economic stability and the steady,    albeit modest, growth rates exhibited by Brazilian economy that its diplomacy    has been able to capitalize upon. China, the current engine of the world economy    became the main Brazil's trading partner in the last year of Luis In&aacute;cio    Lula da Silva's mandate, but it was China that that has contributed most to    Brazilian growth, a growth much more based on the value given to its commodities    than on the diversification and expansion of exported manufactures. In fact,    economic growth in Brazil is perhaps becoming too dependent on China, as was    the case in the past with the Brazilian-American relationship. However, in the    context of the BRIC countries, Brazil has shown the worst growth rate of the    four nations, and has not lost its relative share of the world GDP or the intensity    of its participation in international trade.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Thus, despite Luis    In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's satisfaction with the greater presence of Brazil    in the world, which allows him to enhance his own leading role in building that    position, it would not be wrong to say that this new role derives much more    from a hyperactive diplomacy, based on the strong promotion of the President    himself, than from a real transformation in the objective position of Brazil    in the economic and political scenarios. Growth in nominal GDP as compared to    other countries is, at least in some measure, the result of the currency's appreciation    against the dollar; in the same way, growth in exports reflects the growing    demand from dynamic countries for Brazilian commodities; there is also the expansion    of domestic credit for consumption, even at the risk of a bubble arising from    excessive debt contracted by individuals and families. On a similar topic, the    economic stability granted since Cardoso's administration, and rightfully preserved    by da Silva, together with the size of the domestic market and Brazilian connections    within the framework of Mercosur, are responsible for the huge amounts of foreign    direct investments that have been attracted since then. This relatively benign    scenario will probably be maintained for the next few years, depending on the    main markets for Brazilian products (today tending towards China) and on external    credits from financial markets.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">An overall evaluation    of Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's diplomacy should be able to recognize    its ability to project a dynamic image of Brazil worldwide, helping to make    the country a fully-fledged actor in the forefront of international diplomacy.    Brazil is certainly present in many of the most important discussion bodies    dealing with economic and political issues in the world agenda. Not surprisingly,    the personal figure of da Silva is even more present than the country, which    confirms the real success of his diplomacy in projecting his own image as the    personification of Brazil.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In terms of its    own development though, Brazil is still an emerging country, with many social    deficiencies, economic imbalances, uneven regional progress, and an extremely    problematic public education system; its state institutions and corruption levels    are much more akin to the standard patterns already familiar in developing countries    than with the advanced economies that Brazil is struggling to imitate. Incidentally,    it is worth noting that Brazil could be a full member of the OECD, as it has    received 10 open invitation in recent years to consider becoming associated    with that organization; it was only for ideological and political reasons that    Luis In&aacute;cio Lula da Silva's diplomacy choose to stand aside. Even taking    into account some economic challenges arising from such a decision, OECD patterns    in economic policy and governance would help Brazil to modernize its structures    and improve the overall performance of its public policies.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Indeed, the main    challenges for Brazil in the years ahead are entirely internal, with few, or    none, deriving from external factors. Domestic problems are mainly to blame    for the modest role still characterizing Brazil's world presence; an ambitious    set of governance reforms - the taxation system, labor legislation, political    and administrative reforms, and an educational revolution - most of them in    line with OECD patterns, should contribute to the international aggrandizement    of Brazil. Those tasks will presumably depend on a less ideological type of    governance and on a new kind of diplomacy, open-minded and market-friendly.    This task is for a post-da Silva government.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Received August    14, 2010    <br>   Accepted November 18, 2010</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="back1"></a><a href="#top1">1</a>    Some of the questions debated in this essay have been already dealt with in    other articles by the author, namely: "Brazil in the world context, at the first    decade of the 21<sup>st</sup> century: regional leadership and strategies for    its integration into the world economy", In: Joam Evans (org.), <i>Brazilian    Defense Policies: Current Trends and Regional Implications</i> (London: Dunkling    Books, 2009), p. 11-26; "Lula's Foreign Policy: Regional and Global Strategies",    In: Werner Baer and Joseph Love (eds.), Brazil under Lula (New York: Palgrave-Macmillan,    2009), p. 167-183; "Pol&iacute;tica exterior: potencia regional o actor global",    In: "Brasil Emerge", <i>Vanguardia Dossier</i> (Barcelona: La Vanguardia, n.    36, Jul-Sept., 2010), p. 68-72.    <br>   <a name="back2"></a> <a href="#top2">2</a> Minutes of the regular meetings of    the FSP, since its foundation, in 1990, up to 2007, with evidence of the participation    of the Colombian narco-terrorist group FARC, can be found at this website: <u><a href="http://www.midiasemmascara.org/arquivo/atas-do-foro-de-sao-paulo/7.html" target="_blank">http://www.midiasemmascara.org/arquivo/atas-do-foro-de-sao-paulo/7.html</a></u>    , accessed on 20<sup>th</sup> October 2010.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[ ]]></body>
</article>
