<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0034-7329</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista Brasileira de Política Internacional]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. bras. polít. int.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0034-7329</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Instituto Brasileiro de Relações Internacionais]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0034-73292012000300001</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0034-73292012000300001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Global climate governance and transition to a low-carbon economy: a special issue of RBPI[subtitle]]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Viola]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Eduardo]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Lessa]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Antônio Carlos]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Brasília  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Brasília  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>55</volume>
<numero>spe</numero>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><b><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EDITORIAL</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="4" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Global climate governance and transition to     a low-carbon economy: a special issue of RBPI</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Eduardo Viola<sup>I</sup>; Ant&ocirc;nio Carlos Lessa<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><sup>I</sup>Full   Professor of International Relations at the University of Bras&iacute;lia (UnB) and   Research Fellow of the National Council for Scientific and Technological   Development (CNPq) (<a href="mailto:eduviola@gmail.com">eduviola@gmail.com</a>)<br />   <sup>II</sup>Associate Professor of International Relations at the University of   Bras&iacute;lia, editor of the <i>Brazilian     Journal of International Politics</i> &#150; <i>Revista Brasileira de       Pol&iacute;tica Internacional</i> (RBPI) &#150; and Research Fellow   of the National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)   (<a href="mailto:aclessa@gmail.com">aclessa@gmail.com</a>)</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Brazil may be considered one   of the most important players in defining the great environmental agenda that   involves national governments, the academia, and nongovernmental organizations   (NGOs). This fundamental attribute is better yet noticed within the great   public international debate that develops around issues related to climate   change. At a time in which the United Nations Conference on Sustainable   Development (UNCSD) was held in Rio de Janeiro, called Rio+20, which took place   in June 13&#150;22, 2012, in Rio de Janeiro city, we believe there would be no   better pretext to organize a special edition of the <i>Brazilian Journal of International Politics</i> &#150; <i>Revista Brasileira de     Pol&iacute;tica Internacional</i> (RBPI) &#150; about this grand agenda.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This issue of RBPI is focused on the international   political economy of climate change. All the articles consider climate change   as one of the most relevant and urgent questions faced by humanity and the   international system. Also, they agree about the strong dissonances between the   recognition of the severity of the problem by all countries and the low   effectiveness and slow pace of the international collective action to cope with   it, so far. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">We are grouping the articles in three types. The first   group &#150; four articles &#150; deals with the general dynamic of the international   system on climate change: the limits of climate governance in an international   system under conservative hegemony; the contradictory performance of the G-8   countries; the role of G-77 and BASIC in the multilateral negotiations; and the   conflict between the European Union and all the other major powers on taxation   of global aviation. The second group &#150; four articles &#150; addresses the domestic   and foreign climate policies of key players:   United States of America, China, the European Union and Brazil. Finally, the   third group &#150; one article &#150; focuses in the subnational climate governance:   municipalities in the Brazilian Amazon. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>Climate   governance in an international system under conservative hegemony: the role of   major powers</i> by Viola, Franchini and Ribeiro defines the existence   of eight major powers considering as criteria a high share of global carbon   emissions and the availability of human and technological capital for the   transition to a low-carbon economy: United States, China, European Union,   India, Russia, Brazil, Japan and South Korea. Considering the effective   behavior of the countries in terms of trajectory of carbon emissions and   effective mitigation policies, the article finds a cleavage between the   behavior of conservative countries (Russia and India) and moderate conservative   countries (USA, China and Brazil) from one side and reformist countries   (European Union, South Korea and Japan) from the other side. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>Climate   paradox of the G-8: legal obligations, policy declarations and implementation   gap</i> by Brauch analyzes the trajectory of G-8 countries in relation   to their commitments in the Kyoto Protocol from 1997: relatively homogeneous   for the G-7 and very singular in the case of Russia. The author finds five   countries fulfilling the obligations (Germany, France, United Kingdom, Italy   and Russia) and three countries with an implementation deficit (USA, Canada and   Japan).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>The   G-77, BASIC, and global climate governance: a new era in multilateral   environmental negotiations</i> by Hochstetler analyzes the recent   growing differentiation among Southern countries standing in negotiations,   focusing in the formation of the BASIC coalition in 2009 and its impact in the   traditional G-77 coalition. The major question of the article is whether   differentiation of the South is now strong enough for changing the usefulness of   the North/South framework for understanding climate governance.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>Fighting   climate change in the air: lessons from the EU directive on global aviation</i> by Domingos analyzes an emblematic conflict in the present international   political economy of climate change. The article describes the multiple   dimensions of the conflict and finds three major factors explaining the   situation: more progressive climate policy of the EU, concerns about   competitiveness and legal inconsistence from all other major powers and   perception of unilateral imposition by most countries. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>An   overview of domestic aspects in US climate policy</i> by Ferreira,   Ferreira and Vigevani analyzes domestic climate policy and politics during the   Clinton, Bush and Obama administrations. The article shows increasing   conservatism in domestic politics originated in diverse social and economic   dynamics as a major factor in blocking progress in the international climate   policy of USA and consequently in multilateral international negotiations. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>Dilemma   of choice: China's response to climate change</i> by Hung and Tsai   analyzes various dilemmas faced by the Chinese elites facing responses to   climate change: fast economic growth for consolidating as a new superpower and   eliminating poverty versus the need of avoiding the blame for the stagnation on   climate change negotiations; the fact that China is one of the most threatened   countries by climate change and particularly extreme weather events versus the   temptation that growing faster in the next decade could diminish the   vulnerability of the country when the situation will become worse; the growing   awareness about climate change in the national elites versus the drive to   continuous fast economic growth in the local elites. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>The   European Union as an actor in global climate governance: meeting formal   requirements, playing a role in practice</i> by Pavese and Torney   analyzes the unique role of the European Union in climate negotiations derived   from grouping countries and having shared negotiation powers build up in a very   complex process. The article provides a consistent theoretical framework   related to the elements of actorness (recognition, capability, opportunity, and   cohesion) and through empirical analyses of different historical periods, and   it shows the power and limitations of the European Union as a leader on climate   negotiations. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>The   Brazilian position on forests and climate change from 1997 to 2012: from veto   to proposition</i> by Carvalho analyzes the evolution of the Brazilian   position on forest and climate change since 1997 to 2012, showing how the   defensive and conservative position of Brazil in 1997 suffered a shift in the   second half of the 2000s because of a combination of dramatic reduction in   deforestation in the Amazon and changes in the relative force of domestic   actors. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The article <i>Governance   of global climate change in the Brazilian Amazon: the case of Amazonian   municipalities in Brazil</i> by Inoue compares two dynamics in climate   governance in Amazonian municipalities. The first one, top-down, has involved   multiple actors and has been effective in reducing deforestation, but the   municipalities have not had the capacity of shaping the outcome. In the second   dynamic, bottom-up, which has also been effective and involved multiple actors,   the municipalities have had the capacity of influencing the process more in   correspondence with their particular situation and mindset. Inoue's article   analyzing the dynamic of deforestation in the local level is fully convergent   with Carvalho's focused in the national level. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">There are major convergences among all the articles in   the many aspects that addressed the same or similar issues. There is only one   divergence, between Viola, Franchini and Ribeiro's article and Brauch's, in the   assessment of the performance of Russia and Japan in their trajectory of   emissions and general government behaviors because of the different conceptual   frameworks used by both. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This special edition is the result of a major   international call, launched in October 2011. We were really pleased with the   wide reception and repercussion that our initiative had, and we hope this   historical edition of RBPI really contributes for the high-level reflection on   the theme of climate change economics.</font></p>      ]]></body>
</article>
