<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0034-7329</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista Brasileira de Política Internacional]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. bras. polít. int.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0034-7329</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Instituto Brasileiro de Relações Internacionais]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0034-73292012000300008</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0034-73292012000300008</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The contribution of the European Union to global climate change governance: explaining the conditions for EU actorness]]></article-title>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[A contribuição da União Europeia à governança da mudança climática global: explicando as condições para a actorness da UE]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Pavese]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Carolina B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Torney]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Diarmuid]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,London School of Economics and Political Science Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Oxford  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>55</volume>
<numero>spe</numero>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<lpage>143</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300008&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300008&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0034-73292012000300008&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[As a regional organization, the European Union's role in global climate governance faces constraints that do not apply to other members of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) and Kyoto Protocol. Addressing that uniqueness, this article provides a theoretical and empirical analysis of how the elements of actorness (recognition, capability, opportunity and cohesion) shape the EU's engagement with the international climate change regime.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Como organização regional, o papel da União Europeia na governança global do clima enfrenta obstáculos que não se aplicam a nenhuma outra parte da Convenção-Quadro das Nações Unidas sobre a Mudança do Clima (CQNUMC) e do Protocolo de Quioto. Avaliando essa singularidade, este artigo fornece uma analise teórica e empírica de como os elementos de actorness (reconhecimento, capacidade, oportunidade e coesão) definem a participação da UE no regime internacional de mudanças climáticas.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[actorness]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[climate change]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[European Union]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[actorness]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[mudança climática]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[União Europeia]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><b><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">ARTICLE</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="4" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>The contribution of the European Union to global climate   change governance: explaining the conditions for EU <i>actorness</i></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>A contribui&ccedil;&atilde;o da Uni&atilde;o Europeia &agrave; governan&ccedil;a     da mudan&ccedil;a clim&aacute;tica global: explicando as condi&ccedil;&otilde;es     para a actorness   da UE</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Carolina B. Pavese<sup>I</sup>; Diarmuid Torney<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><sup>I</sup>PhD   Candidate in International Relations and Research Assistant at the Grantham   Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment, the London School of   Economics and Political Science. The author would like to thank the   Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (CAPES) for the   financial support to her doctoral studies (<a href="mailto:c.boniatti-pavese@lse.ac.uk">c.boniatti-pavese@lse.ac.uk</a>)<br />   <sup>II</sup>PhD in International Relations, University of Oxford. During the   writing of this article, Diarmuid Torney was a postdoctoral fellow at the   Kolleg-Forschergruppe (KFG) "The Transformative Power of Europe," hosted at the   Freie Universit&auml;t Berlin. He is particularly grateful to Thomas Risse and Tanja   B&ouml;rzel (<a href="mailto:diarmuidtorney@gmail.com">diarmuidtorney@gmail.com</a>)</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">As a regional organization, the European Union's   role in global climate governance faces constraints that do not apply to other   members of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC)   and Kyoto Protocol. Addressing that uniqueness, this article provides a   theoretical and empirical analysis of how the elements of actorness   (recognition, capability, opportunity and cohesion) shape the EU's engagement   with the international climate change regime.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Keywords:</b> actorness; climate change; European Union.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Como organiza&ccedil;&atilde;o regional, o papel da Uni&atilde;o   Europeia na governan&ccedil;a global do clima enfrenta obst&aacute;culos que n&atilde;o se aplicam a   nenhuma outra parte da Conven&ccedil;&atilde;o-Quadro das Na&ccedil;&otilde;es Unidas sobre a Mudan&ccedil;a do   Clima (CQNUMC) e do Protocolo de Quioto. Avaliando essa singularidade, este   artigo fornece uma analise te&oacute;rica e emp&iacute;rica de como os elementos de <i>actorness</i> (reconhecimento, capacidade, oportunidade e coes&atilde;o) definem a participa&ccedil;&atilde;o da   UE no regime internacional de mudan&ccedil;as clim&aacute;ticas.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Palavras-chave:</b> actorness; mudan&ccedil;a clim&aacute;tica; Uni&atilde;o Europeia.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Introduction</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">From an early stage, the European Union (EU) has   played what has often been considered a leadership role in global climate   governance, pushing for ambitious international commitments. Yet, as the only   regional organization member of the United Nations Framework Convention on   Climate Change (UNFCCC) and the Kyoto Protocol (KP), the EU can be considered a   sui generis international climate actor. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Sharing competences on climate politics with its   member states, the EU's presence in the international climate regime does not   replace but rather complements that of its 27 members. As a result, the EU's   identity and role in the regime faces constraints that do not apply to any   other party. Understanding EU engagement with global climate governance   requires, therefore, considering the singular nature of EU's identity as an   international actor, or <i>actorness</i>.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This article assesses the EU as an actor in the case   of the international climate change regime, and is divided into three core   parts. First, the article presents a brief overview of theoretical discussions   on <i>actorness</i> that set the ground for this study. Second, the article explores two formal   requirements for <i>actorness</i>,   namely, external recognition and capability. It looks at the EU's membership of   the UNFCCC and the KP and seeks to identify how the EU's status as the sole   regional organization member of this regime affects formal external recognition   of the EU as part of global climate governance. Next, considering capability as   legal competences and institutional settings, the article assesses the power   invested in the EU to act over climate issues. Identifying the strong   intergovernmental nature of EU external climate policy, we then explore how   this impacts the dynamics of internal decision-making process, and the external   representation of the EU.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The final part of the article focuses on the aspects   we claim influence EU's identity as an actor in practice: cohesion and   opportunity. Analyzing the EU's engagement with the development of the   international climate regime from the adoption of the Kyoto Protocol to   Conference of the Parties 17 (COP-17) in Durban in 2012, we identify how the   degree of external opportunity and the level of internal coherence have varied   over time. The overall conclusion of the article points to a limited degree of   formal conditions for <i>actorness</i> and an irregular pattern of opportunity and cohesion. Nevertheless, this   article reveals that the EU has been able to overcome these constrains to a   large extent, thus affirming its identity as an international climate actor.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>The EU as an actor in   global climate governance:     a theoretical overview</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The first attempt to formulate a theoretical framework   for analyzing the EU's condition as an international actor dates back to the   pioneering work of Sj&ouml;stedt, which recognized the European Community (EC) as "a   genuine actor in the international actor" but claimed that the degree of a<i>ctorness</i> can vary   according to the capability to deliver as an actor in each issue-area (Sj&ouml;stedt   1977, 4). Building on this work, Bretherton and Vogler (2006) argued that,   rather than being a given and well-established attribute, the EU's condition as   an actor emerges from an ongoing process and results from the interaction of a   complex set of factors of internal and external nature, namely,   (i) opportunity, (ii) presence, and (iii) capability.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Opportunity</b> reflects the external structural context that creates the environment in which   the EU can perform as an international actor &#150; or not. Adopting a   constructivist approach, the authors then consider as opportunity ideas,   perceptions, and events that favor EU <i>actorness</i>,   going beyond a focus on material conditions. The second element, <b>presence</b>, is defined as   the ability of the EU to benefit from this opportunity not only to project its   existence in the international arena, but also to exert external influence. <b>Capability</b> is established by   internal conditions, and refers to the delegation of competences and the set of   political instruments for EU external policies. It is underpinned by a certain   degree of domestic legitimacy of EU action in combination with the shared   understanding of the EU's ability to transform opportunities into valuable   circumstances to project its presence in the international scene (Bretherton   and Vogler 2006). As an evolving entity, the presence of the EU in the   international scene varies in terms of degree and form, according to the   issue-area at stake. Consequently, EU <i>actorness</i> cannot be expressed in a single and comprehensive definition; it requires a   case-by-case assessment.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Taking a somewhat different approach, Jupille and   Caporaso (1998) posit a theoretical framework to measure the degree in which   the EU could be understood as an actor. According to their model, <i>actorness </i>comprises four   components: (i) recognition, (ii) authority, (iii) autonomy, and   (iv) cohesion. <b>Recognition</b> can be considered as a pre-condition for an actor's existence as it refers to   the external acceptance by third parties of an actor's participation in world   politics. The acknowledgement of this international presence can be de jure or   de facto. That is to say <i>actorness </i>does not necessarily imply recognition formalized by diplomatic   means or international law &#150; it could also be determined in practice. The   second criterion, <b>authority</b>, entails   internal delegation of competence to an entity to perform in a given political   area as an actor. <b>Autonomy</b>,   the third element of <i>actorness</i>,   corresponds to the institutional distinctiveness that makes the performance of   an entity independent from that of its members. Finally, <b>cohesion</b> means ability to   formulate and deliver policy preferences consistently between the entity and   its member states.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Applying these analytical tools to measure EU <i>actorness</i> in   environmental regimes, Jupille and Caporaso concluded that the EU does have a   significant degree of <i>actorness</i> that favors its presence in the international arena. Fulfilling the criterion   of external recognition, the member states invest some authority in the EU to   perform as an international actor within these regimes. However, constrains   over the EU's ability to deliver cohesion and autonomy underpin the prospects   for a fully-fledged <i>actorness </i>within environmental regimes (Jupille and Caporaso 1998, 214&#150;24).</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Jupille and Caporaso's framework covers many important   characteristics of actorness, but has limitations. Firstly, it is not the   outcome of an in-depth analysis; secondly, nor are they applied to a specific   regime part of the constellations of issues under the domain of environmental   politics. Finally, these arguments were postulated in the late 1990s &#150; arguably   when environmental regimes were in an early stage of development. In the past 20   years certainly much has changed not only in terms of the dynamics of these   regimes, but also on the EU's capacity vis-&agrave;-vis the four criteria of <i>actorness</i> presented by   Jupille and Caporaso, and other scholars have more recently attempted to update   and extend their analysis.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Considering the contributions and limitations of these   approaches to <i>actorness</i>,   this article builds on the existing literature and provides a theoretical and   empirical account of the EU's identity in the specific domain of climate change.   When selecting the criteria (or components) of <i>actorness </i>to be analyzed, the article   borrows two elements of Bretherton and Vogler's approach, capability and   opportunity, and two factors postulated by Jupille and Caporaso, recognition   and cohesion.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The section that follows addresses the legal and   institutional elements that provide the basis for the EU's identity as an   international actor: recognition and capability.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Assessing formal   requirements for EU actorness:     recognition and capability</b></font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU membership of the   international climate regime:     the question of recognition</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The UN climate regime does not limit membership to   nation-states. Rather, it allows the so-called Regional Economic Integration   Organizations (REIOs) &#150; like the EU &#150; to take part in their framework under   essentially the same terms as states (UNFCCC, Article 22). In terms of   commitments, the UNFCCC declares that the responsibilities of REIOs cannot   overlap that of its member states. Therefore, REIOs are bound to fully comply   with agreements only when their participation in the regime replaces that of   any of its member states. In the circumstances in which both REIO and its   members join the regime, there should be a distribution of responsibilities   among them and "the organization and the member States shall not be entitled to   exercise rights under the Convention concurrently." Moreover, when that is the   case, the REIOs should inform other parties of the scope of its competences   over the matters addressed by the Convention (Article 22).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Having both the European Community and its 12 member   states, at the time, signed the UNFCCC, EU engagement with the international   climate regime falls into this latter category, i.e. they have what can be   considered shared membership.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Another peculiarity of EU membership to the UNFCCC   regards its voting rights. As defined by Article 18, a REIO cannot vote when   its member states are exercising their voting rights, and vice-versa. Should a   regional organization vote on behalf of their members, they have the same   number of votes corresponding to their member states part to the UNFCCC (UNFCCC   1992). Hence, even if considered a fully-fledged member to the climate regime,   the EU has restricted voting powers. In practice, this formal restriction on   voting rights that grants the EU a treatment different from that of other   parties (states) has no relevance for EU participation on climate negotiations,   as agreements have always been promoted by consensus among the parties, and   rules for voting have never been defined.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This "shared system" of representation has also   reflected on the group position the EU occupies in terms of the Annexes of the   UNFCCC and Kyoto Protocol, as well as on negotiating coalitions. The EU and 25   of its member states are included in the Annex I of the UNFCCC, the exceptions   being Malta and Cyprus. Yet, only the first 15 countries to adhere to the EU,   known as "the old members," and the Community feature in the Annex II;   considered as economies in transition (EIT), the latest 12 states that joined the   EU in the enlargement processes of 2004 and 2007 are excluded from this list.   Finally, the EU and all its members are part of the Annex B of the Kyoto   Protocol, being subjected to emission reduction targets.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">In terms of negotiating groups in climate negotiations,   the EU constitutes a group in itself, which stresses the need for internal   cohesion. Partially reflecting this condition, the EU has taken unilateral   actions in many rounds of the negotiations, reinforcing the view of the EU as a   group in itself. Nevertheless, as the next section of this article further   explores, the EU has had a mixed approach to negotiations, forming coalitions   with different groups and/or bilateral alliances with other parties, on a   circumstantial basis.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Overall, it can be concluded that the EU is formally   recognized as an actor in the international climate regime. Furthermore, in   addition to this de jure recognition, the fact that the other parties do pursue   engagement with the EU within negotiations supports the claim of a de facto   recognition. Having external acceptance, the EU meets the first pre-condition   for its <i>actorness</i>.</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU external climate policy: the question of capability</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Having external recognition means that the EU is   allowed to take part in the international climate regime, sharing a space that   would otherwise be exclusive to states. But does the EU have internal   capability to pursue its role as an actor part of the in regime?</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">As a second formal requirement for EU <i>actorness</i>, capability is   here understood as the delegation of competences and the institutional   framework that legitimizes and provides the tools for the EU's action at the   international arena as an actor per se. In order to assess the EU's capability   in the realm of external climate politics, the next section breaks this concept   into different elements. The analysis that follows first scrutinizes the EU's   legal competences, and explores the internal decision-making process of EU   external climate policy. Second, we then assess the EU's external representation   at the multilateral level.</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Legal competences and   decision-making</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The EU can act in areas in which it has legal   competences delegated by member states under treaty provisions. The degree of   power invested in the EU varies according to the issue, as competences can be   exclusive or shared.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">For a small number of areas, the EU has exclusive   competence to adopt legally-binding acts, whereas member states can no longer   legislate on these matters and must comply with EU legislation &#91;Article 2 (1)   Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union&#93;. An example of exclusive EU   competence is the Common Commercial Policy, which implies not only the setting   of EU regulations over internal trade activities, but also a common EU external   trade policy that must be endorsed by all member states. Hence, even if the EU   and its 27 member states are part of the international trade regime &#150; more   specifically the World Trade Organization (WTO) &#150;, they cannot adopt an   individual approach at the multilateral level and must follow the EU's   position.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU legal competences over trade contrast with its   power on environmental issues. Although the EU is recognized as a fully-fledged   actor within the climate regime, sharing the same status as states, climate   change is not an area of exclusive competence. As defined by Article 4 (2e) of   the Treaty on the European Union, competences in the field of the environment   are shared<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1" title=""><sup>1</sup></a> between the member states and the EU.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Hence, EU engagement within the international climate   regime does not replace legal commitments undertaken individually by member   states &#150; rather it complements their participation. Consequently, compliance   with these agreements is also a shared responsibility.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2" title=""><sup>2</sup></a> Once   ratified, mixed agreements become part of Community law, and the implementation   and observation of the international obligations set by these accords fall   under the legal jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice (Tabau and   Maljean-Dubois 2010, 750). That is to say, in areas of shared competence the EU   has limited power to act, and member states can still legislate as long as   there is no EU legal act on the matter.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">As a result of this legal framework, both the EU and   its 27 member states are part of the climate regime, and are not only entitled   to take part in international negotiations, but can, in principle, represent   their own interests at the multilateral level (van Schaik 2010). Finally, as   Delreux (2006, 244) contends, the EU needs to articulate a common position with   its member states prior to international negotiations. The EU's mandate to act   within these multilateral instances becomes limited to positions internally   agreed. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The process of articulating this agreed position is   negotiated in advance of each UNFCCC meeting, and consists of a number of   steps. Negotiations on a common EU position start with debate at a technical   level led by the relevant Council working group, namely the Working Party on   International Environmental Issues &#150; Climate Change (WPIEI-CC). The conclusions   of these activities are taken to the Committee of Permanent Representatives &#150; Comit&eacute; des Repr&eacute;sentants Permanents (COREPER). Once the COREPER   has deliberated on the conclusions of the WPIEI-CC, it passes its   recommendations to the Council of Ministers, meeting in its Environmental   configuration. At this third stage, ministers from the 27 EU member states hold   a last round of debate, adopting a final position by consensus.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">In recent years, climate change has become a more   politicized issue within the EU agenda, leading to an increased engagement of   the European Council in the decision-making of EU external climate policy.   Thus, a fourth stage can be added to this process, with the European Council   giving an extra input on some core &#150; and more political &#150; decisions regarding   the EU's common position in this field (Schunz 2012, 206). The result of this   process within the Council is a mandate for the EU to negotiate at the   multilateral level.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Overall, the definition of climate change as an area   of shared competence implies limited legal capability for EU<i> actorness</i> in global   climate governance. Moreover, this sharing of responsibilities with member   states reflects directly on the policymaking of EU external climate policy, as   its strong intergovernmental nature denotes. Nonetheless, this limited scope   for action does not prevent the EU from formulating its own approach to climate   regime independently of its member states. But what are the implications of   this shared competence status to EU representation at the multilateral level?   In other words, can the EU speak as a single international actor?</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU representation at the   multilateral level</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Up to the entry into force of the Lisbon Treaty, on   December 1, 2009, the EU's negotiating delegation at the international climate   regime was formed by the "troika," composed by the European Commission, the   Presidency of the European Council, and the incoming Presidency of the Council   (Delreux 2011, 17&#150;25). In 1996, the Commission formally requested a negotiating   mandate from the Council, which was firmly rejected by the Council. This mixed   system of representation has been managed with certain flexibility, enabling   the EU to improve coordination and capacity to respond to negotiations. Over   the past decade, the EU has emphasized the role of experts in the working   groups of the Council, thus enhancing their participation in the deliberation   of negotiation positions (Oberth&uuml;r and Roche Kelly 2008, 38). Since 2004, a   system of "issue leader" and "lead negotiations" has been in place. Consisting   of experts from the Commission and several member states, these two groups have   been in charge of representing the EU on the various multilateral negotiation   groups that address specific issues of the climate regime (Oberth&uuml;r and Roche   Kelly 2008, 38).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The Lisbon Treaty brought significant changes to the   EU institutional setting, most prominently through the establishment of a   permanent presidency for the European Council, the creation of the European   External Action Service (EEAS), and the decision that a Vice-President of the   Commission should also perform the role of the new post of High Representative   of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security. Adding to this picture, Article   17 of the Lisbon Treaty establishes that "with the exception of the common   foreign and security policy, and other cases provided for in the Treaties, it   &#91;the European Commission&#93; shall ensure the Union's representation." Without   further specifying, this provision creates legal basis for the Commission to   exert a leading role in EU external representation in multilateral climate   negotiations. However, being climate change an area of shared competence and of   high profile in the EU's agenda, the Commission's mandate never materialized.   Rather, member states vehemently insisted in maintaining the inter-governmental   nature of EU representation.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">In 2010, the Spanish Presidency of the Council broke a   deal on EU representation in the post-Lisbon context, establishing that both   the Commission and the Presidency of the Council had the mandate to speak on   behalf of the EU, whereas internal coordination remains as a responsibility of   the Presidency (Emerson et al. 2011, 83).The degree in which these recent   changes have contributed to EU <i>actorness</i> within the international climate regime, in terms of external representation   and internal decision-making, remains dubious. For Barnes (2010, 56&#150;57), the   Lisbon Treaty enhanced the role of the Commission in the development of EU   external climate policy, and also the prospects of EU cooperation with other   partners on this realm (Barnes 2010, 56&#150;57). However, the tortuous path for the   implementation of these institutional changes and the wide room for   interpretation of the Treaty provisions have hindered the policymaking of EU   external policies (Kaczy&#324;ski   2011).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The analysis of the two formal criteria for <i>actorness </i>conducted in   this section supports the claim that the EU does have external recognition, and   institutional and legal basis for <i>actorness</i> in the international climate regime. Meeting the two prerequisites to <i>actorness </i>does not imply   the EU actually delivers this <i>actorness</i>.   Hence, having recognition and capability, the performance of the EU as an actor   on global climate governance depends on two contextual elements: opportunity   and cohesion. The next section scrutinizes these issues, providing an account   of EU engagement on climate negotiations over the past decades.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Assessing EU actorness   in practice: the questions of cohesion     and external opportunity</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Having analyzed the formal components of EU <i>actorness</i> &#150; recognition   and capability &#150;, this section examines EU <i>actorness</i> in practice. As well as being dependent on formal characteristics discussed, EU <i>actorness</i> also   depends on the degree of EU internal cohesion, and on the external opportunity   structure of world politics. The analysis below draws out these two themes and   explores how they have each varied over time since the mid-1990s. The aim is to   trace the broad trajectory of European policymaking and to draw out how this   has been a function of both the external opportunity structure and internal   cohesion.</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Target-setting and regime-building: the 1990s</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">For most of the 1990s, EU climate policymaking was   marked by a lack of cohesion. This is illustrated by the fact that efforts to   formulate EU climate change policies during the 1990s were, for the most part,   unsuccessful. The "flagship" policy proposal from the Commission, a   carbon/energy tax, was rejected by the Council of Ministers in 1992 and there   was little effort by way of internal policy development during the rest of the   1990s. However, the external opportunity structure at that time was broadly   favorable. The end of the Cold War ushered in a new period of optimism in world   politics, with hopes for a new liberal world order and enhanced possibilities   for multilateral cooperation. Furthermore, there was increasing evidence that   the US would not assume the kind of global leadership on environmental issues   which it had undertaken in the 1970s and 1980s. This created a leadership   vacuum on the climate issue.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This favorable external opportunity structure explains   to a large extent the EU's success in shaping the international climate regime   during the 1990s. The EU played a significant role in setting the outcome of   negotiations on the UNFCCC, securing US participation in an agreement that   differed significantly from the US position entering the negotiations in   1990&#150;1991. However, this success was not reflective of EU <i>actorness</i> as such<i>.</i> During the final   negotiations in 1992, the crucial compromise deal with the US was struck not by   Portugal, the country holding the EU Presidency at the time, but rather by the   UK acting to some extent independently of the broader EU effort (Haigh 1996).</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The next phase of climate regime-building culminated   in agreement on the KP. In March 1997, in preparation for the upcoming Kyoto   conference later that year, EU heads of state proposed that, as part of a   global agreement, industrialized countries should reduce their emissions of the   three main greenhouse gases (CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub>, and N<sub>2</sub>O)   by 15% relative to 1990 levels by 2010. They also agreed on how to divide up an   overall EU target among the member states. Significantly, however, under this   "burden-sharing" agreement, the sum of member state targets in fact only added   up to roughly a 9.2% reduction (Oberth&uuml;r and Ott 1999, 67). Therefore, while   there was superficial EU cohesion regarding this pre-Kyoto EU target, the EU   effort was not underpinned by a deeper cohesion on how the EU and its member   states would achieve this target. This reflects the fact that member states   were deeply divided with respect to the priority they attached to combating   climate change.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Nonetheless, the EU had some success in shaping the   results of the Kyoto negotiations. The EU's main priority was to secure the   participation of other industrialized countries in a legally-binding agreement   with specific targets for each country. In this, the EU was successful: the KP   set binding emission reduction or limitation targets relative to 1990 levels   for Annex I Parties. However, the EU was forced to make several key concessions   to the US on significant aspects of the Protocol design (Jordan and Rayner   2010, 65). One of the most significant issues in this regard was the inclusion   of provisions for the so-called "flexibility mechanisms": the Clean Development   Mechanism (CDM), Joint Implementation (JI), and Emission Trading. These   concessions secured the agreement of the US delegation at Kyoto but stored up   problems for the future, since the Clinton Administration in the US had no real   chance of securing Congressional ratification of the KP.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Operationalizing the Kyoto Protocol &#150; in particular   the flexible mechanisms and the compliance procedures &#150; was undertaken at the   UNFCCC negotiations over the following years. This process was due to be   concluded at COP-6 in The Hague in November 2000. However, these negotiations   were characterized by strong conflict between the EU and the US, and by a   significant lack of EU cohesion. On the final night of COP-6, the negotiations   broke down spectacularly (Grubb and Yamin 2001, 261). UK Deputy Prime Minister   John Prescott and French minister Dominique Voynet, as part of the EU Troika,   initiated bilateral consultations with the US delegation while the COP was   still meeting in plenary session. The EU Troika agreed a provisional deal on   some issues with the US delegation, only to have it rejected by the larger EU   group, reportedly led by Germany and Denmark (Rajamani 2006, 186&#150;87). On the   day after the negotiations were scheduled to conclude, COP-6 was suspended   until May or June 2001.</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The EU response to US unilateralism: 2001&#150;2005</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Entering the 21<sup>st</sup> century, EU internal   cohesion was boosted significantly by a change in the external opportunity   structure. Arguably the most significant event in this regard in the early   years of the 21<sup>st</sup> century was the decision taken by the Bush   Administration in March 2001 not to submit the Kyoto Protocol to Congress for   ratification. The US decision to withdraw from the Protocol widened the window   of opportunity for the EU at the international level, and also had a catalytic   impact on EU internal cohesion.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">In response to the US move, EU heads of state affirmed   their commitment to the existing climate regime by taking a decision at the   European Council in June 2001 to proceed with ratification of the Protocol in   the absence of US support (European Council 2001). More broadly, the increasing   US turn to unilateralism on climate change served to transform climate change   from a sectoral policy into an issue of high politics and a core element of   European identity. This transformation had a significant impact on domestic   political coalitions within the EU. It strengthened the relative influence of   those with a strong commitment to combating climate change by increasing the   political appeal of leading the international climate negotiations and   developing strong internal climate policies (Costa 2008, 537). This resulted in   increasing internal EU cohesion with respect to climate policymaking.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Around this time, another narrative began to take hold   over the climate issue in Europe, driven particularly by the German and UK   governments. Action to combat climate change was framed increasingly in terms   of economic opportunities that would be generated as a result (Rayner and   Jordan 2010, 102). This reconceptualization of the issue was reflected in the   conclusions of the EU Council of Ministers as well. In contrast to the 1990s,   when it merely acknowledged that action was technically and economically   possible, from 2000 onwards, European governments began to pay more attention   to the economic benefits associated with combating climate change (Oberth&uuml;r and   Dupont 2010, 86&#150;87).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">These factors combined to generate increasing internal   cohesion among EU member states. The centerpiece of EU policymaking during this   period was the EU Emissions Trading Scheme (EU-ETS). The decision to move   forward with emissions trading represented a significant departure for the EU,   since the EU strongly opposed the so-called flexible mechanisms during the   Kyoto negotiations, and was driven significantly by the European Commission   (Skj&aelig;rseth and Wettestad 2007). Despite initial resistance from Germany and   watering down by other member states, the EU Emissions Trading Directive   (2003/87/EC) was adopted in 2003, which set caps on the emissions of large installations   accounting for approximately 40% of total EU emissions. There was also a strong   external dimension to the EU-ETS, brought about by the decision to "link" the   EU-ETS to the other two flexible mechanisms of the Kyoto Protocol &#150; the CDM and   the JI. The EU-ETS, and market mechanisms more generally, became an   increasingly central aspect of the EU's approach to international cooperation   on climate change during the following years. Creating a "global carbon market"   formed an important part of the EU strategy for the negotiations on a post-2012   regime (Council of the European Union 2009).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This growing internal cohesion and deepening domestic   policymaking combined with a favorable external opportunity structure to   generate enhanced EU international <i>actorness</i>.   At the international level, EU attention in the early years of the 21<sup>st</sup> century focused on securing entry into force of the Kyoto Protocol. US   withdrawal from Kyoto in early 2001 not only galvanized European support for   the protocol; it also left the stage clear for the EU to drive forward the   process of operationalizing the Protocol. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Following failure in The Hague in December 2000,   negotiations resumed in very different circumstances in Bonn in July 2001. In   these discussions, the EU sought to defend the "environmental integrity" of the   KP. However, other industrialized countries resisted and, under the agreement   reached, the actual reduction would only be approximately 2.5% as opposed to   the 5.2% reduction set out in the Protocol text (Ott 2001, 470). Nonetheless,   reaching this level of agreement was an achievement, given what had gone   before. The Marrakech Accords, which operationalized the Kyoto Protocol, were   agreed at COP-7 in Marrakech in October&#150;November 2001. The success of these   negotiations was due in part to the increasing <i>actorness</i> of the EU.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Following the agreement at Marrakech, EU attention   turned to securing entry into force of the Protocol. In order for this to   occur, the Protocol had to be ratified by countries representing at least 55%   of 1990 emissions of Annex I Parties. Since the US had withdrawn, the EU had to   secure the ratification of the other industrialized countries with significant   emissions, including Canada, Japan, and the Russian Federation. The Russian   Federation, which accounted for 17.3% of Annex I emissions in 1990, proved to   be the most reticent. However, in late 2004 the EU brokered an informal deal   with the Russian government under which the EU supported Russia's entry into   the World Trade Organization in return for Russian ratification of the Kyoto   Protocol (Damro 2006).</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Domestic success and international failure: 2006&#150;2009</font></h5>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The period from 2006 to 2009 was marked by growing   internal EU cohesion with respect to climate change, but also by a much less   favorable external opportunity structure for EU international <i>actorness</i>. Increased EU   cohesion was underpinned by a number of factors. First, public concern   regarding climate change increased significantly during this period. This built   on growing scientific evidence which was synthesized in the Fourth Assessment   Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), released in   November 2007 (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change 2007). While the   growth of knowledge and understanding of climate change was not, of course,   purely &#150; or even predominantly &#150; a European phenomenon; European public opinion   was particularly receptive to this message. For example, a November 2009 <i>Eurobarometer</i> opinion   survey found that 63% of Europeans considered climate change a very serious   problem, 24% considered it a fairly serious problem, and only 10% did not   consider it a serious problem (European Commission 2009, 15).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Second, the economic case for taking action to combat   climate change continued to be emphasized and strengthened by European   governments. One of the most significant contributions in this regard was the <i>Stern Review</i>,   commissioned by the UK government, which made the case that the short-term   costs of mitigating climate change would be significantly less than the longer-term   costs of inaction, and that action to mitigate greenhouse gas emissions should   begin straight away (Stern 2006). Separately, the European Commission succeeded   in linking the development of EU climate policy with a concern for Europe's   energy security in the medium term (Adelle et al. 2009).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Third, a crisis in European integration in the   mid-2000s provided another stimulus for EU climate policy. In 2005, the   electorates of France and the Netherlands voted to reject a proposed EU   Constitutional Treaty, which would have created a constitutional document for   the EU. The resulting fallout created a political opportunity for climate   policy. It became politically almost impossible to continue discussions on   further EU institutional reform, which led to a search for more concrete   projects where Brussels could show its ability to solve pressing cross-border   policy problems. Thus, climate change had become "a savior issue for the EU   itself" (van Schaik 2010).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This combination of factors underpinned increasing EU   cohesion with respect to climate policymaking in the latter half of the 2000s.   Against this background, EU heads of state agreed in March 2007 to set climate   change targets for the period to 2020, as well as targets for energy   consumption, renewable energy, and biofuels in transport fuels (European   Council 2007). Building on a proposal from the European Commission in January   2008, a Climate and Energy Package was negotiated throughout 2008 by member states.   A final agreement was brokered by French President Nicolas Sarkozy at the   December 2008 European Council meeting, though member states succeeded in   weakening the Commission's original package in several respects (Oberth&uuml;r and   Dupont 2010, 83).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The EU's 2020 climate targets and the Climate and   Energy Package were framed explicitly as Europe's contribution to a post-2012   climate regime. However, despite this increased internal cohesion with respect   to domestic policymaking, the international efforts of the EU had limited   impact on the climate change negotiations in the period leading up to COP-15 in   Copenhagen. In these negotiations, the EU pushed for a strong international   agreement with binding targets for national emissions reductions, a timetable   according to which those targets would have to be met, and robust enforcement   and compliance mechanisms. Nonetheless, the EU was largely unsuccessful in   achieving its aims. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The Copenhagen Accord &#150; the text that emerged in the   final day of the negotiations &#150; was a strikingly minimalist final agreement   which contrasted sharply with the EU's preferred approach to the global   governance of climate change (UNFCCC 2010, 4&#150;9). It included a goal of limiting   the rise in global mean temperature to 2 degrees Celsius but contained no   concrete commitments by any parties that suggested that this aspirational goal   would be achieved. It took the form of a "pledge and review" agreement under   which countries were invited to communicate their national targets for   emissions reduction or limitation to the UNFCCC Secretariat. The Accord did not   set out legally-binding targets for any countries, as the EU had sought, nor   did it contain any reference to a "peaking year" for emissions from large   developing countries. Moreover, in a symbolic blow to European leadership   aspirations, the EU famously was "not in the room" during key negotiations on   the final day of COP-15, in which the leaders of the US, Brazil, South Africa,   India, and China decisively shaped the final outcome without EU involvement   (BBC 2009).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The failure of the EU to successfully influence the   international process was due significantly to the changing external   opportunity structure. Three developments were particularly important. First,   the US returned to the negotiating table. The inauguration of Barack Obama in   January 2009 ended eight years of US disengagement from the climate change   negotiations. Second, the preferences of an increasingly powerful coalition of   actors diverge significantly from those of the EU. The US, China, and India   altogether in particular attach much greater priority to national sovereignty   and therefore support forms of international cooperation that involve much less   intrusion into domestic policymaking. Third, the EU has become significantly   less important with respect to global emissions. The EU-27 share of global   emissions has decreased from approximately 19% in 1990 to 11% in 2011. Other   countries' emissions have increased over the same period &#150; most strikingly that   of China, whose share of global emissions has grown from 11% in 1990 to almost   29% in 2011 (Olivier et al. 2012, 28). In short, the "window of   opportunity" that facilitated the emergence and development of EU international <i>actorness</i> on   climate change in the 1990s and early 2000s grew significantly smaller over the   second half of the 2000s.</font></p> <h5><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU retreat or resurgence: 2010&#150;2012</font></h5>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The outcome of the Copenhagen conference, and the EU's   marginalization in the final negotiations, came as a blow to the EU's   self-image as an international leader on climate change. Following on from   this, 2010 saw a period of reflection concerning the EU approach to the   international climate change negotiations and to its external relations more   generally (European Commission 2010).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">EU internal cohesion with respect to climate   policymaking has declined in the period since Copenhagen for a number of   reasons. First, EU leaders have focused considerably less attention on climate   policy as they have become ever-more preoccupied by the European sovereign debt   crisis. Little room has been left for consideration of EU climate change   policies at the highest political level. This contrasts sharply with the   2007&#150;2009 period, during which climate change featured regularly on the agenda   of European Council meetings.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Second, some newer member states have become   increasingly assertive in expressing their opposition to strengthening EU   climate policy. This has been led by Poland, which joined the EU in 2004 and   which relies on coal for 90% of its energy generation. While the EU's climate   change targets for 2020 and the Climate and Energy Package remain intact,   efforts to increase the level of ambition of these measures, or to set targets   for the period beyond 2020, have been thwarted. For example, in March 2012 and   again in June 2012, Poland vetoed EU proposals for EU climate change targets   beyond 2020 (Euractiv 2012). These factors have combined to reduce the EU's   internal cohesion with respect to climate policymaking.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The external context has also moved on somewhat since   Copenhagen. The opportunity structure still acts as a constraint on EU   actorness, but shifting dynamics in the global politics of climate change have   recently expanded the scope for EU influence. In particular, the role of China   has changed in subtle but important ways. Widely portrayed as one of the causes   of the minimalist outcome at COP-15, the Chinese government has undertaken a   deliberate strategy of constructive engagement in the climate change   negotiations during the period since. This was most evident at the Durban   climate change conference in November&#150;December 2011, during which the Chinese   government announced mid-way through the two-week negotiations &#150; for the first   time &#150; its willingness to be bound by a binding international climate agreement   for the period from 2020 onwards (McGroarty 2011).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">It was in the context of these broader shifts in   global climate politics that the EU succeeded in playing a more significant and   arguably more successful role, particularly at the Durban conference. It is   true that the positions of other key actors have moved subtly but decisively   towards the EU position, but EU <i>actorness</i> was also underpinned by a more nuanced and effective external diplomatic   strategy. In particular, the European Commission and a number of EU member states   participated in the period since Copenhagen in the Cartagena Group/Dialogue for   Progressive Action, a group of 30 states seeking to develop a common vision and   strategy for global climate action. Through such activities, the EU has been   able to build alliances with other like-minded states in an informal setting.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">COP-17 agreed to the launch of negotiations under a   Durban Platform for Enhanced Action, which is tasked with negotiating a   "protocol, another legal instrument or an agreed outcome with legal force under   the Convention applicable to all Parties" (UNFCCC 2012). This is only a first   step: negotiations are scheduled to be concluded by 2015, with a future   agreement &#150; if indeed agreement can be reached &#150; due to enter into force in   2020. Nonetheless, the Durban represents an improvement towards the model of   global climate change governance favored by the EU &#150; namely a top-down   international agreement with binding targets for all states. Moreover, the EU   played a key role in bringing the final negotiations to a successful conclusion   (Harvey 2011). That the EU succeeded in playing a significant role in shaping   the Durban outcome seems surprising given the decline of EU internal cohesion   over the period since 2009. However, EU actorness was facilitated by the more   favorable circumstances provided by the shifting constellation of actors and   interests in the global politics of climate change.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Conclusion</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This article set out to analyze EU's identity as an   actor part of the international climate regime by addressing the factors that   define <i>actorness</i>:   recognition, capability, opportunity, and cohesion. The scrutiny of these   issues was divided into two parts. The first provided an account of the formal   requirements for <i>actorness</i>,   whereas the second part conducted an analysis of the elements that shape the   EU's identity in practice. In both sections, the conclusion points out to the   fulfillment of all the four criteria of <i>actorness</i> &#150; albeit to a limited extent.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">The first part demonstrated that the EU meets only   partially the formal prerequisites (recognition and capability) for <i>actorness</i>. As a   signatory of the UNFCCC and the KP, the EU has full membership of the   international climate regime, which denotes complete external recognition of   the EU as an actor in the regime at the same level as nation-states. Formal   constraints are then of EU's capability to perform as such. As an area of   shared competence, responsibility over climate change issues is divided between   the Union and its 27 member states. In the absence of exclusive legal   competence, EU policymaking on external climate policy has a strong   intergovernmental nature, in which member states, operating through the   Council, play a pivotal role. These internal dynamics reflect on the EU's   representation in the multilateral area, where again member states set the   boundaries to the EU's capability to act. Nevertheless, in spite of legal and   procedural constraints, the EU has been able to forge mechanisms that, in   practice, support its unitary engagement in the international climate regime.   Overall, the first part concluded that the EU meets &#150; to a certain extent &#150;   some of the minimum requirements for its <i>actorness</i>. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">However, a significant implication of the analysis of   the formal attributes of recognition and capability is that, because of the   strongly intergovernmental nature of EU participation in the climate regime, EU   actorness depends crucially on internal cohesion and the external opportunity   structure. The second part of the article traced the development of EU   participation in the climate regime, highlighting the importance of these two   factors. Internal cohesion was limited during the 1990s, grew significantly   over the 2000s, and has declined again in the period since 2009. By contrast,   the external opportunity structure was most favorable for EU actorness during   the 1990s and early 2000s, and grew less favorable in the period since 2008. In   other words, internal cohesion and external opportunity are not correlated, and   the changing patterns are helpful in explaining variation in EU actorness over   time in the climate change regime.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Overall, this article cautions against viewing EU   participation in the climate regime in simplistic, unitary terms. If we judge   EU effectiveness and influence by the standards we apply to nation-states, we   are likely to be disappointed by what we find. But viewed as a collection of   nation-states with divergent interests and preferences, the EU contribution to   the global governance of climate change has in fact been significant, though it   has varied over time. The Durban climate change conference in December 2011   launched a new round of negotiations on a future climate change regime, and the   EU was credited with playing a significant role in reaching a final deal at   Durban. Despite shifting constellations of power and interest in the   international politics of climate change, progress over the coming years in   these negotiations is likely to depend in part on the continued ability of the   EU to contribute to global action to combat climate change.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Bibliographic references</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Adelle, Camilla, Marc Pallemaerts, and   Joana Chiavari. <i>Climate     Change and Energy Security in Europe</i>. Stockholm: Swedish Institute   for European Policy Studies, 2009.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000094&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Barnes, Pamela M. "The Role of the   Commission of the European Union: Creating External Coherence from Internal   Diversity." In <i>The     European Union as a Leader in International Climate Change Politics</i>,   edited by R&uuml;diger K. W. Wurzel and James Connelly, 41&#150;57. London &amp; New   York: Routledge, 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000096&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">BBC. "Key Powers Reach Compromise at   Climate Summit." <i>BBC News     website</i>, 19 December 2009.   Availability: &lt;<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8421935.stm" target="_blank">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8421935.stm</a>&gt;, accessed   11 August 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000098&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Bretherton, Charlotte and John Vogler. <i>The European Union as a Global   Actor</i> (2nd edn.). London: Routledge, 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000100&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Costa, Oriol. "Is Climate Change Changing   the EU? The Second Image Reversed in Climate Politics." <i>Cambridge Review of International     Affairs</i> 21, no. 4 (2008): 527&#150;44.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000102&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Council of the European Union.   "Contribution to the Spring European Council (19 and 20 march 2009): Further   Development of the EU Position on a Comprehensive Post-2012 Climate Agreement &#150;   Council Conclusions." Document 7128/09, 3 March 2009. Brussels.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000104&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Damro, Chad. "EU-UN Environmental   Relations: Shared Competence and Effective Multilateralism." In <i>The European Union at the United     Nations: Intersecting Multilateralisms</i>, edited by Katie Verlin   Laatikainen and Karen E. Smith, 175&#150;92. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000106&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Delreux, Tom. "The European Union in   International Environmental Negotiations: A Legal Perspective on the Internal   Decision-Making Process." <i>International     Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics</i> 6, no. 3   (2006): 231&#150;48.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000108&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Delreux, Tom. <i>The EU as International Environmental Negotiator</i>.   Farnham: Ashgate, 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000110&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Emerson, Michael, et al. <i>Upgrading the EU's Role as a Global   Actor: Institutions, Law and the Restructuring of European Diplomacy</i>.   Brussels: Centre for European Policy Studies, 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000112&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Euractiv. "Poland Blocks EU's Zero-Carbon   Plan." <i>Euractiv website</i>,   18 June 2012. Availability:   &lt;<a href="http://www.euractiv.com/climate-environment/poland-blocks-eus-zero-carbon-pl-news-513368" target="_blank">http://www.euractiv.com/climate-environment/poland-blocks-eus-zero-carbon-pl-news-513368</a>&gt;,   accessed 5 August 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000114&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">European Commission. "Europeans'   Attitudes Towards Climate Change: Special Eurobarometer 322." Document 2009.   Brussels.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000116&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">European Commission. "Communication from   the Commission to the European Parliament, the Council, the Economic and Social   Committee and the Committee of the Regions: International Climate Policy   Post-Copenhagen: Acting Now to Reinvigorate Global Action on Climate Change."   Document COM (2010) 86 final, 9 March 2010. Brussels.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000118&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">European Council. "Presidency Conclusions   &#150; G&ouml;teborg European Council, 15-16 June 2001." Document SN 200/1/01 REV 1.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000120&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">European Council. "Brussels European   Council, 8-9 March 2007: Presidency Conclusions." Document 7224/1/07, 2 May   2007. Brussels.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000122&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Grubb, Michael and Farhana Yamin.   "Climatic Collapse at The Hague: What Happened, Why, and Where Do We Go From   Here?" <i>International     Affairs</i> 77, no. 2 (2001): 261&#150;76.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000124&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Haigh, Nigel. "Climate Change Policies   and Politics in the European Community." In <i>The Politics of Climate     Change: A European Perspective</i>, edited by Tim O'Riordan and Jill   J&auml;ger. London: Routledge, 1996.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000126&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Harvey, Fiona. "Durban Talks: How Connie   Hedegaard Got Countries to Agree on Climate Deal." <i>The Guardian</i>, 11 December 2011.   Availability:   &lt;<a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2011/dec/11/connie-hedegaard-durban-climate-talks?intcmp=239" target="_blank">http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2011/dec/11/connie-hedegaard-durban-climate-talks?intcmp=239</a>&gt;,   accessed 5 August 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000128&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate   Change. <i>Climate Change     2007: Synthesis Report</i>. Geneva: Intergovernmental Panel on Climate   Change, 2007.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000130&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Jordan, Andrew and Tim Rayner. "The   Evolution of Climate Change Policy in the European Union: An Historical   Overview." In <i>Climate     Change Policy in the European Union: Confronting the Dilemmas of Mitigation and     Adaptation?</i>, edited by Andrew Jordan et al., 52&#150;80. Cambridge:   Cambridge University Press, 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000132&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Jupille, Joseph and James A. Caporaso.   "States, Agency, and Rules: The European Union in Global Environmental   Politics." In <i>The European     Union in the World Community</i>, edited by Carolyn Rhodes, 213&#150;29.   Boulder: Lynne Rienner, 1998.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000134&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Kaczy&#324;ski,   Piotr Maciej. "Swimming in Murky Waters: Challenges in Developing the EU's   External Representation." Document Helsinki.</font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">McGroarty, Patrick. "China Shakes Durban   Climate Talks." <i>The Wall     Street Journal</i>, 5 December 2011. Availability:   &lt;<a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/source/2011/12/05/china-shakes-durban-climate-talks/" target="_blank">http://blogs.wsj.com/source/2011/12/05/china-shakes-durban-climate-talks/</a>&gt;,   accessed 5 August 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000137&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Oberth&uuml;r, Sebastian and Hermann Ott. <i>The Kyoto Protocol: International   Climate Policy for the 21st Century</i>. Berlin: Springer, 1999.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000139&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Oberth&uuml;r, Sebastian and Claire Roche   Kelly. "EU Leadership in International Climate Policy: Achievements and   Challenges." <i>The International     Spectator</i> 43, no. 3 (2008): 35&#150;50.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000141&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Oberth&uuml;r, Sebastian and Claire Dupont.   "The Council, the European Council and International Climate Policy: From   Symbolic Leadership to Leadership by Example." In <i>The European Union as a Leader in International     Climate Change Politics</i>, edited by R&uuml;diger K. W. Wurzel and James   Connelly, 74&#150;91. London &amp; New York: Routledge, 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000143&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Olivier, Jos G.J., Greet   Janssens-Maenhout, and Jeroen A.H.W. Peters. <i>Long-Term     Trend in Global CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions: 2012 Report</i>. The Hague: PBL   Netherlands Environmental Assessment Agency &amp; EU Joint Research Centre,   2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000145&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800026&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Ott, Hermann. "The Bonn Agreement to the   Kyoto Protocol &#150; Paving the Way for Ratification." <i>International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law     and Economics</i> 1, no. 4 (2001): 469&#150;76.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000147&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800027&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Rajamani, Lavanya. <i>Differential Treatment in   International Environmental Law</i>. Oxford: Oxford University Press,   2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000149&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800028&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Rayner, Tim and Andrew Jordan. "The   United Kingdom: A Paradoxical Leader?" In <i>The European Union as a     Leader in International Climate Change Politics</i>, edited by R&uuml;diger   K. W. Wurzel and James Connelly, 95&#150;111. London &amp; New York: Routledge,   2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000151&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800029&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Schunz, Simon. "EU in the United Nations   Climate Change Regime." In <i>The     European Union and Multilateral Governance: Assessing EU Participation in     United Nations Human Rights       and Environmental Fora</i>, edited by Jan Wouters et al., 191&#150;213.   Basingstoke: Palgrave     Macmillan, 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000153&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800030&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Sj&ouml;stedt, Gunnar. <i>The External Role of the European   Community</i>. Farnham: Saxon House, 1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000155&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800031&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Skj&aelig;rseth, Jon Birger and J&oslash;rgen   Wettestad. <i>EU Emissions     Trading: Initiation, Decision-Making and Implementation</i>. Aldershot:   Ashgate, 2007.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000157&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800032&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Stern, Nicholas. <i>The Economics of Climate Change:   The Stern Review</i>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press and Cabinet   Office &#150; HM Treasury, 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000159&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800033&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Tabau, Anne-Sophie and Sandrine   Maljean-Dubois. "Non-Compliance Mechanisms: Interaction between the Kyoto   Protocol System and the European Union." <i>European     Journal of International Law</i> 21, no. 3 (2010): 749&#150;63.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000161&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800034&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">UNFCCC. "Report of the Conference of the   Parties on its fifteenth session, held in Copenhagen from 7 to 19 December 2009   " Document FCCC/CP/2009/11/Add.1, 30 March 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000163&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800035&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">UNFCCC. "Report of the Conference of the   Parties on its Seventeenth Session, held in Durban from 28 November to 11   December 2011." Document FCCC/CP/2011/9/Add.1, 15 March 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000165&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800036&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">van Schaik, Louise. "The Sustainability of the EU's Model of Climate   Diplomacy." In <i>The New     Climate Policies of the European Union: Internal Legislation and Climate     Diplomacy</i>, edited by Sebastian Oberth&uuml;r and Marc Pallemaerts,   251&#150;80. Brussels: Brussels University Press, 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000167&pid=S0034-7329201200030000800037&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Received August   9, 2012<br />   Accepted   September 15, 2012</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1" title="">1</a> &nbsp;<i>Shared competence</i> is one   the three principles that determines the legal basis for EU external climate   policy; EU decision-making within this area also needs to observe the   principles of <i>proportionality</i> and <i>subsidiarity</i>, defined by Article 5 of the Treaty on European Union.<br />   <a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2" title="">2</a> &nbsp;The problem, however,   is that there is no clear line delimiting the distribution of competences   betweenthe EU and member-states regarding compliance. The absence of a Treaty   provision setting a legal framework for the distribution of competences in   compliance of 'mixed agreements' was not addressed by the Lisbon Treaty, and   remains a gap in the EU legal system. Consequently, the lack of a clear legal   framework setting the limits of EU's authority and affects the dynamics of   power between the EU and its member states.</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Adelle]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Camilla]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Pallemaerts]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Marc]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Chiavari]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Joana]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Climate Change and Energy Security in Europe]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Stockholm ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Swedish Institute for European Policy Studies]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Barnes]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Pamela M]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Role of the Commission of the European Union: Creating External Coherence from Internal Diversity]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Wurzel]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Rüdiger K. W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Connelly]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[James]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union as a Leader in International Climate Change Politics]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>41-57</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[LondonNew York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>BBC</collab>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Key Powers Reach Compromise at Climate Summit]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[BBC News website]]></source>
<year>19 D</year>
<month>ec</month>
<day>em</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bretherton]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Charlotte]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Vogler]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[John]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union as a Global Actor]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<edition>2</edition>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Costa]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Oriol]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Is Climate Change Changing the EU? The Second Image Reversed in Climate Politics]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Cambridge Review of International Affairs]]></source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<issue>4</issue>
<page-range>527-44</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Council of the European Union</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Contribution to the Spring European Council (19 and 20 march 2009): Further Development of the EU Position on a Comprehensive Post-2012 Climate Agreement - Council Conclusions]]></source>
<year>3 Ma</year>
<month>rc</month>
<day>h </day>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Damro]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Chad]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[EU-UN Environmental Relations: Shared Competence and Effective Multilateralism]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union at the United Nations: Intersecting Multilateralisms]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<page-range>175-92</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Basingstoke ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Palgrave Macmillan]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Delreux]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Tom]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The European Union in International Environmental Negotiations: A Legal Perspective on the Internal Decision-Making Process]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>231-48</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Delreux]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Tom]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The EU as International Environmental Negotiator]]></source>
<year>2011</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Farnham ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ashgate]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Emerson]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Upgrading the EU's Role as a Global Actor: Institutions, Law and the Restructuring of European Diplomacy]]></source>
<year>2011</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Centre for European Policy Studies]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Euractiv</collab>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Poland Blocks EU's Zero-Carbon Plan]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Euractiv website]]></source>
<year>18 J</year>
<month>un</month>
<day>e </day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>European Commission</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Europeans' Attitudes Towards Climate Change: Special Eurobarometer 322]]></source>
<year></year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>European Commission</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Communication from the Commission to the European Parliament, the Council, the Economic and Social Committee and the Committee of the Regions: International Climate Policy Post-Copenhagen: Acting Now to Reinvigorate Global Action on Climate Change]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<month>9 </month>
<day>Ma</day>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>European Council</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Presidency Conclusions - Göteborg European Council, 15-16 June 2001]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>European Council</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Brussels European Council, 8-9 March 2007: Presidency Conclusions]]></source>
<year>2 Ma</year>
<month>y </month>
<day>20</day>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Grubb]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Farhana]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Yamin]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Climatic Collapse at The Hague: What Happened, Why, and Where Do We Go From Here?]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Affairs]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>77</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>261-76</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Haigh]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Nigel]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Climate Change Policies and Politics in the European Community]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Politics of Climate Change: A European Perspective]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Harvey]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Fiona]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Durban Talks: How Connie Hedegaard Got Countries to Agree on Climate Deal]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Guardian]]></source>
<year>11 D</year>
<month>ec</month>
<day>em</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Climate Change 2007: Synthesis Report]]></source>
<year>2007</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Geneva ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Jordan]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Andrew]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Rayner]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Tim]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Evolution of Climate Change Policy in the European Union: An Historical Overview]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Climate Change Policy in the European Union: Confronting the Dilemmas of Mitigation and Adaptation?]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>52-80</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Jupille]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Joseph]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Caporaso]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[James A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[States, Agency, and Rules: The European Union in Global Environmental Politics]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union in the World Community]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<page-range>213-29</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Boulder ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Lynne Rienner]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McGroarty]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Patrick]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[China Shakes Durban Climate Talks]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Wall Street Journal]]></source>
<year>5 De</year>
<month>ce</month>
<day>mb</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Oberthür]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ott]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Hermann]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The Kyoto Protocol: International Climate Policy for the 21st Century]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Berlin ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Springer]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Oberthür]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Kelly]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Claire Roche]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[EU Leadership in International Climate Policy: Achievements and Challenges]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The International Spectator]]></source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>35-50</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Oberthür]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Dupont]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Claire]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Council, the European Council and International Climate Policy: From Symbolic Leadership to Leadership by Example]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union as a Leader in International Climate Change Politics]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>74-91</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[LondonNew York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Olivier]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Jos G.J]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Janssens-Maenhout]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Greet]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Peters]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Jeroen A.H.W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Long-Term Trend in Global CO2 Emissions: 2012 Report]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[The Hague ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[PBL Netherlands Environmental Assessment Agency & EU Joint Research Centre]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ott]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Hermann]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Bonn Agreement to the Kyoto Protocol - Paving the Way for Ratification]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Environmental Agreements: Politics, Law and Economics]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<issue>4</issue>
<page-range>469-76</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Rajamani]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Lavanya]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Differential Treatment in International Environmental Law]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Oxford ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Oxford University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Rayner]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Tim]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Jordan]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Andrew]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The United Kingdom: A Paradoxical Leader?]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union as a Leader in International Climate Change Politics]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>95-111</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[LondonNew York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Schunz]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Simon.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[EU in the United Nations Climate Change Regime]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The European Union and Multilateral Governance: Assessing EU Participation in United Nations Human Rights and Environmental Fora]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<page-range>191-213</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Basingstoke ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Palgrave Macmillan]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B31">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Sjöstedt]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Gunnar]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The External Role of the European Community]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Farnham ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Saxon House]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B32">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Skjærseth]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Jon Birger]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Wettestad]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Jørgen]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[EU Emissions Trading: Initiation, Decision-Making and Implementation]]></source>
<year>2007</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Aldershot ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ashgate]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B33">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Stern]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Nicholas]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The Economics of Climate Change: The Stern Review]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press and Cabinet Office - HM Treasury]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B34">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Tabau]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Anne-Sophie]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Maljean-Dubois]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Sandrine]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Non-Compliance Mechanisms: Interaction between the Kyoto Protocol System and the European Union]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[European Journal of International Law]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>749-63</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B35">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNFCCC</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Report of the Conference of the Parties on its fifteenth session, held in Copenhagen from 7 to 19 December 2009]]></source>
<year>30 M</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>ch</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B36">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNFCCC</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Report of the Conference of the Parties on its Seventeenth Session, held in Durban from 28 November to 11 December 2011]]></source>
<year>15 M</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>ch</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B37">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[van Schaik]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Louise]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Sustainability of the EU's Model of Climate Diplomacy]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The New Climate Policies of the European Union: Internal Legislation and Climate Diplomacy]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<page-range>251-80</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brussels ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Brussels University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
