<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032006000400002</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032006000400002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Impacts of the U.S. subsidy to soybeans on World prices, production and exports]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Brandão]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Antônio Salazar P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Lima]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Elcyon Caiado Rocha]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A03"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,State University of Rio de Janeiro  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,IPEA  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A03">
<institution><![CDATA[,State University of Rio de Janeiro  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2006</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2006</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<fpage>631</fpage>
<lpage>676</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[This paper specifies and estimates an econometric model of the soybean market (grain, oil and meal) to assess the effects of U.S. domestic support to soybeans on world soybean prices, production and exports. The model divides the world into five regions (modules): Argentina, Brazil, the European Union, the United States (US) and the Rest of the World (ROW). There are interactions between the modules through the international prices and the net exports of each soybean product. The international prices of grain, oil and meal are endogenous and are determined equating net exports of the first four modules (Argentina, Brazil, European Union and the U.S.) to net imports of the ROW. The analysis is conducted eliminating the U.S. domestic support to soybeans and simulating the impacts on the variables of interest. The simulations show a significant impact of the US subsidy to soybeans on world prices and net exports of the four selected regions.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Este trabalho estima um modelo econométrico do mercado de soja e derivados com o objetivo de avaliar os efeitos das políticas de apoio interno dos Estados Unidos sobre os preços internacionais, sobre a produção e sobre as exportações. O modelo divide o mundo em cinco regiões: Argentina, Brasil, Estados Unidos, União Européia e Demais países. A interação entre as regiões ocorre através dos preços internacionais e pelas exportações líquidas em cada um dos mercados. Os preços internacionais dos três produtos são determinados igualando-se a soma das exportações líquidas das cinco regiões. A análise é feita eliminando o apoio doméstico nos Estados Unidos e simulando o impacto nas variáveis de interesse. As simulações mostram impactos significativos do subsídio americano sobre os preços internacionais e sobre as exportações líquidas de Argentina, Brasil, Estados Unidos e União Européia.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[soubeans subsidy]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[soybean market]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[international trade]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[subsídio à soja]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[mercado da soja]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[comércio internacional]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font size="4" face="Verdana"><B><a name="title"></a>Impacts of the U.S. subsidy    to soybeans on World prices, production and exports<a href="#nt01"><sup>1</sup></a></B></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Ant&ocirc;nio Salazar P. Brand&atilde;o<sup>I</sup>;    Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><sup>I</sup>Professor of the State University    of Rio de Janeiro (UERJ). <a href="mailto:abrandao@firjan.org.br">abrandao@firjan.org.br</a>>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Researcher at IPEA and Professor of the State University of Rio    de Janeiro (UERJ). <a href="mailto:elcyon@ipea.gov.br">elcyon@ipea.gov.br</a></FONT></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"> This paper specifies and estimates an econometric    model of the soybean market (grain, oil and meal) to assess the effects of U.S.    domestic support to soybeans on world soybean prices, production and exports.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   The model divides the world into five regions (modules): Argentina, Brazil,    the European Union, the United States (US) and the Rest of the World (ROW).    There are interactions between the modules through the international prices    and the net exports of each soybean product. The international prices of grain,    oil and meal are endogenous and are determined equating net exports of the first    four modules (Argentina, Brazil, European Union and the U.S.) to net imports    of the ROW.     <br>   The analysis is conducted eliminating the U.S. domestic support to soybeans    and simulating the impacts on the variables of interest. The simulations show    a significant impact of the US subsidy to soybeans on world prices and net exports    of the four selected regions.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Key words:</b> soubeans subsidy, soybean market,    international trade.    <br>   <b>JEL Classification:</b> F17, Q17</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Este trabalho estima um modelo econom&eacute;trico    do mercado de soja e derivados com o objetivo de avaliar os efeitos das pol&iacute;ticas    de apoio interno dos Estados Unidos sobre os pre&ccedil;os internacionais, sobre    a produ&ccedil;&atilde;o e sobre as exporta&ccedil;&otilde;es.    <br>   O modelo divide o mundo em cinco regi&otilde;es: Argentina, Brasil, Estados    Unidos, Uni&atilde;o Europ&eacute;ia e Demais pa&iacute;ses. A intera&ccedil;&atilde;o    entre as regi&otilde;es ocorre atrav&eacute;s dos pre&ccedil;os internacionais    e pelas exporta&ccedil;&otilde;es l&iacute;quidas em cada um dos mercados. Os    pre&ccedil;os internacionais dos tr&ecirc;s produtos s&atilde;o determinados    igualando-se a soma das exporta&ccedil;&otilde;es l&iacute;quidas das cinco    regi&otilde;es.    <br>   A an&aacute;lise &eacute; feita eliminando o apoio dom&eacute;stico nos Estados    Unidos e simulando o impacto nas vari&aacute;veis de interesse. As simula&ccedil;&otilde;es    mostram impactos significativos do subs&iacute;dio americano sobre os pre&ccedil;os    internacionais e sobre as exporta&ccedil;&otilde;es l&iacute;quidas de Argentina,    Brasil, Estados Unidos e Uni&atilde;o Europ&eacute;ia. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Palavras-chave:</b> subs&iacute;dio &agrave;    soja, mercado da soja, com&eacute;rcio internacional.    <br>   <b>Classifica&ccedil;&atilde;o JEL: </b>F17, Q17</font> </p> <hr size="1" noshade>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><a name="tx02"></a><b>1. Introduction<a href="#nt02"><sup>2</sup></a></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The Farm Bill of 1996, the Federal Agriculture    Improvement and Reform (Fair) Act, introduced significant changes in U.S. agricultural    policy. This partial reform of agricultural policy was an attempt to reduce    budget expenditures and to meet agreements signed in the Uruguay Round. Traditional    types of assistance, mostly based on current production and market conditions,    were discontinued in favor of decoupled payments (called production flexibility    contracts, PFC) not associated with current production or area. All acreage    restrictions were eliminated. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With the fall in prices after 1997, U.S. government    expenditures with <i>Amber Box</i> support (not excluding de <i>minimis</i>    exemptions) went from US$ 7 billions in 1997, to US$ 14 billion in 1998, to    US$ 23 billion in 1999 and fell slightly to US$ 21 billion in 2000 (Hart and    Babcock, <a href="#tab02">Table 2</a>, p. 10). Support for soybeans under this    category increased from almost zero in 1997 to US$ 1.3 billion in 1998, to US$    2.8 billion in 1999 and 2000.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Payments based on historical programs (the same    as the PFCs), which have replaced the old Loan Deficiency Payments, have been    another major component of U.S. support to agriculture. Expenditures under this    heading went from US$ 5.2 billion in 1996, to US$ 6.3 billion in 1997, to US$    8.4 billion in 1998, to US$ 10.9 billion in 1999 and have fallen slightly to    US$ 10.5 billion in 2000 (OECD).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Soybeans have benefited from the U.S. commodity    loan programs since 1941, but were not subjected to the acreage restrictions    imposed on feed grains, rice, wheat and upland cotton (Westcott and Price, p.15).    In most of the period after 1970 market prices have been above the loan rate    and the main benefit of the program was to provide liquidity to farmers until    production was sold. This was not the case before 1970 and in the middle of    the decade of the 1980s (see Westcott and Price pp. 16 and 17).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The marketing loan program in the U.S. started    in 1986 for rice and upland crop and was extended to soybeans and other oilseeds    in 1991 (Westcott and Price, p.3) and to wheat and feed grains in 1993. The    Fair Act continued the market loan program for these crops.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The PFC payments, introduced by the Fair Act,    were an attempt to move towards income support rather than price support. Producers    of commodities previously eligible for deficiency payments were entitled to    payments based the area planted with such crops during the 5-year period previous    to 1996. Soybeans were not eligible for PFC payments.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The PFC payments have been considered by U.S.    policy makers and by the WTO official decoupled with no or small effect on current    production and on trade. However, time has shown that what seemed true in principle    was not so in practice. With the elimination of acreage controls the PFC payments    provided extra operating capital that allowed farmers to expand area. This took    place for products that had higher returns per hectare. The increase in the    loan rate for soybeans US$ 5.26 per bushel in the 1997/98 marketing year triggered    a substantial expansion of soybean acreage at the expenses of other crops, mainly    wheat. But the production and trade distortions became even more evident with    the Farm Security and Rural Investment Act (FSRIA) of 2002 that allowed changes    in base acreage and yield and, as such, introduced an expectation element in    the farmer’s decision process. In other words, farmers that grow soybeans (and    other products included in the policy) now will be eligible to receive the subsidies    of the 2008 Farm Bill. That is, tomorrow’s subsidies induce more production,    more exports and lower world prices today. This is clearly a non-decoupled form    of domestic support.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">After 1999 the U.S. government introduced direct    payments to soybean producers (the Oilseed Program). These payments were introduced    after marketing loss assistance was granted to other crops and they are based    on past areas and yields. Nevertheless, these payments have effects that are    similar to the PFCs and are likely to raise current production in the U.S.,    raise U.S. exports and further reduce world prices of soybeans.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The Farm Security and Rural Investment Act (FSRIA)    of 2002 did not change principles embedded in the earlier policy and introduced    counter cyclical payments that provide a guarantee against low prices. Again    these payments are based on past acreage and yield, but through expectations    they will increase U.S. production and exports and will depress world prices    in the present.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In this paper we assess the effects of the U.S.    domestic support to soybeans and its consequences to world prices and to Brazilian    production and exports. To achieve this we first built an econometric model    of the world soybean market. The counter factual analysis consisted of the elimination    of the U.S. domestic support to soybeans and to track the impacts on the variables    of interest.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The paper is organized as follows: section 2    presents stylized facts about the production of soybeans in the U.S. and Brazil;    section 3 describes the U.S. Marketing Assistance Loan Program and other policies    that have distorting effects on production, trade and world prices; section    4 lays down the principal characteristics of the econometric model used to estimate    the impact of domestic support in the U.S. on world prices and Brazilian production    and exports; section 5 contains the principal results and section 6 concludes    the paper.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><B>2. Stylized facts</B></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">U.S. acreage for products where area was tied    to deficiency payments before the Fair Act decreased substantially after 1996.    Between 1996 and 2000 area reductions were as follows: corn 1.9 million hectares;    wheat 5.0 million hectares; sorghum 1.6 million hectares; and barley 506 thousand    hectares. During the same period the increase in soybeans area was 4.2 million    hectares<a name="tx03"></a><a href="#nt03"><sup>3</sup></a>, which shows that    the change in legislation had a major impact on the area planted with this crop.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Production of soybeans increased mostly because    of area, since yields did not change during this period<a name="tx04"></a><a href="#nt04"><sup>4</sup></a>.    This is seen in <a href="#tab01">Table 1</a> that displays area, production    and yield for the period 1979/2001. Production increased 17 percent between    1996 and 2001, area increased 19 percent and yield, declined 1 percent over    the same period<a name="tx05"></a><a href="#nt05"><sup>5</sup></a>. Figure 1,    which is based on indices of three-year averages, shows the same data.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The corresponding data for Brazil are shown in    <a href="#tab02">Table 2</a> and Figure 2, where it can be seen the strong expansion    of both area and yield during the same period. But the key difference is that    domestic support has not changed at all during this period in Brazil, while    this was not the case in the U.S.. A significant policy change that took place    recently in Brazil was the elimination of the value added tax (ICMS) on exports    of agricultural and semi processed goods in 1996. In other words, market forces    have driven the strong performance displayed by the sector in Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Figure 3 shows the volume of U.S. soybeans exports    since 1990. After the loan rate was raised to US$ 5.26 per bushel in the 1997/1998-crop    year exports have jumped, increasing 11 percent between 1997 and 1999 and 21    percent between 1998 and 1999. U.S. exports have been expanding since 1990,    as figure 3 shows; however, from 1998 to 2001 they have shown additional vigor.    This is particularly disturbing in light of the fact that the U.S. dollar has    become stronger over this period, that world prices have been declining and    that yields have not increased (Figure 4 shows export volumes and yield indices).    </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">These elements show clearly that marketing assistance    loan program have played a major role to explain the evolution of production    and exports. In other words, while in Brazil the market has been the driving    force behind the expansion of the soybean sector, in the U.S. the recent expansion    is induced by government expenditures to support the sector.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><B>3. The U.S. Marketing Loan Assistance,    Fixed Payments and Counter Cyclical Payments</B></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The US <u>Marketing Loan Assistance Program</u>    operates through two instruments:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Loan Rates; and    <br>   • Marketing Loans.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Loan Rates.</b> The Marketing Loans for soybeans    started in 1991. Before their introduction only Loan Rates were available. These    allow soybean farmers to borrow from the government with production pledged    as loan collateral. The loan value is determined by a crop specific loan rate    per unit of production. Farmers can borrow anytime after harvest through May    31. Most of the operations occur shortly after harvest when prices are seasonally    low.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Loan repayment can be made in either of the forms    below:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• payment of the principal plus interest; or    <br>   • forfeiting ownership of the loan collateral and keeping the proceeds of the    loan.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Marketing Loans.</b> Marketing loans changed    significantly the operation of the program. Farmers are allowed to repay the    loans at prices below the original loan rate plus interest. This is likely to    occur when market prices are below the loan rates.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With marketing loans the government accumulation    of stocks is reduced, since farmers retain ownership of production and sell    directly on the market. In consequence the policy has removed the price support    mechanism embedded in the Loan Program before.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The benefits of the program to farmers are granted    through two different channels:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Loan Program. In this case production is pledged    as collateral for the loan in the same form described before. But farmers can    repay the loan, at anytime during the loan period, at market prices. For soybeans    the repayment prices are posted county prices that are calculated daily. The    difference between the Loan Rate and the county prices represents a benefit    of the program for producers. Notice also that no interest accrues on the loan    when the loan repayment rate is below the loan rate plus interest.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Loan Deficiency Payment (LDP). In this case    farmers do not take any loans and the benefit of the program is the difference    between the loan rate and the county prices. If an LDP is paid on portion of    a crop it is no longer eligible for a loan.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The benefits of the Marketing Loan feature of    the program have been, on average, higher than described above. This is due    to the fact that farmers retain ownership of production and to the fact that    the Loan Rate no longer provides price support. Thus the decision to take the    benefit of the Marketing Loan is independent of the decision to sell production.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Typically a farmer will take the benefit of the    program at the time market prices are seasonally at the lowest point and sell    the crop later when prices are high again. Westcott and Price conclude the following    from this:</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><i>Raising the realized per-unit revenue above      the loan rate also increases the economic incentive to plant crops. This further      encourages producers to plant more land to supported crops than they otherwise      would and, as discussed earlier, may also influence the mix of crops planted.</i>      (p. 7)</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Based on 1999 information, Westcott and Price    (p.8) show the following for soybeans:</font></p> <table width="580" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top">     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<blockquote>              <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Season average price:</font></p>       </blockquote></td>     <td width="280" valign="top">    <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">$ 4.65/bushel;</font></p></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top">     <blockquote>              <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Marketing loan benefit:</font></p>       </blockquote></td>     <td width="280" valign="top">    <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">$ 0.85/bushel;          (95 percent of the crop received a marketing loan benefit; about 88 percent          received and LDP with an average payment rate of $ 0.91/bushel and 7 percent          received a loan gain of $ 0.76/bushel)</font></p></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top">     <blockquote>              <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Average per-unit revenue:</font></p>       </blockquote></td>     <td width="280" valign="top">    <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">$ 5.50/bushel;</font></p></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top">     <blockquote>              ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Commodity Loan Rate (1999):</font></p>       </blockquote></td>     <td width="280" valign="top">    <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">$ 5.26/bushel;          and</font></p></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top">     <blockquote>              <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Revenue above Loan Rate:</font></p>       </blockquote></td>     <td width="280" valign="top">    <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">$ 0.24/bushel.</font></p></td>   </tr> </table>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Thus, the marketing loan benefit amounts to 18.28    percent of the season average price and the revenue above the loan rate amounts    to 5.16 percent. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Westcott and Price (2001) have estimated the    impact of this subsidy on world prices and other variables. Selected parts of    their analysis and conclusions are quoted below:</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">"Soybean plantings are higher with marketing      loans through 2004 except in 2000 ...Marketing loan benefits increase soybean      net returns relative to returns to other crops in most years of the simulations,      providing an economic incentive to plant more soybeans. In 2000, however,      relatively large marketing loan benefits for corn pull away land from soybeans."      (p. 17)    <br>     "Exports of soybeans are increased through 2004, except in 2000 when      corn program benefits lead to lower soybean plantings. Exports of soybean      meal and soybean oil rise as well when soybean acreage increases as higher      domestic crush of soybeans leads to higher production and lower prices in      soybean product market." (p. 17)    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>     "...when marketing loan benefits shift land into soybeans (2001 through      2004) prices for soybeans are reduced, with the largest impact of 49 cents      occurring in 2001 when acreage gains for the crop are highest." (p. 19)</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In the simulation made by these author’s, the    impacts on prices from 1998 to 2000 are minor; the highest is in 2001 when the    marketing assistance loan reduces prices by 49 cents per bushel, corresponding    roughly to a reduction of 10 percent relative to the baseline with the marketing    loan assistance<a name="tx06"></a><a href="#nt06"><sup>6</sup></a>. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Westcott and Price (2001) analysis takes into    account the following crops: wheat, corn, sorghum, barley, oats, soybean, rice    and cotton. The effect of the marketing loan assistance on area planted is larger    from 1999 to 2001 with acreage increases of 810 to 1.6 million hectares<a name="tx07"></a><a href="#nt07"><sup>7</sup></a>    relative to the no marketing loan assistance scenario. As inspection of figures    20 to 24 (p. 16) of the paper indicates that the effects on upland cotton and    on soybeans are the largest relative to those on wheat, corn and rice. A similar    conclusion regarding to exports is suggested by figures 25 to 30, with the difference    that impacts on rice exports are large too. And for prices, other than soybean,    the conclusion of the authors is that:</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">"In 1999 through 2001, wheat prices are      lowered 4 to 7 cents per bushel in the marketing loan simulation, while corn      prices are reduced 3 to 9 cents per bushel in 1999 and 2000.... Rice prices      are reduced throughout the simulation period, with declines of 10 to 20 cents      per hundredweight in 2000 through 2005. Simulated price reductions for upland      cotton range from 1 to 5 cents per pound through 2002, the years of the largest      cotton acreage increase due to marketing loan benefits." (p. 19).</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OECD (2000, p. 59) has performed a similar exercise.    They have assumed that:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• there were no loan program payments for other    crops and that other countries' policies remain unchanged; and     <br>   • the marketing loans to be US$ 49/ton in 2000<a name="tx08"></a><a href="#nt08"><sup>8</sup></a>;    US$ 43/ton in 2001; US$ 31/ton in 2002; US$ 21/t in 2003; US$ 2/t in 2004 and    zero in 2005.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Based on these assumptions, they have concluded    that:</font></p>     <blockquote>        ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">"The withdrawal of such payments leads      to lower soyabeans output (initially –5 percent) and increase the output of      maize (initially +2 percent) and wheat (initially +1 percent). These production      changes have temporary impacts on export levels and world prices. Initially      world prices of soyabeans are 6 to 7 percent higher while world maize price      are 3 percent lower. However, these effects are eroded by 2004 as markets      adjust." (OECD 2000, p. 59)</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">These studies indicate clearly that the Marketing    Assistance Loan Program does have effects on world soybean prices and trade.    However the impacts on Brazil’s production and exports are not mentioned in    the papers and cannot be inferred from their results. A dedicated model, where    Brazil in explicitly included, is needed to make this assessment.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Direct payments for oilseeds were introduced    in the crop year 1999/2000 based on past acreage and yields. They not only have    been maintained by the FSRIA but were raised from about US$ 0,15 per bushel    to US$ 0,44 per bushel. These payments are now specific to soybeans and are    based on the acreage and yields of the period 1998/2001. As before they are    likely to be treated as decoupled by the WTO<a name="tx09"></a><a href="#nt09"><sup>9</sup></a>.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The FSRIA reduced the loan rate for soybeans    from US$ 5.26 per bushel to US$ 5.00 per bushel for the period 2002-2007. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The counter cyclical payments are a novelty of    the FSRIA in comparison with the FAIR Act. These are based on a target price    whose value is US$ 5.80 per bushel until 2007. The counter cyclical payments    are determined by the following formula: </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Target price - (higher of farm price or loan    rate) - direct payment</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Counter cyclical payments are based on area and    yield of soybeans during past periods, and are likely to be treated as decoupled    by the WTO<a name="tx10"></a><a href="#nt10"><sup>10</sup></a>. For the sake    of completeness, we indicate below the methodology established by the FSRIA    to determine acreage and yields for both direct and counter cyclical payments.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B><I>For direct payments </i></B></font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Soybean area is the average area during 1998/2001.      (Farm Economics Facts &amp; Opinions, June 5, 2002, no page numbers)     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>     Soybean yields, for the purpose of direct payments, are calculated as follows:      <i>average of soybean yields from 1998 through 2001 times .7814. The .7814      equals the ratio of the national soybean yields between 1981</i> </font></p>       <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"> <i>through 1985 to national yields from 1998      to 2001. This adjustment keeps soybean program yield on a comparable base      with corn and wheat yields. If a farm yield form 1998 through 2001 is below      75% of the county yield, the farm yield can be replaced by 75% of the county      yield.</i> (Farm Economics Facts &amp; Opinions, June 5, 2002, no page numbers)      </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B><I>For counter cyclical payments </i></B>    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The area is determined exactly as in the case    of the direct payments. For the determination of yields however the farmer may    choose from three methodologies, as indicated below. (Farm Economics Facts &amp;    Opinions, June 5, 2002, no page numbers) </font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B>Program yield</b>, which is determined by      the same procedure used in the direct payments program.     <br>     The <B>70% difference method</B> where yield is equal to the program yield      plus 70% of the difference between the average yield for 1998 through 2001      and the program yield.     <br>     The <B>93.5% method</B> where yield is equal to 93.5% of the average yield      during the period1998 to 2001. </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With the increase in direct payments and the    introduction of counter cyclical payments the FSRIA increased domestic support    to soybean producers relative to the previous legislation. The raise in other    payments more than compensated the reduction of the loan rates. For comparison    purposes, assume that soybean market price, in the crop year 2002/2003, is US$    4.45 per bushel and that acreage and yield of a typical farmer remain constant.    A hypothetical comparison of the support received before and after the FSRIA    made below:</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img01.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img02.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">As seen in the two boxes above the FSRIA raises    total return by 4.75%. If the WTO accepts the view that direct and counter cyclical    payments are decoupled, the part of the support that is considered non-trade    distorting has actually decreased from US$ 1.08/bushel to US$ 0.82/bushel. This    is a critical issue for the next round of trade negotiations and for the soybean    panel against the U.S. in the WTO.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp; </p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>4. Model structure and experiments</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This section lays down the main aspects of the    world soybean model, describes the steps to simulate the policy change and the    counter factual analysis.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The world is divided into five regions (modules):    Argentina, Brazil, the European Union, the United States (US) and the Rest of    the World (ROW). The diagrams in Annex III show the model structure for each    module.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For each module, area and yield equations determine    the supply of soybeans. The domestic demand for soybeans by the crushing industry    and the domestic demand for "Other Uses" of soybeans are estimated<a name="tx11"></a><a href="#nt11"><sup>11</sup></a>.    After determining the demand for crushing, "Other Uses" and soybeans    supply, net exports are obtained from the identity: </font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">net exports = production – crushing demand      – other uses</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Productions of oil and meal are fixed proportions    of the volume of soybeans crushed. These are, in turn, divided in two parts:    net exports and "Other Uses". We estimate equations for net exports    of soybean meal and for "Other Uses" of soybean oil. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Net imports of soybeans, soybean oil and soybean    meal of the rest of the world are exogenous, which means that they are not affected    by the elimination of the U.S. Marketing Assistance Loan and other policies.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Equating net exports of the first four modules    (Argentina, Brazil, European Union and the U.S.) to net imports of the ROW determines    the international price of grain, oil and meal. These prices are expressed in    domestic currency units, in real terms, by multiplying the dollar values by    the region real exchange rate.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Equations linking the international price in    domestic currency, to the domestic prices in domestic currency – price transmission    equations – for the three products are also estimated. This is done with due    consideration of domestic policies that may have affected this relation, such    as the elimination of the export tax on soybeans in Brazil in 1996.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The equations of the model, with the respective    coefficients and statistics, are presented in Annex I. All variables have the    correct signs and are significant. There is no evidence of autocorrelation of    the residuals and the fit of model within the sample is good.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Comparing the baseline scenario with one where    no subsidy exists allows for the estimation of the effects of the changes in    policies. The baseline consists of the model forecasts for the period where    data is available and of the projections, based on the relevant parameters of    the FSRIA. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The two scenarios considered in the counter factual    analyses are described below:</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<blockquote>        <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Scenario 1. WTO rules are not changed and      the Marketing Loan Assistance is the only policy that influences U.S. exports      and world prices. This scenario is consistent with the lower impact on world      prices and on world trade.    <br>     • Scenario 2. In addition to Marketing Loan Assistance, direct payments and      counter cyclical payments are removed. This gives an upper bound for the impacts      on world prices and world trade.</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It is clear that neither the direct payments    nor the counter cyclical payments are entirely decoupled, as assumed in Scenario    2. The impact of these two subsidies on production and exports depend on expectations    regarding the next farm bill in 2007 and, as such, their effects may be smaller    than those indicated in the simulations below. Nevertheless, the two scenarios    give a reasonable range of variation for the variables relevant for this analysis.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>5. Results</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab03">Table 3</a> shows values of    the subsidy from 1998 to 2001. The values for the period 2002 to 2004 are estimated    taking into account the FSRIA and prices generated by the baseline (scenario    1) of the econometric model. Total return is what farmers receive above market    price due to the marketing loan, direct payments and counter cyclical payments.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab03"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab03.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In <B>Scenario 1</B> the values of the marketing    loan payments are reduced to zero. In the <B>Scenario 2</B> the producer return    is the same as producer price, that is, the marketing loan payments, the direct    payments and the counter cyclical payments are all reduced to zero.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Scenario 1. </b><a href="#tab04">Tables 4    to 13</a> contain results of simulations. <a href="#tab04">Table 4</a> contains    estimated price changes due to the removal of the marketing loan assistance.    The average increase in world prices increase over the period 1998/2004 in 3.95    percent, with highest values, of the order of 7 percent, in 2000 and in 2001    when the marketing loan payments were at their peak. It is seen that producer    prices in the U.S. are reduced on average 11.48 percent and Brazilian prices    increase by about 3.81 percent, in line with the change in world prices.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It must be noted that the world price changes    estimated by the model are in line with those obtained in other studies, such    as those of Westcott and Price (1999, 2001) and the OECD Agricultural Outlook    (2000). The fact that removing large subsidies to commodities does not cause    large impacts on market prices is well known and documented in the literature,    as noted by Vald&eacute;s and Foster (2002). </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The changes in world oil and meal prices are    seen in <a href="#tab05">Table 5</a>. The average impact on oil prices is quite    surprising, since it is even higher than the impact on grain prices. This is    caused by the large reduction on crushing in the U.S. and by the small effect    on domestic consumption. Meal prices, on the other hand, increase less than    soybean world prices.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab06">Table 6</a> shows the impacts    on soybeans production in Argentina, Brazil and the U.S.. There is a reduction    of approximately 30 million tons during the period 1998/2004 in the U.S. production    of soybeans, which correspond to approximately 5.3 percent of the production    estimated in the baseline. This is, in part, compensated by increases in Argentina    and Brazil of the order of 4 percent in each country. The largest impacts on    Brazil take place during the period 2001 and 2003, where production losses between    2 and 2.5 million tons per year.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab07">Tables 7</a>, <a href="#tab08">8</a>    and <a href="#tab09">9</a> show the corresponding impacts on soybean oil production,    soybean meal production and in soybean crushing. These impacts are in line with    the changes observed in world prices and in soybeans production. Notice that    the impact on Brazil is quite significant compared with that of Argentina and    of the European Union.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In summary, the analysis of these tables indicate    that the removal of the marketing loan assistance in the U.S. will have favorable    impacts on soybean production as well as on the domestic crushing industry.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab10">Tables 10 to 13</a> show net    exports. The results indicate again that the impact of the removal of this subsidy    on the world market is significant. Exports from the U.S. would be smaller (about    3 million tons in 2002) and those of Brazil and Argentina increased. In Brazil    the highest impact is in 2001, about 2 million tons, and the impact, during    the period 1998/2004, is of the order of 7 million tons. The impact on the value    of exports, as seen in <a href="#tab11">Table 11</a>, is close to US$ 2 billion    dollars, with the largest values (US$ 450 and US$ 382 millions) concentrated    in 2001 and 2002.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">By the total value of net exports of the soybean    complex are larger, since Brazilian exports of soybean oil and soybean meal    will increase too. The total effect reaches the value of US$ 751 million in    2001, dropping to US 699 millions in 2002. The total increment of exports of    the soybean complex during the period is US$ 3 billion.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">These results illustrate another perverse aspect    of the current concepts used in the WTO regarding export subsidies. The marketing    loan assistance is defined as domestic support (Amber Box). However, its impacts    on U.S. exports are large relative to the change in production, as the following    analysis shows. Total reduction in production in the U.S. over the period 1998/2004    is of the order of 30 million tons. This is turn lead to a reduction of about    14 million tons in crushing and 14 million tons in exports of soybeans. That    is, 50 percent of the effect on production influences directly exports. The    50 percent directed to additional crushing also finds its way to the world markets    through more exports of soybean oil and soybean meal. Thus, this program contains    an important element of export subsidy that is ignored by the current definitions    adopted in the WTO.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Scenario 2.</b> <a href="#tab14">Tables 14    to 23</a> contain results of simulations. The results encountered in this scenario    do not differ qualitatively of those found in Scenario 1. The difference in    the simulation between the two is that we have included fixed payments and counter    cyclical payments as if they were not decoupled. As noted before, there is clearly    an impact on production and trade induced by these policies that works through    an expectation mechanism induced by the fact that the 2007 farm bill is likely    to allow revisions of acreage and yield and only farmers who are now producing    will be eligible for the revisions. To capture this mechanism in an econometric    model is not easy and not feasible since the data is not yet available. In view    of this difficulty, the authors agreed to simulate the effect of the removal    of these policies as if they were not decoupled. This is likely to provide an    upper bound for the actual impacts of the change in policy.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It is not necessary to analyze <a href="#tab14">Tables    14 to 23</a> in detail since the nature of the results is similar. Nevertheless,    we emphasize the points below.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• World price of soybeans increase by a maximum    of 9 percent in 2000 and the increase remains above 7 percent in 2001 and 2002.    <br>   • Producer prices in the U.S. are reduced 16 percent on average, with values    as high as 20 percent towards the end of the period.    <br>   • Brazilian losses due to the policy can be summarized as follows: production    of soybeans is reduced by almost 13 million tons during the period 1998/2004;    during the same period net exports of soybeans are reduced by 9 million tons,    equivalent to US$ 2.2 billion; and net exports of the soybean complex are reduced    by US$ 4 billions.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>6. Summary</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This paper has analyzed the impact of the current    U.S. policy for soybeans on Brazilian production and trade of soybean and soybean    products. The main findings of the study were:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The elimination of the domestic support to    soybeans will increase world prices of soybeans and of soybean products. The    average increase in soybean prices during the period 1998/2004 varies between    4 and 5 percent according to the liberalization scenario considered. The maximum    increase in prices occurs in 2000 and 2001, when the marketing loan program    provided the highest levels of support.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   • Brazilian production over the entire period is reduced between 10 and 13 million    tons.    <br>   • Exports of soybeans are reduced between 7 and 9 million tons, equivalent to    US$ 1.6 to US$ 2.2 billion.    <br>   • Exports of the soybean complex are reduced between US$ 3 and US$ 4 billion    dollars.    <br>   • This domestic support provided by U.S. policy has a significant impact on    trade, since about 50 percent of the increase in soybean production will be    exported directly. But the total impact is even greater since exports of soybean    meal and soybean oil will take place too.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In conclusion this subsidy is causing damage    to Brazilian producers and exporters. Governmental initiatives leading to the    elimination of this type of support are important not only because of the estimated    impacts but because these policies are likely to continue and cumulative effects    can cause distress in the sector, with reductions in income and employment.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><B>7. Tables</B></font></p>     <p><a name="tab01"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab01.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab02"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab02.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab04"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab05"></a></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab05.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab06"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab06.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab07"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab07.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab08"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab08.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab09"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab09.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab10"></a></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab10.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab11"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab11.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab12.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab13.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab14"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab14.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab15.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab16.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab17.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab18.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab19.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab20.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab21.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab22.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab23.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><B>8. References</B></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Hart, Charles E. and Bruce A. Babcock. <B>Implications    of the WTO on the Redesign of U.S. Farm Policy</B>. Center for Agricultural    and Rural Development, Iowa State University, <i>Briefing Paper</i> 01-BP 32,    May 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000248&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Nelson, Frederick J. <B>Aligning U.S. Farm Policy    with World Trade Commitments</B>, <i>Agricultural Outlook</i>, January – February    2002, pp. 12-16.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000249&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OECD <B>Agricultural Outlook 2000-2005</B>, Paris,    2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000250&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OECD <B>Agricultural Outlook 2001-2006</B>, Paris,    2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000251&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OECD <B>Agricultural Policies in OECD Countries:    Monitoring and Evaluation</B>, Paris, 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000252&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OECD <B>Agricultural Databases</B>, CD, Paris    2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000253&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Orden, David. <B>Reform’s Stunted Crop</B>, in    <i>Regulation</i>, Spring 2002, Vol. 25, N° 1.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000254&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Scronce, Philip W. <i>Grains and Oilseeds Outlook    for 2001</i>. Feed Grains and Oilseeds Analysis Group, Farm Service Agency,    U.S. Department of Agriculture. Agricultural Outlook Forum 2001, February 23,    2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000255&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">USDA <B>Agricultural Statistics 2001</B>, CD,    Washington, D.C., 2001</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000256&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Vald&eacute;s, Alberto and William Foster. <B>Reflections    on the Policy Implications of Agricultural Price Distortions and Price Transmission    for Producers in Developing Countries and Transition Economies</B>. Paper presented    at the <i>OECD Global Forum on Agriculture</i>, OECD, Paris, May 23 and 24,    2002.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000257&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Westcott, Paul and Michael J. Price. <B>Analysis    of the U.S. Commodity Loan Program with Commodity Loan Provisions</B>. Economic    Research Service/USDA, <i>Agricultural Economic Report No. 801</i>, April 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000258&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Westcott, Paul C. and Michael J. Price. <B>Impacts    of the U.S. Marketing Loan Program for Soybeans</B>. Special Article for <i>Oil    Crops Situation and Outlook</i>, Economic Research Service/USDA, October 1999,    pp. 15-21.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000259&pid=S0103-2003200600040000200012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Recebido em junho de 2006 e revisto em outubro    de 2006. &nbsp; </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a name="nt01"></a><a href="#title">1</a> This    paper has been prepared at the request of the Confedera&ccedil;&atilde;o Nacional    da Agricultura e Pecu&aacute;ria do Brasil (CNA) as a partial fulfillment of    agreement nº 21.010.830/2001-12 signed by the CNA and the Minist&eacute;rio    da Agricultura, Pecu&aacute;ria e Abastecimento to assess the effects of U.S.    domestic support to soybeans on the Brazilian soybean sector. The authors want    to express their gratitude to several people and institutions: the participants    of the various meetings and seminars headed by Pedro de Camargo Netto who was    then Secretary of Production and Marketing, Minist&eacute;rio da Agricultura    e do Abastecimento; to ABIOVE staff who shared information and knowledge of    U.S. policy with us; to Guilherme Leite da Silva Dias, S&aacute;vio Pereira,    Get&uacute;lio Pernambuco and F&aacute;bio Trigueirinho who have had extensive    discussions with us and contributed significantly to the conception of the model    and to our understanding of U.S. agricultural policy; to the OECD Agricultural    Directorate who shared their knowledge of agricultural policies in the OECD    countries and their modeling experience with us. We have also benefited enormously    from data and other information contained in AgLink (which was accessible to    us through the agreement of Minist&eacute;rio da Agricultura and the OECD).    None of those mentioned above are responsible for the errors and omissions that    may still remain.    <br>   <a name="nt02"></a><a href="#tx02">2</a> This paper was prepared in 2002 to    support the the WTO panel against the U.S. domestic support policies for soybeans    that was Brazil was then considering. Due to changes in the world soybeans market,    with significant price increases, the WTO panel was not requested. We submitted    for publication the original version of the paper, without updating the data    and model estimation.    <br>   <a name="nt03"></a><a href="#tx03">3</a> Area increases were also observed in    cotton (358 thousand hectares); sunflower (104 thousand hectares) and rice (98    thousand hectares).    <br>   <a name="nt04"></a><a href="#tx04">4</a> Yield is a partial index of productivity.    A more appropriate indicator is the total factor productivity index, whose calculation    goes beyond the scope of this analysis.    <br>   <a name="nt05"></a><a href="#tx05">5</a> These are based on the three-year averages.    <br>   <a name="nt06"></a><a href="#tx06">6</a> The paper does not contain tables.    The percentage mentioned in the text is based on inspection of Figure 34, page    20.    <br>   <a name="nt07"></a><a href="#tx07">7</a> This is equivalent to 2 to 4 million    acres.    <br>   <a name="nt08"></a><a href="#tx08">8</a> The actual value of the marketing loan    assistance in 2000 was US$ 37/ton (calculations based on Hart and Babcock, 2001,    <a href="#tab02">Table 2</a> and the U.S. production of 75,055 million tons).    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="nt09"></a><a href="#tx09">9</a> Please see the introduction where we    have argued that these payments are trade distorting.    <br>   <a name="nt10"></a><a href="#tx10">10</a> Please see the introduction where    we have argued that these payments are trade distorting.    <br>   <a name="nt11"></a><a href="#tx11">11</a> The exception is the European Union    where a net import equation was estimated and other uses were calculated as    a residual.</FONT></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>9. Annex I - Equations</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><I>Argentina Module</I></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab24.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab25.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Brazil Module</i></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab26.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab27.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>European Union Module</i></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab28.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab29.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>U.S. Module</i></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab30.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab31.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>The equations for area and yield for the    U.S. were reestimated for Scenario 2. The new equations are shown in <a href="#tab32">Table    32</a> below.</i></b></font></p>     <p><a name="tab32"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02tab32.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>10. Annex II - Notation</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><I>Argentine Module</I></b></font></p> <table width="500" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argfaoc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal other        uses, 1000 ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argfapdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal domestic        price, Pesos/ton, MECON/SAGPyA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argfapid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal international        price, Pesos/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argfaqp</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal production,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argmargid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">crushing margin        at international prices</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argmlpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"> <font size="2" face="Verdana">maize domestic        price, pesos/ton, MECON/SAGPyA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argmlyld</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">maize yield, kg/ha.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argoloc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"> <font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil other        uses,1000 ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argolpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil domestic        price, Pesos/ton, MECON/SAGPyA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argolpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil international        price, Pesos/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argostax</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">oil seed tax rate</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argpib</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">gross domestic        product, FMI/IFS - International.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjoc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean other uses,        1000 ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjarea</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean area planted,        1000 ha, MECON.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjesmag</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean crushing,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean domestic        price, Pesos/ton, MECON/SAGPyA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean international        price, Pesos/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>argsjyld</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean yield ton/ha,        MECON.</FONT></td>   </tr> </table>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><I>Brazilian Module</I></b></font></p> <table width="500" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brfaexl</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal net        exports, 1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brfapdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal domestic        price, R$/ton, DERAL/DEB - SEAB/PR.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brfapid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal international        price, R$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brfaqp</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal production        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brfrango</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">chicken meat production        1000 ton, UBA / APINCO.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brmlpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">maize domestic        price, R$/ton, FGV.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>broloc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil other        uses,1000 ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brolpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil domestic        price, R$/ton, DERAL/DEB - SEAB/PR.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brolpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil international        price, R$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brpop</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">population estimated,        IBGE.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brrecunit</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">unitary revenue        from crushing</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjarea</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean area planted,        1000 ha, IBGE.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjesmag</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean crushing,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjoc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean other uses,1000        ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean domestic        price, R$/ton, FGV.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean international        price, R$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brtjur</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">real interest rate.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsjyld</b></FONT></td>     <td valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean yield ton/ha, IBGE.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>brsuqp</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">pork production        1000 ton, IBGE.</FONT></td>   </tr> </table>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><I><b>U.S. Module</b></I></font></p> <table width="500" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euafaexl</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal net        exports, 1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euafapdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal domestic        price, US$/ton, USDA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euafapid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal international        price, US$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euafaqp</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal production        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euamlrret1</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">farm return for        corn producers</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euamargid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">crushing margin        at international prices</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euaoloc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil other        uses,1000 ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euaolpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil domestic        price, US$/ton, USDA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euaolpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil international        price, US$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euatrplr</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">loan rate for wheat</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjarea</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean area planted,        1000 ha, USDA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjesmag</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean crushing,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjoc</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean other uses,1000        ton, calculation.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjpdd</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean domestic        price, US$/ton, USDA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjpid</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean international        price, US$/ton, CBOT.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjqp</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean production        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjrret1</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean farmer        return</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjyld</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean yield ton/ha,        USDA.</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euasjturet</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">price paid to the        soybean producer (includes subsidies, marketing loan assistance, direct        payment and counter cyclical payment), calculation</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euatrturet</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">price paid to the        wheat producer (includes subsidies, marketing loan assistance, direct payment        and counter cyclical payment), calculation</FONT></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>euamlturet</b></FONT></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">price paid to the        maize producer (includes subsidies, marketing loan assistance, direct payment        and counter cyclical payment), calculation</FONT></td>   </tr> </table>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><I>European Union Module</I></b></font></p> <table width="500" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cefaiml</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal net        imports, 1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cefapdd</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal domestic        price, Euro/ton, AgLink</font> </td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cefapid</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean meal international        price, Euro/ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cemargid</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">crushing margin        at international prices</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceolexl</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil net        exports,1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceolpdd</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil domestic        price, Euro/ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceolpid</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil international        price, Euro/ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceolqp</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean oil production        1000 ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjarea</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean area planted,        1000 ha, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjesmag</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean crushing,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjiml</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean net imports,        1000 ton, OIL WORLD.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjpdd</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean domestic        price, Euro/ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjpid</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean international        price, Euro/ton.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceruqp</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">ruminant production        1000 ton, AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjyld</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean yield ton/ha,        AgLink</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjtcr</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean farm return</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>cesjtyld</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean yield trend,        calculation.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>misjpid</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">soybean international        market price Euro/ton, calculation.</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="100" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ceuatrrret1</b></font></td>     <td width="400" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">price paid to the        wheat producer (includes subsidies: marketing loan assistance), calculation</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>11. Annex III – Model structure</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img03.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img3a.gif" border="0"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img04.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img4a.gif" border="0"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img05.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img5a.gif" border="0"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img06.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n4/a02img6a.gif" border="0"></a></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[ ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Hart]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Charles E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Babcock]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Bruce A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Implications of the WTO on the Redesign of U.S. Farm Policy]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Center for Agricultural and Rural Development, Iowa State University]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Nelson]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Frederick J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Aligning U.S. Farm Policy with World Trade Commitments]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Outlook]]></source>
<year>Janu</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>y </day>
<page-range>12-16</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OECD</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Outlook 2000-2005]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OECD</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Outlook 2001-2006]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OECD</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Policies in OECD Countries: Monitoring and Evaluation]]></source>
<year></year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris^e2001 2001]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OECD</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Databases]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Orden]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[David]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Reform’s Stunted Crop]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Regulation]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Scronce]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Philip W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Grains and Oilseeds Outlook for 2001]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[ Agricultural Outlook Forum 2001]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>February 23, 2001</conf-date>
<conf-loc> </conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[ Agricultural Statistics 2001]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>2001</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Washington D.C.</conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Valdés]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Alberto]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Foster]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[William]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Reflections on the Policy Implications of Agricultural Price Distortions and Price Transmission for Producers in Developing Countries and Transition Economies]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[ OECD Global Forum on Agriculture]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>May 23 and 24, 2002</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Paris </conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Westcott]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Paul]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Price]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Analysis of the U.S. Commodity Loan Program with Commodity Loan Provisions]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural Economic Report]]></source>
<year>Apri</year>
<month>l </month>
<day>20</day>
<numero>801</numero>
<issue>801</issue>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Westcott]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Paul C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Price]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Impacts of the U.S. Marketing Loan Program for Soybeans]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Oil Crops Situation and Outlook]]></source>
<year>Octo</year>
<month>be</month>
<day>r </day>
<page-range>15-21</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[Economic Research ServiceUSDA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
