<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032004000100003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032004000100003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Consumer-driven profit maximization in broiler production and processing]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Costa]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Ecio de Farias]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Houston]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Jack E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidade Federal de Pernambuco  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Georgia  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>01</month>
<year>2004</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>01</month>
<year>2004</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032004000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032004000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032004000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Increased emphasis on consumer markets in broiler profit-maximizing modeling generates results that differ from those by traditional profit-maximization models. This approach reveals that the adoption of step pricing and consideration of marketing options (examples of responsiveness to consumers) affect the optimal feed formulation levels and types of broiler production to generate maximum profitability. The adoption of step pricing attests that higher profits can be obtained for targeted weights only if premium prices for broiler products are contracted.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Um aumento na ênfase dada ao mercado de consumidores de carne de frango e modelos de maximização de lucros na produção de frangos de corte geram resultados que diferem daqueles obtidos em modelos tradicionais de maximização de lucros. Esta metodologia revela que a adoção de step-pricing e considerando opções de mercado (exemplos de resposta às preferências de consumidores) afetam os níveis ótimos de formulação de rações e os tipos de produção de frangos de corte que geram uma lucratividade máxima. A adoção de step-pricing atesta que maiores lucros podem ser obtidos para pesos-alvo somente se preços-prêmio para produtos processados de carne de frango forem contratados.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[consumer preferences]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[processor decisions]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[marketing options]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[step pricing]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[decisões do produtor]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[opções de mercado]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[preferência do consumidor]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[step-pricing]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="4"><b>Consumer-driven    profit maximization in broiler production and processing</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Ecio    de Farias Costa<sup>I</sup>; Jack E. Houston<sup>II</sup></font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>I</sup>Professor    de Economia at UFPE- Ph.D. em Economia Agr&iacute;cola, University of Georgia,2001-    E-mail: <u><a href="mailto:ecio@yahoo.com">ecio@yahoo.com</a>    <br>   </u> <sup>II</sup>Professor    de Economia Agr&iacute;cola- University of Georgia- Ph.D em Economia Agr&iacute;cola,    Washington State University, 1986. E-mail: <a href="mailto:jhouston@agecon.uga.edu">jhouston@agecon.uga.edu</a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b>    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Increased    emphasis on consumer markets in broiler profit-maximizing modeling generates    results that differ from those by traditional profit-maximization models. This    approach reveals that the adoption of step pricing and consideration of marketing    options (examples of responsiveness to consumers) affect the optimal feed formulation    levels and types of broiler production to generate maximum profitability. The    adoption of step pricing attests that higher profits can be obtained for targeted    weights only if premium prices for broiler products are contracted.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Key Words:</b>    consumer preferences, processor decisions, marketing options, step pricing.</font></p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>RESUMO    </b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Um aumento    na &ecirc;nfase dada ao mercado de consumidores de carne de frango e modelos    de maximiza&ccedil;&atilde;o de lucros na produ&ccedil;&atilde;o de frangos    de corte geram resultados que diferem daqueles obtidos em modelos tradicionais    de maximiza&ccedil;&atilde;o de lucros. Esta metodologia revela que a ado&ccedil;&atilde;o    de step-pricing e considerando op&ccedil;&otilde;es de mercado (exemplos de    resposta &agrave;s prefer&ecirc;ncias de consumidores) afetam os n&iacute;veis    &oacute;timos de formula&ccedil;&atilde;o de ra&ccedil;&otilde;es e os tipos    de produ&ccedil;&atilde;o de frangos de corte que geram uma lucratividade m&aacute;xima.    A ado&ccedil;&atilde;o de step-pricing atesta que maiores lucros podem ser obtidos    para pesos-alvo somente se pre&ccedil;os-pr&ecirc;mio para produtos processados    de carne de frango forem contratados.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Palavras-chave:    </b>decis&otilde;es do produtor, op&ccedil;&otilde;es de mercado, prefer&ecirc;ncia    do consumidor, step-pricing.</font></p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Introduction</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Vertically integrated chains of production in the broiler industry make determination    of profit-enhancing decisions perplexing. Ascertaining profits in broiler production    is complex, because the production and processing involve many steps, ranging    from hatchery to production using formulated feeds to processing in the plants    and to distribution onwards. Efficient organization and utilization of resources    will produce not necessarily the heaviest, but the most profitable, broilers.    The retail market is consumer-driven, and thus it is important for the processors    to meet the specific characteristics desired by consumers for product size and    quality most profitably.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The retail market demands specific finished products that are not always the    most technically efficient results of production processes. Fast food restaurants,    for example, only want breast meat that falls into the weight that will fit    in their sandwich bread. This smaller weight bird, however, may not be as profitable    to a broiler processor who could make more profit by feeding for longer periods    or feeding a low-cost feed that will not give the desired weight or fat content.    Further, the retail market pays a premium price for meeting the specifications    of the products they expect from broiler processors. Using the specifications    for desired weight and the premium prices they attract, a profit maximization    model must show efficient ways of meeting such distinctive products yet resulting    in profitability for the firm. Modeling consumer-driven broiler production to    obtain maximum profits requires the adoption of marketing requirements that    induce efficient production. This study analyzes the adoption of step-pricing    and marketing options on profitable broiler production.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Higher prices are paid to processed parts that meet specifications of the retail    market, and this premium price concept is termed step pricing. Such specifications    can be used for selling chicken parts that target a weight range that the consumer    prefers, for example. The concept of marketing options is based on the premise    that broiler processors must decide at what processing level they want to sell    their products; <i>i.e.</i>, whether to process chickens into whole carcasses,    or to further process them to sell as cut-up parts, seasonally adjusting to    the market. The prices paid differ as to the level of processing, and the production    process is also directly influenced by the marketing decision process. After    the step-pricing and marketing options are chosen, it is necessary to integrate    this information into the decision model to determine the most efficient feed    formulation and production process to yield targeted products.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The proper feed ration is formulated according to prior information on step-pricing    and marketing options, but it will also be formulated according to the prices    and availability of nutrient sources. Other factors also play a role in the    broiler model composition. For example, it is necessary to factor in the gender    percentage of the chicks, temperature and size of the house, and other factors    influencing the optimal production of the targeted product.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The profit-maximizing analysis for consumer market-driven broiler production    and processing decisions presented in this study is composed of three stages.    First, broiler response functions over experimental feeding data are estimated    to determine the broiler production functions to be used in the profit maximization    model. Second, results obtained from the production scenarios are used for profitability    analysis of the two marketing options: selling broilers processed as whole carcass    <i>vs.</i> selling broilers processed as cut-up parts. Finally, a step-pricing    analysis of outputs generated by the two marketing options determines premium    prices (step-prices) that are as profitable as baseline scenarios for target    weights determined by the retail market in response to consumer preferences.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The main objective of this study is then to simulate the adoption of consumer    preferences in a profit maximization model, through the adoption of step-pricing    in different marketing scenarios. The advantages of the adopted methodology    are that broiler integrators will face a more efficient production system that    will yield in more profitable production processes.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Related    Literature</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b><i>Profit Maximization and Cost Minimization Broiler Models</i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Starting in the 1950's with the widespread adoption of mathematical programming,    interest in feed formulation was renewed. For decades, the major objective to    be attained in optimal broiler production was to minimize the cost of feed,    and little consideration was allocated to other determinants of profitability.    Least-cost rations minimize the cost of diets, given a certain set of ingredients    and their nutritional content. An important assumption of least-cost formulated    diets is that every unit of a least-cost formulated ration has the same productivity    regardless of ingredient sources (Allison and Baird, 1974).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The adoption of simple cost minimization does not account for differentials    in productivity among input sources; <i>e.g.</i>, broiler performances in experimental    trials of those birds fed peanut meal protein <i>vs.</i> those fed soybean meal    (SBM) protein have been shown to differ significantly (Costa <i>et al.</i>,    2001). On the other hand, the adoption of profit maximization techniques later    in the 1990's has taken into consideration the productivity aspects of economically    efficient broiler production. Few models have been developed thus far, and they    differ in their approaches to the problem.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Gonzalez-Alcorta <i>et al.</i> (1994) developed a profit maximization model    that uses nonlinear and separable programming to determine the precise energy    and protein levels in the feed that maximize profit. Their model is distinguished    by the assumption that body weight is not fixed at a predetermined level. Feed    cost is not determined by least cost feed formulation. Rather, feed cost is    determined as a variable of the profit maximization model in a way similar to    that described in Pesti <i>et al.</i> (1986). Gonzalez-Alcorta <i>et al.</i>    (1994) conclude that setting energy and protein levels that vary with output    and input prices can raise profit compared to fixed diet levels of energy and    protein based on previous nutritional guidelines.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Costa <i>et al.</i> (2001) developed a 2-step profit maximization model that    minimizes feed cost and maximizes profit in broiler production. Their model    indicates the optimal average feed consumed, feed cost, live and processed body    weight of chickens, as well as the optimal length of time that the broilers    must stay in the house and other factors, for given temperature, size of the    house, costs of inputs and outputs and for certain, pre-determined protein level,    source, and processing decisions. They conclude that peanut meal can be more    profitable than SBM for growing birds to be processed and sold as whole carcasses.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The analysis conducted in our study differs from Costa <i>et al.</i> (2001)    by developing a decision model that allows for a single, feedback procedure    that is determined by the consumer-oriented price signals. This construction    not only generates processing alternatives for selling whole carcass and cut-up    parts, but the model also determines the marketing option that is the most profitable,    given expected product prices. The solutions allow for adjustment of the production    to given targeted weights and premium prices for broiler products in the procedure,    called step pricing, as already mentioned. An important feature of this model    is that the processing decision takes place only after expected prices of inputs    and outputs are determined. The prices of outputs are determined by consumers    in the market place.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">This study    uses data obtained from an experiment conducted at the University of Georgia<a name="top1"></a><a href="#back1"><sup>1</sup></a>,    which uses trials conducted for the collection of information on live body weight,    feed consumption and weight of processed parts. This data set, which contains    productivity information, is used to estimate the production response functions    that are used in the profit maximization model of this study.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Model    Description</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">A brief    description of the model follows<a name="top2"></a><a href="#back1"><sup>2</sup></a>.    The objective function to be optimized is:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922x1.gif"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">subject to (among the full set of constraints):</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922x2.gif"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">for marketing options,</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922x3.gif"></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">and, for the step-pricing,</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922x4.gif"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the objective    function (Equation 1), maximum profit per bird per day (<img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922x5.gif" align="absmiddle">),    is defined as a function of derived price (<i>DP<sub>BW</sub></i>), live body    weight (<i>BW</i>), cost of feed consumed (<i>P<sub>FC</sub></i>), feed consumed    (<i>FC</i>), interest cost (<i>I</i>), and feeding time (<i>t</i>). Due to the    objective function's specification, the constraint set includes a number of    equations (nutrition constraints, and other constraints in the model) that are    not specifically mentioned in this manuscript. However, the most relevant constraints    that allow for a direct comparison between the two marketing options and step-pricing    analyses are described next. Cost of feed consumed (<i>P<sub>FC</sub></i>) includes    feed delivery cost (<i>DEL</i>) and the least cost feed (<i>P<sub>F</sub></i>,    Equation 2). The least cost feed function (<i>FC</i>) minimizes the cost of    feed for pre-determined ingredients (<i>X<sub>i</sub></i>) and their prices    (<i>P<sub>i</sub></i>) and is determined by the optimization process (Equation    3). Live chicken body weight (<i>BW</i>) is determined by feed consumed (<i>FC</i>),    feed consumed squared (<i>FC<sup>2</sup></i>), protein level (<i>PR</i>), protein    level squared (<i>PR<sup>2</sup></i>), and an intercept shifter for female chickens    (<i>FE</i>, Equation 4). The coefficients of the <i>BW</i> function are determined    by ordinary least squares (OLS) on experimental data. Feed consumed (<i>FC</i>)    is determined by feeding time (<i>t</i>), feeding time squared (<i>t<sup>2</sup></i>),    protein level (<i>PR</i>), protein level squared (<i>PR<sup>2</sup></i>), and    an intercept shifter for female chickens (<i>FE</i>, Equation 5). Interest cost    (<i>I</i>) is determined as a function of the annual interest rate (<i>r</i>)    figured daily (dividing by 365 days) and the number of days necessary to grow    broilers (<i>t</i>, Equation 6).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The constraints in the model that introduce alternative marketing options are    presented in Equations 7-10. The marketing option varies according to the marketing    option <i>k</i> (whole carcass or cut-up parts marketing option). Derived price    (<i>DP<sub>BW</sub></i>, Equation 7) is a function of live value of birds delivered    to the plant (<i>LV<sub>K</sub></i>) divided by the number of birds that finished    the production process (<i>BF</i>). <i>LV<sub>K</sub></i> (Equation 8) is a    function of <i>BF,</i> and average values of the weights of processed part <i>k</i>    (<i>ADP<sub>k</sub></i>, Equation 9) depend on the processed weight (<i>w<sub>l</sub></i>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Equation 10 is estimated as processed weight, <i>w<sub>l</sub></i>, of each    part <i>l</i> derived from a live bird (<i>l = WC</i> for whole carcass, <i>BR</i>    for skinless boneless breast weight, <i>TE</i> for tenderloin, <i>LQ</i> for    leg quarters, <i>WI</i> for wings, <i>FP</i> for fat pad, and <i>RC</i> for    rest of chicken for the cut-up parts processed broiler). The sum of all processed    parts must be equal to the live weight of the bird (plus offal and giblets).    Each equation is estimated as a function of live bird weight (<i>BW</i>), protein    level (<i>PR</i>), protein level squared (<i>PR<sup>2</sup></i>), and gender    of birds (<i>FE</i>). The coefficients are estimated by OLS on experimental    data.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">We modify the model for the adoption of the step-pricing constraint by setting    a further constraint on the targeted weight for the processed part that is to    be produced. Equation 11 presents the constraint that is added to the model.    The target weight of part <i>l</i>, <i>TW<sub>l</sub></i>, is determined by    the consumer retail market and must be met by the processor by contracting with    buyers of such weight-targeted processed parts. If the model finds the target    weight as an optimal answer, it uses the premium price, <i>TP<sub>l</sub></i>,    as a step-price in the model. If not, the model uses the lower, general product    price, <i>P<sub>l</sub></i>.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The linear program model is simulated using a built-in linear program analysis    package in Microsoft Excel (2000), Solver. Each simulation is recorded and comparison    analyses are conducted among the optimal results for every scenario. Step-prices    are also incorporated in the simulations to obtain the targeted weights. The    optimal answers and comparison analyses are presented next, as well as the estimated    production responses that are estimated using SAS (1996).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Estimated    Production Responses</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Production    Equations 4, 5 and 10 are estimated by OLS and presented next (<a href="#tab1">Tables    1</a> and <a href="#tab2">2</a>). <a href="#tab1">Table 1</a> displays the estimated    coefficients of Equations 4, 5 and 10 (only for estimation of carcass weight    in 10). Live bird weight (<i>BW</i>) increases at a decreasing rate with respect    to feed consumed (<i>FC</i>) and protein level (<i>PR</i>), while feed consumed    increases at an increasing rate with respect to feeding time (<i>t</i>) and    increases at a decreasing rate with respect to protein level (<i>PR</i>). Weight    of whole carcass (<i>W<sub>WC</sub></i>) increases at a decreasing rate with    respect to protein level (<i>PR</i>). Estimated coefficients of Equation 10    (for skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, leg quarters, and wings weights)    are shown in <a href="#tab2">Table 2</a>. Weights of skinless boneless breast,    tenderloin, leg quarters, and wings (<i>W<sub>BR</sub></i>, <i>W<sub>TE</sub></i>,    <i>W<sub>LQ</sub></i>, and <i>W<sub>WI</sub></i>, respectively) increase at    increasing rates with respect to <i>PR</i>. These results concur with those    of Pesti and Smith (1984) that show that production responses of broilers to    dietary energy and protein levels show diminishing marginal returns.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a name="tab1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922t1.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a name="tab2"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922t2.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Prices of inputs and outputs are collected for the profit maximization analysis.    The prices data include prices of ingredients available for the ration formulation,    including major feedstuffs and synthetic amino acids that supplement the deficiencies    of major sources, and prices received in Georgia (or the Southeast of the United    States, which is responsible for the largest production in the world) for the    outputs considered in the analysis as well as other costs considered in the    analysis. Other inputs to the model include average temperature and size of    the broiler house.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Model    Interactions, Marketing Options and Step-pricing Analyses</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Our model    is first used to estimate the profitability of two baseline scenarios, where    broilers are produced and sold after being processed into whole carcasses or    into cut-up parts. Thus, the baseline scenarios are analyzed for the collected    data on prices of inputs and outputs. Initially, comparisons are made directly    between whole carcass marketing option and cut-up parts marketing option results    for each selling alternative. Lastly, targeted weights are applied to the model    in order to simulate premium prices and their profitability through the step-pricing    concept. Optimal solution sets report broiler weights, feed consumption, feeding    time, and feed composition that maximize profit under certain production function    estimation, marketing option, and input/output prices. All optimal formulated    rations meet all nutrient requirements from the National Research Council (NRC,    1994) for the nutrient requirements for poultry production and replicate the    industry standards. The results obtained from the interaction of the program    formulate an optimal grow-out feeding ration. Each optimized ration is fed to    broilers for an optimal number of days in order to obtain an optimal weight    that is to be processed and sold to a specific market, given the prices of outputs    and ingredients and other costs integrated in the model, as illustrated by the    case scenario in <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="fig1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922f1.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Assume in    <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a> that the current price of whole carcass is higher    at a certain time of the year because consumers are demanding relatively more    whole carcass meat (roasting). Prices of outputs and inputs are then entered    in the model, which uses previously entered information and relationships on    production and returns to carcass weight products of broilers, nutrient requirements    determined by the NRC (1994), size of the house, temperature, chicks gender    information, and other production costs. The model incorporates these two aspects    of the input and output markets, and model results suggest that the processor    grow and process broilers into whole carcass. The optimal solution set that    is generated by the model goes first to decisions in the broiler house, where    optimal feed composition and optimal feeding time are set to deliver live body    weight of birds. The body weight produced in the broiler house is transmitted    to the processing plant, where the profit-maximizing carcass weight is the outcome.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">A second    output solution set generated by this model is represented in <a href="#fig1">Figure    1</a> by the dotted lines. The dotted lines show the option in the model that    represents the setting of a targeted weight by the retail market that is rewarded    by a step-price paid to processors. As consumer demand increases for whole carcass,    the whole carcass weights that are targeted are conformable to the weights retailers    sell in their market. As a reward for requiring such weight for the output,    retailers provide a step-price to the poultry processor, who redefines the process    of production to attain such target weight. This redefinition of targeted products    involves using a different length of time of production as well as a different    combination of inputs to attain the desired weight efficiently.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b><i><font size="2">Selling    Broilers According to Marketing Options - Baseline Scenarios</font></i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Results    demonstrating the most-profitable production process for selling broilers that    are processed into whole carcass or selling cut-up parts are presented in <a href="#tab3">Table    3</a>. Results indicate the baseline scenarios where feeding formulations are    most profitable for the production of broilers that are processed and sold as    whole carcass or cut-up parts markets under the prices of inputs and outputs    observed for the time period chosen. Although processing broilers into cut-up    parts generates the most profitable marketing option, results can and will differ    for different price circumstances.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a name="tab3"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922t3.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The NRC    (1994) recommends that the protein level in the diets used for broilers in the    grower phase, from 3 to 6 weeks, should be equal to 20%. However, the formulated    feeds in this model present protein levels above the recommended level. Comparative    results also indicate that a longer feeding time and more feed consumed are    allocated to produce a heavier bird for the cut-up parts marketing option than    for the whole carcass marketing option. Cut-up parts have an aggregated value    that is higher than the value of whole carcass. Therefore, a longer feeding    cycle and more feed consumed can be used to seek a higher profitability in terms    of net returns per bird per day.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b><i><font size="2">Step-Pricing    Analysis for Targeted Weight of Whole Carcass and Cut-up Parts</font></i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Profitability    is next related to optimally producing broilers to target weights; <i>i.e.</i>,    weights determined by the retail market in response to consumer preferences    require that a new constraint be added to the model that sets carcass or cut-up    parts weights equal to a desired level (as indicated in Equations 10 and 11,    and <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>). This desired level is determined by the retailers,    who learn from their own consumption studies what processed weights of carcass    or cut-up parts their consumers prefer. Thus, a poultry processor must meet    certain weight levels in order to induce a premium price from the retailers.    As an example, fast food restaurants require that the weight of chicken breasts    fall within a tight range that will fit in the standard sandwich bread. They    will pay a premium price (or step-price in our model) to the processor that    sells them a product meeting these specifications.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Sample data    on carcass, skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, leg quarters and wings weights    were collected from a food retailer, and the average weights for each processed    part were assumed to be the target weights. All averaged weights reported by    the food retailer are higher than the optimal levels indicated in the previous    analyses of the baseline scenarios conducted with current market prices and    no target weights set as constraints. Despite those differences, the next analyses    show target weights and the corresponding step-prices that make the production    process as profitable as the baseline solutions for the various marketing options.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b><i><font size="2">Step-Pricing    Analysis on Whole Carcass</font></i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the step-pricing    analysis on the whole carcass market, a carcass target weight of 3.99 lbs. (against    baseline levels of 2.90 lbs.) is set. Initially, in the first column of <a href="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922t4.gif">Table    4</a>, the target weight constraint is applied to broilers using the same market    price as the result presented in <a href="#tab3">Table 3</a>, analysis for whole    carcass. Profit levels decline for attaining that target weight, showing that    if no step-price is applied, the target weight generates economic inefficiency.    Protein level, feeding time, live weight, feed cost, and feed conversion ratio    all increase as the target weight is considered. Further interactions of the    model, increasing the price of whole carcass above market level to obtain higher    profits, show that if one seeks to achieve a profit level equal to the baseline    profit reported in <a href="#tab3">Table 3</a> and also a target weight of 3.99    lbs., then there must be an increase in the price of whole carcass on the order    of 2.44%.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b><i><font size="2">Step-Pricing    Analysis on Cut-up Broiler Parts</font></i></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The step-price analysis for target weights is next applied to cut-up processed    parts: skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, leg quarters, and wings. According    to sample data collected from a food retailer, their target weights are 1.00,    0.20, 1.93, and 0.41 lbs., respectively. The sampled average weights from the    food retailer are again higher than the baseline optimal solutions, with exception    of the weight of wings, which is lower than the baseline solution. In other    words, the optimal solution obtained in the model interaction at current prices    indicates that the weight of skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, and leg quarters    are lower (and for wings, higher) than the average weights reported by the food    retailer.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Columns    3-10 of <a href="/img/revistas/resr/v42n1/20922t4.gif">Table 4</a> exhibit the premium price analyses    on targeted skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, leg quarters, and wings weights.    Target weights drive profitability down for all processed parts when compared    to the baseline solutions if no step-price is applied to the model. In order    to attain the same profitability level of production as reported in <a href="#tab3">Table    3</a>, increases in the prices of cut-up parts are necessary. The prices of    skinless boneless breast, tenderloin, leg quarters, and wings would have to    increase by 7.03%, 2.42%, 8.77%, and 0.64%, respectively, to match profitability    levels recorded in the baseline solutions. Notice that the protein level, feeding    time, and live bird weight are higher for the targeted weights of processed    parts, with the exception of wings weight (that is lower), than the baseline    solutions. This response is again due to more inputs being allocated when there    is an extra reward expected as a step-price to induce the altered efficient    production of broilers.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Conclusions</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The profit-maximization model developed in this work interactively generates    optimal solutions for marketing options that process and sell broilers in the    carcass and cut-up parts markets. Feeds formulated for all optimal solutions    meet all NRC requirements for nutrient composition of feed rations, but the    protein levels indicated by this model are substantially above the average levels    reported in the industry and range from 23% to just less than 25% protein level    in the diet.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Comparison between marketing options indicates that profits are higher for    the cut-up parts marketing option than for the whole carcass market option,    because more value is added to broilers processed into cut-up parts. In the    whole carcass marketing option, birds are fed for shorter feeding times than    are broilers in the cut-up parts marketing option. Both the average live body    weight and feed consumed are lower for broilers produced in the whole carcass    marketing option than for broilers produced in the cut-up parts marketing option.    Adoption of target weights represents a decline in profits, if no step-price    is applied to induce the adoption of target weights. However, as step-prices    are employed, profits can be increased for both marketing options to profit    levels in the baseline scenarios. Negotiation must take place between retailers    and processors when deciding what step-price should be adopted for different    marketing options. Broiler processors must incorporate all steps of their production    and processing into the decision-making and agree on contract terms that represent    efficient allocation of their inputs. This should include seasonal and other    market-related information, especially as pertains to product mix in each cycle    of production. Retailers must recognize that step-prices may be required to    induce special requests for targeted weights that are expected from poultry    processors. Determining what the terms of negotiation should be is beyond the    scope of this study, but the findings generated by this comprehensive profit-maximizing    model may serve as a promising start. The behavior of broiler processors in    Brazil and the United States must change to incorporate the concepts of step-pricing    and consumer preferences in their production and processing. By doing that,    their profitability in broiler production and processing will increase considerably.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">On the other hand, the impacts of this research results for broiler growers    must be further discussed. As presented, the results may indicate lower optimal    weights and lower production processes that may result in higher number of flocks'    rotations for growers. Growers and integrators must also negotiate how the extra    profits generated by this efficiency gain will be distributed among themselves.    Therefore, new ways of evaluating the grower's production behavior must be determined.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ALLISON, J. R., and D. M. BAIRD. 1974. "Least-cost Livestock Productions Rations."    <i>Southern Journal of Agricultural Economics</i> 6: 41-45.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000093&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">COSTA, E. F. 2001. Economic Modeling for Optimal Broiler Production and Processing.    PhD Dissertation. Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics, University    of Georgia.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000094&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">COSTA, E. F., B. R. MILLER, G. M. PESTI, R. I. BAKALLI, and H. P. EWING. 2001.    "Studies on Feeding Peanut Meal as a Protein Source for Broiler Chickens." <i>Poultry    Science Journal</i> 80(3): 306-313.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000095&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">COSTA, E. F., B. R. MILLER, J. E. HOUSTON, and G. M. PESTI. 2001. "Production    and Profitability Responses to Alternative Protein Sources and Levels in Broiler    Rations." <i>Journal of Agricultural and Applied Economics</i> 33, 3(December):567-581.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000096&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GONZALEZ-ALCORTA, M. J., J. H. DORFMAN, and G. M. PESTI. 1994. "Maximizing    Profit in Broiler Production as Prices Change: a Simple Approximation with Practical    Value." <i>Agribusiness: An International Journal</i> 10:389-399.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000097&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">MICROSOFT<sup>&#174;</sup> EXCEL 2000. Copyright<sup>&copy;</sup> 1985-1999    Microsoft Corporation.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000098&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">NATIONAL RESEARCH CCOUNCIL (NRC). <i>Nutrient Requirements of Poultry</i>.    (9th revised edition). Washington, DC: <sup>&#174;</sup>National Academy Press, 1994.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000099&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">PESTI, G. M., and C. F. SMITH. 1984. "The Response of Growing Broiler Chickens    to Dietary Protein, Energy and Added Fat Contents." <i>British Poultry Science    Journal</i> 25:127-138.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000100&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">PESTI, G. M., R. A. ARRAES, and B. R. MILLER. 1986. "Use of the Quadratic Growth    Response to Dietary Protein and Energy Concentrations in Least-cost Feed Formulation."    <i>Poultry Science Journal</i> 65:1040-51.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000101&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">SAS INSTITUTE INC. SAS<sup>&#174;</sup> Version 6.10, Cary, NC: SAS Institute    Inc. 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000102&pid=S0103-2003200400010000300010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Recebido    em abril de 2003 e revisto em agosto de 2003</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="back1"></a><a href="#top1">1</a>    Feed composition and feeding level experiment was conducted by the Poultry Science    Department at the University of Georgia. The experiment consisted of using four    different levels of protein (17%, 20%, 23%, and 26%) using SBM as protein source    to feed broiler chickens until 42 days and collecting body weight, feed consumed    and weight of processed parts. For more detailed information, contact the authors.    <br>   <a href="#top2">2</a> The objective of this manuscript is not to discuss the    description and functionality of the proposed model, but the application of    the same to consumer-oriented market profitability decisions. For a more detailed    description, see Costa (2001).</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ALLISON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BAIRD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Least-cost Livestock Productions Rations]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Southern Journal of Agricultural Economics]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>6</volume>
<page-range>41-45</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COSTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Economic Modeling for Optimal Broiler Production and Processing]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COSTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MILLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PESTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BAKALLI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. I.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[EWING]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H. P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Studies on Feeding Peanut Meal as a Protein Source for Broiler Chickens]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Poultry Science Journal]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>80</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>306-313</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COSTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MILLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOUSTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PESTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Production and Profitability Responses to Alternative Protein Sources and Levels in Broiler Rations]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Agricultural and Applied Economics]]></source>
<year>Dece</year>
<month>mb</month>
<day>er</day>
<volume>33</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>567-581</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GONZALEZ-ALCORTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DORFMAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. H.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PESTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Maximizing Profit in Broiler Production as Prices Change: a Simple Approximation with Practical Value]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Agribusiness: An International Journal]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>10</volume>
<page-range>389-399</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Microsoft Corporation</collab>
<source><![CDATA[MICROSOFT® EXCEL]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>NATIONAL RESEARCH CCOUNCIL</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Nutrient Requirements of Poultry]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<edition>9</edition>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[National Academy Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PESTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SMITH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Response of Growing Broiler Chickens to Dietary Protein, Energy and Added Fat Contents]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[British Poultry Science Journal]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>25</volume>
<page-range>127-138</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PESTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ARRAES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MILLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Use of the Quadratic Growth Response to Dietary Protein and Energy Concentrations in Least-cost Feed Formulation]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Poultry Science Journal]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>65</volume>
<page-range>1040-51</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>SAS INSTITUTE INC</collab>
<source><![CDATA[SAS® Version 6.10]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cary^eNC NC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[SAS Institute Inc]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
