<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032013000600003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032013000600003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Measurement of the technical efficiency of small pineapple farmers in Santander, Colombia: a stochastic frontier approach]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Trujillo]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Juan C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Iglesias]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Wilman J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidad del Atlántico Department of Economics ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[Barranquilla ]]></addr-line>
<country>Colombia</country>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidade Federal de Viçosa  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[Viçosa Minas Gerais]]></addr-line>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>s049</fpage>
<lpage>s062</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032013000600003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032013000600003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032013000600003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[The objective of this study is to estimate the levels of technical efficiency of the small pineapple farmers of Santander, Colombia, using the stochastic frontier approach. In addition, this study attempts to determine whether the acreage and some of the socio-economic characteristics of farmers can influence the efficiency of their pineapple farms. By exploiting the information that was gathered in a survey of 194 pineapple farmers in the region, these farmers' technical efficiency was estimated using a Cobb-Douglas-type stochastic frontier model and a technical inefficiency model. The results suggest that acreage and the variables that are associated with the human capital, e.g., the level of schooling and the years of experience in agricultural activity, explain the levels of technical efficiency to a significant degree.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[technical efficiency]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[stochastic frontier]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Cobb-Douglas production function]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[pineapple]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><a name="top"></a><b>Measurement    of the technical efficiency of small pineapple farmers in Santander, Colombia:    a stochastic frontier approach</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Juan C. Trujillo<sup>I</sup>;    Wilman J. Iglesias<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>I</sup>Assistant    Professor. Department of Economics, Universidad del Atl&aacute;ntico, Barranquilla,    Colombia. E-mail: <a href="mailto:juantrujillo@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co">juantrujillo@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Student of the Master in Applied Economics. Universidade Federal    de Vi&ccedil;osa, Vi&ccedil;osa, Minas Gerais, Brazil. Scholarship granted by    Coordena&ccedil;&atilde;o de Aperfei&ccedil;oamento de Pessoal de N&iacute;vel    Superior (Capes). E-mail: <a href="mailto:wilman.pinedo@ufv.br">wilman.pinedo@ufv.br</a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr noshade size="1"/>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The objective of    this study is to estimate the levels of technical efficiency of the small pineapple    farmers of Santander, Colombia, using the stochastic frontier approach. In addition,    this study attempts to determine whether the acreage and some of the socio-economic    characteristics of farmers can influence the efficiency of their pineapple farms.    By exploiting the information that was gathered in a survey of 194 pineapple    farmers in the region, these farmers' technical efficiency was estimated using    a Cobb-Douglas-type stochastic frontier model and a technical inefficiency model.    The results suggest that acreage and the variables that are associated with    the human capital, e.g., the level of schooling and the years of experience    in agricultural activity, explain the levels of technical efficiency to a significant    degree.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Key-words:</b>    technical efficiency, stochastic frontier, Cobb-Douglas production function,    pineapple    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>JEL Classification:</b>    C21, Q12, Q16.</font></p> <hr noshade size="1"/>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>1. Introduction</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Small-scale agriculture    represents the smallest link in Colombia's agricultural chain. Within Colombian    agricultural production, the small farmers (peasants, including both indigenous    and African-American communities) constitute most of the domestic producers.<a name="top1"></a><a href="#back1"><sup>1</sup></a>    These small-scale farmers cultivate 7.2 acres on average; furthermore, they    represent 87% of Colombian farmers, they contribute 41% of the agricultural    gross domestic product, and they generate nearly 40% of the products that are    considered basic food necessities in Colombia (MALDONADO et al., 2007). In spite    of these records, it is curious that such issues as the measurement of the levels    of technical efficiency and the determinants of the small farmers from Colombia    have still not been explored.<a name="top2"></a><a href="#back2"><sup>2</sup></a></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">According to the    figures of the Ministerio de Agricultura y Desarrollo Rural -MADR- (2012), Colombia    possesses a harvested area of fruits that comprises approximately 750,085 acres.    As for the pineapple, it reached a surface area of 27,951 acres, which ranks    it as the sixth-most important fruit crop as determined by its sown area.<a name="top3"></a><a href="#back3"><sup>3</sup></a>    Pineapple (<i>Ananas comosus</i>) is a fruit that is native to southeastern    Brazil and Paraguay (SAMSON, 1986). In 2010, the main pineapple-producing countries    were the Philippines, Brazil, Costa Rica and Thailand, and their productions    were 2,169,230, 2,120,030, 1,976,760 and 1,924,660 tons, respectively. In this    regard, Colombia is ranked twelfth with a total of 398,010 tons (FAO, 2011).    Based on Collins (1960), it is presumed that the pineapple was brought to Colombia    by the Indians who spread it throughout Central and South America and reached    the West Indies. From the commercial point of view, the main producing departments    of this fruit in Columbia are Santander, where the predominant variety is Perolera,    which is sold in the domestic market, and Valle del Cauca, where the Smooth    Cayenne and Apple varieties prevail (<a href="#g1">graph 1</a>); most of the    production in the latter region is intended for export.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="g1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03g01.jpg"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Department    of Santander maintains pineapple production during the whole year, and because    it has a favorable altitude and climate, it positions itself as a leader in    the country and has a continuous presence in the domestic market. The municipalities    in which most of this activity is developed are Lebrija, Gir&oacute;n and Rionegro,    and these regions have shares of 62.6%, 22.6% and 11.6% of the total production,    respectively.<a name="top4"></a><a href="#back4"><sup>4</sup></a> However, in recent years there has been an unusual    increase in acreage that is concomitant with a moderate fall in yield (see <a href="#ap">Appendix</a>    1). Even when the gross output has followed the same trend as the acreage, the    drop in the yield leads us to predict technical inefficiency problems in this    crop. Thus, it is necessary to quantify the current levels of technical efficiency    of the small pineapple farmers of Santander and to determine the causes of the    deterioration in the productivity of acreage.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The objective of    this research is to find the determinants of the technical efficiency of small    pineapple farmers from the Department of Santander, Colombia. We should note    that this agricultural activity is characterized by a highly rural life and    the concentration of small-scale farmers, which is common in most of the fruit    crops around the country.<a name="top5"></a><a href="#back5"><sup>5</sup></a> To accomplish our objective, we will econometrically    estimate both a stochastic frontier production function and a technical inefficiency    model. The basic idea is to provide relevant information about the impact of    acreage and the socio-economic characteristics of this group of small farmers    and how these factors influence their levels of technical efficiency.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This research is    organized as follows: in Section 2, we present the theoretical foundations for    the stochastic frontier production function and the technical efficiency as    well as major empirical contributions. In Section 3, we present the methodology    that is used to achieve the stochastic frontier function and the inefficiency    model. The details of the econometric estimation are presented in Section 4.    Finally, we present the conclusions of the study in Section 5.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>2. Theoretical    Foundations</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The main motivation    for measuring the technical efficiency of production processes is to formalize    the responsiveness of the resulting yields to different inputs. The observed    variations in this responsiveness are mainly due to differences in the technology    that is used by firms, differences in the levels of efficiency of the production    processes and differences in the context in which production takes place. Therefore,    the economic efficiency is a function of the technical efficiency.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The methodology    developed by Farrell (1957) represented a first step in the modeling of technical    efficiency, as this research implies the existence of an efficient production-possibility    frontier (PPF). This methodology assumes that the PPF represents the maximum    possible output that can be achieved from a given set of productive factors.    Technical inefficiency is calculated by the difference between the production    levels of each firm and the peak level that is reached in the PPF. Thus, the    technical efficiency can be calculated as a percentage of the most efficient    production unit within the sample.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">There are two alternative    approaches for estimating this production function. Firstly, we have the non-parametric    techniques, which are distinguished by their flexibility; they are less restrictive    in the conditions that are applied to the reference technology and in the modeling    of multi-product production processes. Secondly, there are parametric methods,    which allow one to econometrically estimate a production function to make statistical    inferences on the results that are obtained in the estimation. It should be    noted that the application of these methods requires the dataset selected a    functional form. With the latter method, Aigner et al. (1977) and Meeusen and    van den Broeck (1977) introduce a stochastic production function in order to    distinguish those errors that can be explained by productive inefficiencies    from those errors that are derived from model misspecification. This discrimination    involves defining both the functional form of the production function and the    specific distribution of the error term.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Battese and Coelli    (1995) present the main empirical reference regarding the determinants of technical    efficiency in agriculture. The central conjecture these authors postulate is    the joint estimation of a model that includes both the efficient frontier of    agricultural production and the variables that influence the inefficiency of    production. Indeed, Coelli and Battese (1996) show that Indian farmers with    an older age, a larger farm and higher levels of education tend to be more efficient.    Likewise, Tian and Wan (2000) find that education, the farm size and the adoption    of multiple cropping systems have a positive effect on the efficiency of rice    production in China. Similarly, in a sample of farmers in Central Luzon, the    Philippines, Villano and Fleming (2006) find that variables such as age, education    level, the proportion of adults in the household, and the generation of income    from non-farm activities affect technical efficiency.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In contrast, in    Nigeria, Amaza and Olayemi (2002) indicate that if education, technical assistance    and the diversification of crops increase, higher levels of technical efficiency    are achieved. In the same continent, Essilfie et al. (2011) estimate the technical    efficiency of the maize crop at the farm level in Ghana. Their results show    that differences in age, gender, years of schooling, family size and farmers'    off-farm income affect technical efficiency.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In Latin America,    there is little research on the estimation of the technical efficiency in agriculture    using the stochastic frontier approach. It is worth highlighting the study of    Benoit-Cattin and Moore (1996), which estimates the technical efficiency of    a group of small coffee farmers in Guatemala. These authors conclude that both    technical assistance and credit support contribute to sustaining Guatemalan    coffee plantations. In Brazil, Concei&ccedil;&atilde;o and Ara&uacute;jo (2000)    estimate the technical efficiency of a sample of commercial farmers and find    that experience is a key factor in explaining these farmers' technical efficiency.    Additionally, the study of Richetti and Pereira (2003) examines the economic    efficiency of the productive resources that are used in the cultivation of soybeans    in the State of Mato Grosso do Sul. They show that technical inefficiency is    linked to processes of technology transfers to farmers of this grain. In Chile,    Santos et al. (2006) note that the size of a property, the distance between    a property and the main road, the age of the household head and the membership    in a group that transfers technology positively affects the technical efficiency.    In a similar study that was conducted in the same country, Moreira et al. (2006)    estimate a highly unbalanced panel dataset for a sample of small dairy farms    in Southern Chile. Their findings are as follows: there is no agro-climatic    effect, the presence of technical inefficiency is highly significant and technical    efficiency is time-variant.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">However, concerning    pineapple production, there is a lack of studies on the technical efficiency    of production that use the parametric approach. A noteworthy study is the study    of Chen et al. (2001), in which the technical efficiency of 83 pineapple farms    in China is estimated, with this result: labor is the most important factor    in production. Similarly, Adinya et al. (2010) determine the inefficiency of    pineapple production in Nigeria. Their results indicate that the farmers' levels    of education positively influence the achievement of greater efficiency in production.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>3. Methodology</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Department    of Santander is located in the Central-Eastern Region of Colombia. This Department    contributes approximately 7% to the nation's GDP, therefore, it is classified    as the fourth department in the list of the country's economically important    regions. The Department of Santander is the largest producer of Perolera pineapples    in Colombia. Small pineapple farmers in this department produced 239,130 kilograms    (kg) of this fruit in 2010, and as a result, they obtained an average yield    of 15.4 tons per acre, which is slightly above the national average of 14.6    tons per acre (AGRONET, 2012). This similarity in performance reflects the high    participation of this department in the country's aggregated pineapple production.    In fact, on comparing the yield series for Colombia and Santander, we see the    same drop in the recorded statistics of this variable over the period 2009-2010    (see <a href="#ap">Appendix 2</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The data for this    study were obtained through a survey of 194 small pineapple farmers in the Department    of Santander.<a name="top6"></a><a href="#back6"><sup>6</sup></a> The stratified random sampling technique was adopted    to select the following numbers of respondents in these three municipalities:    124 in Lebrija, 54 in Gir&oacute;n, and 16 in Rionegro. The data collection    was carried out between January and April of 2011, and these data were obtained    through direct questions to the producer that asked about his/her last harvest.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>3.1. The theoretical    stochastic frontier model<a name="top7"></a><a href="#back7"><sup>7</sup></a></i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Given a production    function <i>f</i>(<i>I</i><sub>i</sub>,</font><font  size="2">&#946;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">),    the formulation of the stochastic frontier model is as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s1.jpg"></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which <i>v</i><sub>i</sub>    is a two-sided symmetric, normally distributed idiosyncratic component [<i>v</i><sub>i</sub>    ~ <i>N</i>(0,</font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>)]    and <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> is a one-sided error that represents the technical    inefficiency. It is assumed that the errors in <i>v</i><sub>i</sub> are independent    of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>, and the sum of these two terms is the random error    </font><font  size="2">&#949;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>i</sub>.    Stochastic frontier models differ in the statistical distribution that is assumed    for the error term that corresponds to the technical inefficiency (<i>u</i><sub>i</sub>).    According to Aigner et al. (1977, p. 23), the error may have the following three    types of distribution, as it is assumed that individual firms differ in their    production practices for a given set of inputs; the exponential distribution,    in which the <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> are independently, exponentially distributed    with variance </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>;    the half-normal distribution, in which the <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> are independently    <i>N</i><sup>+</sup>(0, </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>)    distributed; lastly, the truncated normal distribution, in which the <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>    are independently <i>N</i><sup>+</sup>(</font><font  size="2">&#8733;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">,    </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>)    distributed with a truncation point at </font><font  size="2">&#8733;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">From Equation (1),    we can rewrite the stochastic frontier production model as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s2.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which <i>TE</i>    is the technical efficiency. Whenever the producer is on the efficient frontier    of production, <i>TE</i> = 1. Otherwise, <i>TE</i> &lt; 1 because <i>TE</i>    a measure of the distance of the production level that is observed with respect    to the frontier level of production. Thus, the measurement of technical efficiency    can be summarized as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s3.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">To estimate (3),    it is necessary to calculate the error term <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>, which is not    observable. Following Kumbhakar (2000, p. 78), a general expression for the    calculation of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> is:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s4.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which <i>u</i><sub>*i</sub>    and </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>*</sub>    depend on the distribution of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>, </font><font  size="2">&#934;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">(</font><font  size="2">&#8901;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    is the standard normal cumulative distribution function, and </font><font  size="2">&#8709;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">(</font><font  size="2">&#8901;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    is the standard normal distribution function.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In the case of    a half-normal distribution,</font></p>     <blockquote>        ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>u</i><sub>*i</sub>      = -</font><font  size="2">&#949;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>i</sub></font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>      /</font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup></font></p>       <p><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>*</sub>      = </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>u</i></sub></font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>v</i></sub>      / </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">For an exponential    distribution,</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>u</i><sub>*i</sub>      = -</font><font  size="2">&#949;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>i</sub>      - </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>      /</font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>u</sub></font></p>       <p><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>*</i></sub>      = </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>v</i></sub></font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Lastly, for a normal    truncated distribution,</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s5.jpg"></font></p>       <p><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>*</sub>      = </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>u</i></sub></font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>v</i></sub>      / </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font></p> </blockquote>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">It should be noted    that the stochastic frontier model is not the only method for modeling the technical    efficiency. An alternative method would be Data Envelopment Analysis (DEA),    which does not require the production function to be parameterized. This flexibility    implies the assumption that unobserved factors do not affect production decisions.    However, this assumption becomes an obstacle in the particular case of agriculture,    in which the uncertainty that is caused by weather conditions greatly affects    the chosen model. We use the stochastic frontier model to the extent that it    allows us to control the errors and uncertainty from this type of factor (AIGNER    et al., 1977; KUMBHAKAR and LOVELL, 2000).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>3.1.1. Specifying    the stochastic frontier model</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The stochastic    frontier model was initially estimated with a Translog functional specification.    However, when we tested the hypothesis of the input interaction coefficients    for the Translog model, the results indicated that the Cobb-Douglas (CD) functional    form would best fit the data of the obtained sample. The stochastic frontier    model CD is expressed as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s6.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">where <i>Y</i><sub>i</sub>    represents the yield of the <i>i</i>th small pineapple farmer, <i>I</i><sub>i</sub>    are the inputs, and the </font><font  size="2">&#946;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">'s    are the parameters that must be estimated. To estimate the model of the stochastic    production frontier (Equation 5), we used the STATA 12 command <i>frontier</i>.    The model to be estimated has the following form:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s7.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which <i>ln yield</i><sub>i</sub>    is the amount of pineapple that is produced in kilograms per acre; <i>labor</i><sub>i</sub>    is the number of workers per day per acre; <i>seed</i><sub>i</sub> is the number    of seeds used per acre; <i>defensives</i><sub>i</sub> is the amount of chemicals    that are used, and this term is computed by adding the amounts of fertilizers,    fungicides, herbicides, insecticides and pesticides that are used in production    (in liters per acre). Whereas the values of <i>v</i><sub>i</sub> represent the    occurrences that cannot be controlled by the farmer, the values of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>    represent the technical inefficiency of the pineapple exploitation. The vector    of coefficients (</font><font  size="2">&#946;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    represents the parameters to be estimated.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The stochastic    frontier model also estimates the variance parameters for certain errors, such    as the total variance of the model's errors (</font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup><i>2</i></sup>),    which is represented in this way:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s8.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>u</sub>    is the variance of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> and </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>v</sub>    is the variance of <i>v</i><sub>i</sub>. The statistical significance of </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup>    is an indicator of the quality of the fit and a test of the applied specification    assumption for the distribution of those errors that are related to the technical    inefficiency (<i>u</i><sub>i</sub>). Second, the ratio between the standard    deviation of the errors of the technical inefficiency (<i>u</i>) and the standard    deviation of the model specification errors (<i>v</i>) is represented by (</font><font  size="2">&#955;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">);    this ratio is formally expressed as:</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s9.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">If </font><font  size="2">&#955;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    approaches zero, then either </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>v</sub>    is very large or </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>u</sub>    is close to zero. Similarly, when </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub>v</sub>    is close to zero, </font><font  size="2">&#955;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    becomes large and the one-sided error becomes the dominant source of random    variation in the model. In addition, the parameter of the ratio of variances    (</font><font  size="2">&#947;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">),    which relates the variability of <i>u</i><sub>i</sub> to the total variability    of the model's errors, is defined as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s10.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This expression    is a measure of the level of inefficiency of the stochastic frontier production    model, and its outcome ranges between 0 and 1.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>3.2. The empirical    technical inefficiency model</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The model of technical    inefficiency of the production process is formalized as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s11.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The term </font><font  size="2">&#952;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    is a vector of the characteristics of small pineapple farmers that directly    influence the technical efficiency of the production processes, and these characteristics    are as follows: acreage, years of schooling, years of experience, technical    assistance, access to credit and off-farm income. The term </font><font  size="2">&#981;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sub><i>i</i></sub>    represents the errors of the model. The specification of the technical inefficiency    model is as follows:</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s12.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">which </font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup><sub>ui</sub>    represents the variance of the estimated technical inefficiency for the <i>i</i>th    farmer. We include the variable <i>acreage</i> to explain the potential obstacle    that a great acreage poses to farmers who seek to increase their yield. To measure    the levels of formal education, we incorporate the variable <i>school</i><sub>i</sub>,    which is defined as the number of years of formal education of the farmer. However,    because human capital is not exclusively accumulated through formal education,    we also consider the variable <i>exp</i><sub>i</sub>, which indicates the number    of years of experience that the farmer takes in the activity. Meanwhile, <i>offfarm</i><sub>i</sub>    represents a dummy variable that takes the value of 1 if the farmer receives    off-farm income and the value of 0 otherwise. In the field of farm management,    we include the dummy variable <i>tech</i><sub>i</sub> that takes the value of    1 if the farmer receives technical assistance and the value of 0 otherwise.    Similarly, <i>credit</i><sub>i</sub> is a dummy variable that takes the value    of 1 if the farmer has access to credit and the value of 0 otherwise. The vector    of coefficients (</font><font  size="2">&#945;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    represents the parameters that must be estimated.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In addition, we    determine the economic efficiency in the use of inputs by incorporating such    variables as the marginal value product (MVP) and the marginal factor cost (MFC).    The former variable is calculated by multiplying the marginal physical product    (MPP) by the price of the product (<i>p</i>). Formally,</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s13.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Thus,</font></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03s14.jpg"></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The MFC of an input    is the cost of an additional unit of a particular input. This datum is obtained    from the input prices. Then, following Ingosi (2012, p. 22), the relative efficiency    (R) of the use of an input is defined as the ratio between its MVP and MFC.    If R is equal to unity, the input is being used efficiently. However, if R is    greater than unity, the input is underused, and if it is less than unity, the    input is overused. Equivalently, the optimal use of an input is attained when    the MVP is equal to the MFC.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>4. Results</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">We divide the information    that is obtained from the sample of farmers into these three categories: the    production, the socio-economic characteristics of respondents, and the farm    management. The result is summarized in <a href="#t1">Tables 1</a>, <a href="#t2">2</a>    and <a href="#t3">3</a>.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t01.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a name="t2"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t02.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><a name="t3"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t03.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The typical pineapple    farm had an average size of five acres and an average yield level of 20,500    kg per acre. The number of people who were involved in harvesting activities    reached an average of 22 workers per day per acre. Furthermore, the average    amount of seeds used per acre was 5,289, which agrees with the optimal requirements    for planting in Colombia (MORALES and L&Oacute;PEZ, 2002). Moreover, we note    that, on average, farmers use 5,073 liters of defensives per acre.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The socio-economic    characteristics of farmers observed a mean age of approximately 39 years and    average levels of schooling and experience of five and 17 years, respectively.    Moreover, 97% of farmers are male and they dominate small-scale pineapple production    in Santander. In addition, 18% of the surveyed farmers engaged in an off-farm    income-earning activity. In the context of farm management, it appears that    only 11% of farmers receive technical assistance and only 21% have access to    credit.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Further analysis    of the variables that are related to human capital shows that a low level of    education is predominant in most of the farmers. <a href="#t4">Table 4</a> shows    that 81% of the surveyed farmers have educational levels below eight years,    which is the minimum required to complete a basic education. In addition, 78.4%    of these farmers have between one and 25 years of experience in the pineapple    industry.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t4"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t04.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The joint estimation    of the CD stochastic frontier function (Equation 8) and the technical inefficiency    model (Equation 13) is shown in <a href="#t5">Table 5</a>. All of the estimated    coefficients of the stochastic frontier function had a positive impact on yield,    and they were all statistically significant. The estimates reported diseconomies    of scale of 0.71, which indicates that the duplication of pineapple output per    acre would require more than doubling the amount of labor, seeds and defensives.    Nevertheless, the average value of technical efficiency that this sample of    farmers attained is 76%.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t5"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t05.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">It is evident from    the measures of variance, namely, sigma squared (</font><font  size="2">&#963;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>2</sup>)    and lambda (</font><font  size="2">&#955;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">),    that the choice of an exponential distribution for the error <i>u</i><sub>i</sub>    was the best choice, as it ensured the robustness of the model. Furthermore,    lambda (</font><font  size="2">&#955;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    indicates that variations in yield are mainly due to differences in the production    practices of farmers and not random variations. Similarly, gamma (</font><font  size="2">&#947;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    measures the share of changes in the technical inefficiency with respect to    the total variability of the model errors. Thus, the estimator of gamma (</font><font  size="2">&#947;</font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">)    indicates that 74% of the total variation in the pineapple yield is due to technical    inefficiencies in the area under study.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In contrast, the    null hypothesis that tests the technical efficiency of the sample of small pineapple    farmers of Santander is rejected at a significance level of 1% (see <a href="#t6">Table    6</a>). Because of this result, the technical inefficiency model highlights    how the variables that are related to human capital (namely, the education level    and years of experience) have a positive influence on the technical efficiency    of this group of farmers. The estimator of the variable <i>acreage</i> was statistically    significant at a 5% level, and its sign confirms that the acreage and technical    efficiency are inversely related. The estimated coefficients for the variables    <i>school</i> and <i>exp</i> were statistically significant at the 5% and 1%    levels, respectively. The remaining variables had the expected sign but were    not statistically significant.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t6"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t06.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a href="#t7">Table    7</a> shows that few small pineapple farmers achieved outstanding levels of    efficiency, and furthermore, only sixteen of them reached the highest class    of technical efficiency. Nevertheless, only 25% of the group of farmers in the    sample was below the average technical efficiency. Overall, the results highlight    the existence of a wide distribution of the technical efficiency of farmers,    and this distribution varies in a range between 0.11 and 0.95. It is remarkable    that over half of the farmers were above the average technical efficiency. This    situation reveals that technical efficiency can still be improved in the small-scale    pineapple production of this department.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t7"></a></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t07.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03f01.jpg">Figure    1</a> shows the technical efficiency according to the off-farm income, technical    assistance, and credit access. As can be seen, farmers who receive off-farm    income have a greater margin of efficiency compared to those who do not. Similarly,    farmers who have access to credit and receive technical assistance reach higher    levels of efficiency.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a href="#t8">Table    8</a> presents the measures of MPP, MFC, and MVP and includes the average physical    product (APP), which also contributes to measuring the efficiency of inputs'    use.<a name="top8"></a><a href="#back8"><sup>8</sup></a> As can be seen, <i>labor</i> has the highest MPP. Hence, an    increase of one laborer per day is estimated to increase yield by 75 kg per    acre. Similarly, an increase in defensives' application by an additional liter    is estimated to increase the pineapple yield by 0.16 kg per acre. Furthermore,    an increase of one unit of pineapple seeds is estimated to increase the total    yield by 0.41 kg per acre. However, when we evaluate the efficiency of these    inputs, we note that whereas seeds and defensives are overused, labor is underused.    A careful examination of the result of <i>seed</i> suggests that the use of    this input is close to its level of efficiency, which demonstrates that it meets    the standards for the Colombian case. Finally, the APP was greater than the    MPP for the whole set of inputs, which means that these farmers are operating    in the second stage of short-run production.</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="t8"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03t08.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>5. Conclusions</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In this study,    we used the stochastic frontier approach to measure the technical efficiency    and its determinants in a sample of 194 small Perolera pineapple farmers of    Santander, Colombia. To conduct this measurement, we estimated a production    frontier with a Cobb-Douglas functional form using inputs such as labor, the    number of seeds, and the quantity of defensives. All of the estimated coefficients    for inputs showed a positive influence on the pineapple yield, and all of them    were statistically significant. Furthermore, the sum of the elasticities of    the inputs reveals diseconomies of scale production on the order of 0.71. The    results also show that this group of farmers has an average technical efficiency    of 76%, which varies in the range of 11 to 95%. About one fourth of the sample    is below the average estimated technical efficiency. In this respect, it is    still possible for small-scale farmers to reallocate these inputs to improve    their technical efficiency.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The variables used    as the determinants of technical inefficiency indicate that an increase in acreage    does not improve the technical efficiency of these small pineapple farmers.    Moreover, the results show that this group of farmers still lacks the levels    of education and experience that are sufficient to approach optimal levels of    productive efficiency. Strictly speaking, only acreage, education, and experience    were statistically significant. Nevertheless, variables such as off-farm income,    technical assistance and access to credit did contribute positively to the levels    of technical efficiency, but they were not statistically significant.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In addition, we    considered a set of measures to assess the economic efficiency in the use of    inputs, namely, the marginal physical product, the marginal value product, the    average physical product, and the marginal factor cost. According to these results,    the small pineapple farmers of Santander are operating in the second stage of    production. In the case of seeds and defensives, the value of the marginal physical    product is less than the corresponding marginal factor cost, but the opposite    situation occurs in the case of labor. However, the use of seeds approaches    its optimal level in Santander. Therefore, these farmers can further optimize    production by increasing the use of labor and simultaneously reducing the use    of defensives.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">According to the    evidence, the policy implications are clear. Given the high and positive correlation    between the years of schooling and the technical efficiency, these farmers should    be encouraged to improve their levels of education by becoming involved in rural    extension programs such as continuing education centers for adults. Greater    efforts must be made by government institutions with regard to providing technical    assistance and promoting the training of small-scale farmers in new technologies    that would help them boost their current levels of efficiency. If these efforts    were made, small-scale farmers would be better prepared to take advantage of    increases in acreage. Furthermore, access to credit is necessary to stimulate    technological innovations that foster increases in crop yield.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Further studies    on this subject should consider the acreage as a factor that causes technical    inefficiency in the yield of fruit crops in Colombia. Another possibility would    be to conduct studies of technical efficiency on this type of crop by using    non-parametric methods such as the aforementioned Data Envelopment Analysis    to compare the results that have been obtained to date.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>6. References</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ADINYA, I., AFU,    S. and IJOMA, J. Economic meltdown and decline in pineapple production: Determinants    of production inefficiency of Pineapple-Based Alley Cropping Practices in Cross    River State, Nigeria. <i>The Journal of Animal and Plant Sciences</i>, v. 20,    n. 2, p. 107-116, 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000140&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">AGRONET, 2012.    <i>Reportes Estad&iacute;sticos.</i> Available at &lt;<a href="http://www.agronet.gov.co/agronetweb1/Estad&iacute;sticas/ReportesEstad&iacute;sticos.aspx" target="_blank">http://www.agronet.gov.co/agronetweb1/Estad&iacute;sticas/ReportesEstad&iacute;sticos.aspx</a>&gt;.    Diverse accesses. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000142&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">AIGNER, D., LOVELL,    C.A. and SCHMIDT, P. Formulation and estimation of stochastic frontier production    function models. <i>Journal of Econometrics</i>, v. 6, n. 1, p. 21-37, 1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000144&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">AMAZA, P. and OLAYEMI,    J. Analysis of technical inefficiency in food crop production in Gombe State,    Nigeria. <i>Applied Economics Letters</i>, v. 9, n.1, p. 51-54, 2002.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000146&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BATTESE, G. and    COELLI, T. A model for technical efficiency effects in a stochastic frontier    production function for panel data. <i>Empirical Economics</i>, v. 20, p. 325-332,    1995.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000148&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BENOIT-CATTIN,    M. and MENDEZ, J. C. Determinaci&oacute;n param&eacute;trico-estoc&aacute;stica    de la eficiencia t&eacute;cnica de la producci&oacute;n de caf&eacute; de los    peque&ntilde;os productores en Guatemala. <i>Investigaci&oacute;n agraria. Econom&iacute;a</i>,    n. 1, p. 117-138, 1996.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000150&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CHEN, T., YANG,    S. and PAN, T. A study on the technical efficiency of pineapple farms in Taiwan.    <i>Journal of Agricultural Research of China</i>, v. 50, n. 3, p. 88-97, 2001.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000152&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">COELLI, T. and    BATTESE, G. Identification of factors which influence the technical inefficiency    of Indian farmers. <i>Australian Journal of Agricultural Economics</i>, v. 40,    n. 2, p. 103-128, 1996.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000154&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">COELLI, T., RAO,    D. S. P., O'DONNELL C. J. and BATTESE, G. E. <i>An introduction to efficiency    and productivity analysis</i>. New York, NY, USA: Springer, 2005. 331 p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000156&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">COLLINS, J. L.    <i>The pineapple</i>: botany, cultivation and utilization. London: Leonard Hill,    1960. 294 p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000158&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CONCEI&Ccedil;&Atilde;O,    J. C. P. R. and ARA&Uacute;JO, P. F. C. Fronteira de produ&ccedil;&atilde;o    estoc&aacute;stica e efici&ecirc;ncia t&eacute;cnica na agricultura. <i>Revista    de Economia e Sociologia Rural</i>, v. 38, n. 1, p. 45-64, 2000.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000160&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ESSILFIE, F. L.,    ASIAMAH, M. T. and NIMOH, F. Estimation of farm level technical efficiency in    small scale maize production in the Mfantseman Municipality in the Central Region    of Ghana: A stochastic frontier approach. <i>Journal of Development and Agricultural    Economics</i>, v. 3, n. 14, p. 645-654, 26 nov. 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000162&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">FAO, 2012. <i>FAOSTAT-Agriculture</i>.    Available at &lt;<a href="http://faostat.fao.org/site/339/default.aspx" target="_blank">http://faostat.fao.org/site/339/default.aspx</a>    &gt;. Accessed: jul. 3. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000164&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">FARRELL, M. J.    The measurement of productive efficiency. <i>Journal of Royal Statistical Society</i>,    v. 120, n. 3, p. 253-290, 1957.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000166&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">INGOSI, A. <i>Economic    Evaluation of Factors Influencing Maize Yield</i>: In north-rift region of Kenya.    Saarbr&uuml;cken, Germany: LAMBERT Academic Publishing, 2012. 68 p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000168&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">KUMBHAKAR, S. C.    and LOVELL, C. A. K. <i>Stochastic Frontier Analysis</i>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge    University Press, 2000. 333 p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000170&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MALDONADO, J.,    MORENO, R. and VARAS, J. <i>Impactos del TLC sobre agricultura familiar y pol&iacute;ticas    compensatorias</i>: Caso Colombia. Bogot&aacute;: CEDE - Universidad de los    Andes, FAO and BID, 2007.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000172&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MEEUSEN, W. and    van DEN BROECK, J. Efficiency estimation from Cobb-Douglas production functions    with composed error. <i>International Economic Review</i>, v. 18, n. 2, p. 435-444,    1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000174&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MINISTERIO DE AGRICULTURA    Y DESARROLLO RURAL - MADR. <i>Anuario de frutas y hortalizas de Colombia</i>.    Bogot&aacute;, 2008. 80p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000176&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">______. <i>Estad&iacute;sticas    sector agropecuario</i>. Bogot&aacute;, 2012. 37p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000178&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">______. et al.    <i>Plan frut&iacute;cola y hort&iacute;cola nacional.</i> Bogot&aacute;, 2006.    80p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000180&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">______. and GOBERNACI&Oacute;N    DE SANTANDER. <i>Evaluaciones agropecuarias Santander 2009</i>. Bucaramanga,    2010. 146p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000182&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MORALES, J. and    L&Oacute;PEZ, J. <i>Manejo integrado de la mosca de la pi&ntilde;a en Santander</i>.    Bucaramanga, Colombia: Corporaci&oacute;n Colombiana de Investigaci&oacute;n    Agropecuaria (CORPOICA), Regional siete, 2001. 25p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000184&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MOREIRA, V., BRAVO-URETA,    B., CARRILLO, B. and V&Aacute;ZQUEZ, J. Technical efficiency measures for small    dairy farms in southern Chile: A stochastic frontier analysis with unbalanced    panel data. <i>Archivos de Medicina Veterinaria</i>, v. 38, n. 1, p. 25-32,    2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000186&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">PERDOMO, J. and    HUETH, D. Funciones de producci&oacute;n, an&aacute;lisis de econom&iacute;as    a escala y eficiencia t&eacute;cnica en el eje cafetero colombiano: una aproximaci&oacute;n    con frontera estoc&aacute;stica. <i>Revista Colombiana de Estad&iacute;stica</i>,    v. 34, n. 2, p. 377-402, jun. 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000188&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">RICHETTI, A. and    PEREIRA, R. The soybean production frontier and economic efficiency in Mato    Grosso do Sul, Brazil. <i>Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural</i>, v. 41,    n. 1, Bras&iacute;lia 2003, p. 45-64, jan./mar. 2000.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000190&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300026&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">SAMSON, J. A. <i>Tropical    Fruits</i>. 2nd ed. New York: Longman Scientific &amp; Technical, 1986. 335p.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000192&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300027&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">SANTOS, J., FOSTER,    W., ORTEGA, J. and RAMIREZ, E. Estudio de la eficiencia t&eacute;cnica de productores    de papas en Chile: El rol del programa de transferencia tecnol&oacute;gica de    INDAP. <i>Econom&iacute;a Agraria</i>, v. 10, p. 119-132, 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000194&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300028&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">TIAN, W. and WAN,    G. Technical efficiency and its determinants in China's grain production. <i>Journal    of Productivity Analysis</i>, v. 13, n. 2, p. 159-174, 2000.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000196&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300029&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">VILLANO, R. and    FLEMING, E. Technical inefficiency and production risk in rise farming: evidence    from Central Luzon Philippines. <i>Asian Economic Journal</i>, v. 20, N. 1,    p. 29-46, Mar. 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000198&pid=S0103-2003201300060000300030&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="back1"></a><a href="#top1">1</a>. In this article,    we use as synonyms the expressions "small farmers" and "small-scale farmers"    as well as "small-scale agriculture" and "small-scale production".    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="back2"></a><a href="#top2">2</a>. The only exception is the study of Perdomo and Hueth (2011), which measures    the technical efficiency for a sample of small coffee farmers in the Andean    Region.    <br>   <a name="back3"></a><a href="#top3">3</a>. The five main fruit crops in Colombia are, in their order of importance,    banana trees, avocadoes, mangoes, oranges and guavas (MADR, 2008).    <br>   <a name="back4"></a><a href="#top4">4</a>. These percentages are obtained from the information contained in MADR and    Gobernaci&oacute;n de Santander (2010).    <br>   <a name="back5"></a><a href="#top5">5</a>. According to MADR et al. (2006), 70% of those fruit farms that do not produce    bananas for export belong to small and medium farmers.    <br>   <a name="back6"></a><a href="#top6">6</a>. These 194 respondents represented 6.5% of the small pineapple farmers throughout    the department in 2009.    <br>   <a name="back7"></a><a href="#top7">7</a>. The theoretical derivation of the stochastic frontier model can be seen    in more detail in both Kumbhakar and Lovell (2000) and Coelli et al. (2005).    <br>   <a name="back8"></a><a href="#top8">8</a>. The APP is calculated using the formula MPP/input-output elasticity (INGOSI,    2012, p. 21).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="ap"></a><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Appendix</b></font>  </p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">1. The pineapple    output in the Department of Santander, 2000-2010</font></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03x01.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">According to data    from Agronet (2012), in the period from 2009 to 2010, whereas the total acreage    increased from 6,854 to 14,188 acres, which represents a growth of 107%, the    total yield fell from 19 to 17 tons per acre, which represents a decrease of    13%.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">2. The pineapple    output in Colombia, 2000-2010</font></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v51s1/03x02.jpg"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">According to figures    from Agronet (2012), the pineapple acreage in Colombia increased from 19,743    acres in 2009 to 27,951 acres in 2010, which represents an increase of 42%.    In contrast, the total yield increased from 16.6 tons per acre in 2009 to 15.8    tons per acre in 2010, which is equivalent to a decrease of 5%.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[ ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ADINYA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[AFU]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[IJOMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Economic meltdown and decline in pineapple production: Determinants of production inefficiency of Pineapple-Based Alley Cropping Practices in Cross River State, Nigeria]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Journal of Animal and Plant Sciences]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>107-116</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>AGRONET</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Reportes Estadísticos]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[AIGNER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LOVELL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SCHMIDT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Formulation and estimation of stochastic frontier production function models]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Econometrics]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>21-37</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[AMAZA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OLAYEMI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Analysis of technical inefficiency in food crop production in Gombe State, Nigeria]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Applied Economics Letters]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>51-54</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BATTESE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[and COELLI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A model for technical efficiency effects in a stochastic frontier production function for panel data]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Empirical Economics]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<page-range>325-332</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BENOIT-CATTIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MENDEZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Determinación paramétrico-estocástica de la eficiencia técnica de la producción de café de los pequeños productores en Guatemala]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Investigación agraria. Economía]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>117-138</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[YANG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A study on the technical efficiency of pineapple farms in Taiwan]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Agricultural Research of China]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>88-97</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COELLI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BATTESE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Identification of factors which influence the technical inefficiency of Indian farmers]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Australian Journal of Agricultural Economics]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>103-128</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COELLI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RAO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D. S. P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[O'DONNELL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BATTESE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[An introduction to efficiency and productivity analysis]]></source>
<year>2005</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York^eNY NY]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Springer]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COLLINS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The pineapple: botany, cultivation and utilization]]></source>
<year>1960</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Leonard Hill]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CONCEIÇÃO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. C. P. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ARAÚJO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P. F. C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Fronteira de produção estocástica e eficiência técnica na agricultura]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>45-64</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ESSILFIE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F. L.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ASIAMAH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[NIMOH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Estimation of farm level technical efficiency in small scale maize production in the Mfantseman Municipality in the Central Region of Ghana: A stochastic frontier approach]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Development and Agricultural Economics]]></source>
<year>26 n</year>
<month>ov</month>
<day>. </day>
<volume>3</volume>
<numero>14</numero>
<issue>14</issue>
<page-range>645-654</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>FAO</collab>
<source><![CDATA[FAOSTAT-Agriculture]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FARRELL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The measurement of productive efficiency]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Royal Statistical Society]]></source>
<year>1957</year>
<volume>120</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>253-290</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[INGOSI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Economic Evaluation of Factors Influencing Maize Yield: north-rift region of Kenya. Saarbrücken]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[LAMBERT Academic Publishing]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KUMBHAKAR]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LOVELL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. A. K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Stochastic Frontier Analysis]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MALDONADO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MORENO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VARAS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Impactos del TLC sobre agricultura familiar y políticas compensatorias: Caso Colombia]]></source>
<year>2007</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bogotá ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[CEDE - Universidad de los Andes, FAO and BID]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEEUSEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[van DEN BROECK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Efficiency estimation from Cobb-Douglas production functions with composed error]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Economic Review]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>435-444</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>MINISTERIO DE AGRICULTURA Y DESARROLLO RURAL</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Anuario de frutas y hortalizas de Colombia]]></source>
<year>2008</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bogotá ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Estadísticas sector agropecuario]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bogotá ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Plan frutícola y hortícola nacional]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bogotá ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<collab>GOBERNACIÓN DE SANTANDER</collab>
<collab>Evaluaciones agropecuarias Santander 2009</collab>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bucaramanga ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MORALES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LÓPEZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Manejo integrado de la mosca de la piña en Santander]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Bucaramanga ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Corporación Colombiana de Investigación Agropecuaria (CORPOICA), Regional siete]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MOREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BRAVO-URETA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CARRILLO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VÁZQUEZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Technical efficiency measures for small dairy farms in southern Chile: A stochastic frontier analysis with unbalanced panel data]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Archivos de Medicina Veterinaria]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>25-32</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PERDOMO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HUETH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Funciones de producción, análisis de economías a escala y eficiencia técnica en el eje cafetero colombiano: una aproximación con frontera estocástica]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revista Colombiana de Estadística]]></source>
<year>jun.</year>
<month> 2</month>
<day>01</day>
<volume>34</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>377-402</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RICHETTI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PEREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The soybean production frontier and economic efficiency in Mato Grosso do Sul, Brazil]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<month>ma</month>
<day>r.</day>
<volume>41</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>45-64</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brasília ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SAMSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Tropical Fruits]]></source>
<year>1986</year>
<edition>2</edition>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Longman Scientific & Technical]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SANTOS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FOSTER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ORTEGA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RAMIREZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="es"><![CDATA[Estudio de la eficiencia técnica de productores de papas en Chile: El rol del programa de transferencia tecnológica de INDAP]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Economía Agraria]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<page-range>119-132</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TIAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Technical efficiency and its determinants in China's grain production]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Productivity Analysis]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>159-174</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VILLANO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FLEMING]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Technical inefficiency and production risk in rise farming: evidence from Central Luzon Philippines]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Asian Economic Journal]]></source>
<year>Mar.</year>
<month> 2</month>
<day>00</day>
<volume>20</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>29-46</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
