<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0104-7183</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Horizontes Antropológicos]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Horiz. antropol.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0104-7183</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Programa de Pós-Graduação em Antropologia Social - IFCH-UFRGS]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0104-71832007000100022</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-71832007000100022</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The road to clarity: Seventh-day Adventism in Madagascar]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Peeters]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Marisa]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of California  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[San Diego ]]></addr-line>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>27</numero>
<fpage>365</fpage>
<lpage>368</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0104-71832007000100022&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0104-71832007000100022&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0104-71832007000100022&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>RESENHAS</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="4" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b><a name="ast2"></a>KELLER,    Eva. The road to clarity: Seventh-day Adventism in Madagascar. New York: Palgrave    Macmillan, 2005. 286 p. </b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>Marisa Peeters</b><a href="#ast1">*</a></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"> University of    California, San Diego &#150; United States of America </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">In this solid and    well-written ethnography, Eva Keller provides insight into Seventh-day Adventism    as it is manifested in Madagascar, more specifically in the town of Maroantsetra    and the more rural setting of Sahameloka, both situated on Madagascar's northeastern    coast. Seventh-day Adventism, a millenarian church rooted in nineteenth-century    American religious revival but now a worldwide institution, is a recent phenomenon    in Keller's field sites. Whereas in Maroantsetra the Seventh-day Adventist church    has been operative since the mid-sixties, in Sahameloka most conversions have    occurred quite recently, between 1995 and 1997. Despite the newness of the church    in her field sites, Keller explicitly states that she is not interested in uncovering    the motivations that underlie conversion. Instead she wants to address the question,    less commonly posed within the social sciences, of what "people <i>come to see</i>    in the religion that they have embraced as time goes on." (p. 7) </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Keller offers a    convincing interpretation of the nature of the longer-term religious commitment    of Maroansetra and Sahameloka Seventh-day Adventists, which she moreover presents    in a clear and structured way. Her book is composed of three parts. The first    provides necessary background information on Christianity and Seventh-day Adventism    in Madagascar. In the second, she moves to the core of her study by analyzing    the church members' everyday religious practices so as to uncover the subjective    value Adventism holds for them. She concentrates on the intellectual life of    the church members, devoting ample attention to the importance of Bible study.    "&#91;T&#93;he Adventists are not only committed to Bible study," she observes,    "they also define what it <i>means</i> to be an Adventist in terms of knowledge    of the Bible." (p. 117) The emphasis on the subjective meaningfulness of Seventh-day    Adventism taken up in the second part of the book is further elaborated in the    third and last part where Keller discusses what it means for Seventh-day Adventists    to be a member of two worlds: on the one hand the Adventist world of the church    and on the other hand the wider, predominantly non-Adventist, world of the larger    society. In her view both worlds remain quite distinct. She therefore rejects    a point of view that privileges continuity and syncretism, positing an explanation    that "allow&#91;s&#93; for human motivations that may not be explicable by specific    cultural contexts." (p. 245) With regard to the nature of the religious commitment    of the Adventists in Keller's field sites, she argues that their enthusiastic    intellectual endeavors should be seen as part of the human "desire for knowledge    for its own sake." (L&eacute;vi-Strauss 1972, p. 14; quoted on p. 245) </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">This tripartite    structure allows Keller to clearly develop the main argument of her book. She    concludes that the intellectual activities of the Seventh-day Adventists in    Maroantsetra and Sahameloka "are not epiphenomena of some other hidden motivation    to engage in Adventist practice. Rather," she argues, "the primary attraction    of Adventism is the intrinsic worth of the religious activity itself." (p. 233)    Because the emphasis is on communal investigation through dialogue, Keller sees    Adventist Bible study as distinctively Socratic in nature. However, since the    purpose is to better understand rather than to question the truth of the Bible,    she suggests that the Adventist's intellectual pursuit should be viewed in terms    of what Kuhn calls "Normal Science,' which he defines as "paradigm-based research"    (Kuhn 1996, p. 25; cited on p. 128). The paradigm in which Adventists operate    is that of the literal truth of the Bible. Given the fact that according to    the Adventist cosmology "&#91;e&#93;verything that happened in the past, that    is happening at the moment and that will happen in the future is a manifestation    of the struggle for power between God and Satan," (p. 157), the truth is not    necessarily immediately visible since it is obscured by Satan's lies and deception.    Bible study is thus of essential importance in order "to remove the Satanic    veil that blurs our perception of reality." (p. 166) In this sense Bible study    is, according to Keller, at the core of the Adventist experience because it    places them on a "road to clarity" in pursuit of "an unclouded vision of reality."(p.    167) </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Keller's cogent    and convincing argument shows a deeply insightful understanding of Adventism    as it is experienced in Maroantsetra and Sahameloka. She focuses on the intellectual    life of Seventh-day Adventists because, in her view, this comprises the essence    of the Adventist experience. The question nevertheless arises of whether, by    concentrating on this one aspect of Seventh-day Adventism, she is offering a    less comprehensive image of the church members' religious experience than could    have been possible. For example, in comparison with other studies of Seventh-day    Adventism, which usually emphasize not only the central importance of intellectualism    but also that of health, it is striking that the latter is almost entirely absent    from Keller's ethnography. She briefly points out that Adventist dietary restrictions    are easily compatible with local practices since similar restrictions are widespread    throughout Madagascar but she does not discuss if the pursuit of health is significant    for local Adventists. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">When comparing    Keller's analysis with other works on Seventh-day Adventism, in particular Bull    and Lockhart's (1989) lucid examination of American Seventh-day Adventism in    <i>Seeking a Sanctuary</i>, another interesting issue arises. Whereas Bull and    Lockhart highlight the predominance of the sense of hearing, which in their    view implies that Adventists place themselves in time rather than space, Keller    privileges the sense of sight. At the onset of her book she announces that she    wants to uncover what people <i>see </i>in Seventh-day Adventism. Her argument    revolves around the centrality of the quest for clarity. She compares being    an Adventist to looking at the world through Adventist spectacles. Keller does    not offer an explanation of why the sense of sight is privileged in her account    and one can only guess why vision is favored in this way. Perhaps this is due    to Keller's preconceptions, or perhaps vision is of central importance in Madagascar    culture, or perhaps there is yet another reason. By focusing exclusively on    the sense of sight, Keller falls short of giving a fully experiential account    of what it means to <i>be</i> an Adventist. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">Keller repeatedly    states that her purpose is to examine what it means to have a long-term commitment    to Adventism. Yet, as her ethnography unfolds, we are left with the impression    that rather than being entirely faithful to this objective she is more interested    in uncovering the discontinuities between the Adventist subculture as it is    manifested in her field sites and the surrounding culture. By doing so she does    not always give as complete of a picture as she could have. Again, the absence    of a discussion of the centrality of health practices within Adventism leaves    the reader who is familiar with Adventism with a sense of dissatisfaction. If    health practices are not experienced as significant by Maroantsetra and Sahameloka    Adventists, it would have been important to learn why, since this would entail    a significant rupture with global Seventh-day Adventism. If they are significant,    the lack of treatment illustrates how Keller does not succeed in offering a    comprehensive experiential account. Nevertheless, it is obvious that Keller's    analysis is in many ways convincing and powerful. Her endeavor to understand    the subjective value of what it means to be Seventh-day Adventist is valuable,    and her emphasis on the intellectual life of Seventh-day Adventists gives her    work a singular quality when compared to other approaches to the topic of Christianity    in the social sciences. Without any doubt, Keller has made an important contribution    to the anthropological study of Christianity. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>References</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif">BULL, Malcom; LOCKHART,    Keith. <i>Seeking a sanctuary</i>: Seventh-day Adventism and the American dream<b><i>.    </i></b>San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1989. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><a name="ast1"></a><a href="#ast2">*</a>Doutoranda    em Antropologia. </font></p>      ]]></body>
</article>
