<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0104-7183</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Horizontes Antropológicos]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Horiz. antropol.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0104-7183</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Programa de Pós-Graduação em Antropologia Social - IFCH-UFRGS]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0104-71832000000100003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-71832000000100003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Cultura in the modern city: the microgeographies of gender, class, and generation in the costa rican plaza]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Low]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Setha M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,City University of New York  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>United States of America</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2000</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2000</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<numero>13</numero>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>64</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0104-71832000000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0104-71832000000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0104-71832000000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[This article examines the microgeographies of everyday life in Parque Central and Plaza de la Cultura, two plazas located in the central city of San José, Costa Rica. These locales are created by the individual temporal and spatial attributes of plaza users whose daily movements and activities define these spaces. The growing differences of these locales in terms of the users' class, gender, and age, and their corresponding social activities, is reinforced by differences in local interpretations of the concept of cultura. These social, behavioral, and ideological differences have created spatial boundaries such that people do not cross from one locale to the other, the users do not overlap, and their representations of cultural life are seen as competitive and mutually exclusive. Based on ethnographic evidence, I suggest that this differentiation is a constructed spatial representation that symbolizes the changing nature of Costa Rican ideology and culture. The contrasting and often conflicting images of the two plazas reflect important differences in class-orientation, gender participation, and generational values that separate contemporary Costa Ricans socially, and politically. In San José, Costa Rica, cultura is often discussed as a value from the past, a cultural ideal that is desired, but that conflicts with aspects of modern life. In order to discuss how cultura remains a cultural theme in the urban plaza the everyday life and social behaviors of Parque Central and Plaza de la Cultura are compared. In this comparison time, space, and social activity change the meaning and interpretation of cultura reinforcing the contrasting metaphors expressed in the physical design of each.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Este artigo examina as microgeografias cotidianas no Parque Central e na Praça da Cultura, duas praças localizadas no centro da cidade de São José, Costa Rica. Estas localidades são criadas por atributos temporais e espaciais individuais dos usuários da praça cujas atividades e movimentos diários define este espaço. As crescentes diferenças destes locais em termos de seus usuários, classes, gêneros e idade, bem como de suas correspondentes atividades sociais, são reforçadas pelas diferenças das interpretações locais do conceito de cultura. Estas diferenças sociais, comportamentais e ideológicas criaram limites espaciais de tal maneira que as pessoas não cruzam de um local para outro; os usuários não se justapõem, e suas representações de vida cultural expressam a competição e a exclusão. Baseada em evidência etnográfica, sugiro que esta diferenciação é uma representação espacial construída que simboliza a natureza cambiante da ideologia e da cultura costarriquenha. As imagens contrastantes e freqüentemente conflitivas das duas praças refletem importantes diferenças de orientação de classe, identificação de gênero e valores geracionais que separam os costarriquenhos contemporâneos do ponto de vista social e político. Em São José, Costa Rica, a cultura aparece com freqüência nos discursos como um valor do passado, um ideal cultural desejado, mas que entra em conflito com aspectos da vida moderna. Para discutir como a cultura permanece como um tema cultural na praça urbana, o cotidiano e os comportamentos sociais no Parque Central e na Praça da Cultura são comparados. Nesta comparação, tempo, espaço e atividade social mudam o significado e a interpretação de cultura, reforçando as metáforas contrastantes que vão expressas no desenho físico de cada um.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[class]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[culture]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[gender]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[plazas]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[public space]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[spatial analysis]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[análise de espaço]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[classe]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[cultura]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[espaço público]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[gênero]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[praças]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>ARTIGOS</b></font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="4"><b><i>Cultura</i> in the modern city: the microgeographies    of gender, class, and generation in the costa rican plazacultura in the modern    city: the microgeographies of gender, class, and generation in the costa rican    plaza</b></font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>  <font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Setha M. Low </B></font>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">City University of New York – United States of    America </font></p>      <p>&nbsp; </p>      <p>&nbsp; </p> <hr size="1"noshade>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>ABSTRACT</b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"> This article examines the microgeographies of    everyday life in Parque Central and Plaza de la Cultura, two plazas located    in the central city of San Jos&eacute;, Costa Rica. These locales are created    by the individual temporal and spatial attributes of plaza users whose daily    movements and activities define these spaces. The growing differences of these    locales in terms of the users' class, gender, and age, and their corresponding    social activities, is reinforced by differences in local interpretations of    the concept of cultura. These social, behavioral, and ideological differences    have created spatial boundaries such that people do not cross from one locale    to the other, the users do not overlap, and their representations of cultural    life are seen as competitive and mutually exclusive. Based on ethnographic evidence,    I suggest that this differentiation is a constructed spatial representation    that symbolizes the changing nature of Costa Rican ideology and culture. The    contrasting and often conflicting images of the two plazas reflect important    differences in class-orientation, gender participation, and generational values    that separate contemporary Costa Ricans socially, and politically. In San Jos&eacute;,    Costa Rica, cultura is often discussed as a value from the past, a cultural    ideal that is desired, but that conflicts with aspects of modern life. In order    to discuss how cultura remains a cultural theme in the urban plaza the everyday    life and social behaviors of Parque Central and Plaza de la Cultura are compared.    In this comparison time, space, and social activity change the meaning and interpretation    of cultura reinforcing the contrasting metaphors expressed in the physical design    of each. </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Keywords:</B> class, cultura/culture, gender,    plazas, public space, spatial analysis. </font></p>      <hr size="1"noshade>        <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>RESUMO</B> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Este artigo examina as microgeografias cotidianas    no Parque Central e na Pra&ccedil;a da Cultura, duas pra&ccedil;as localizadas    no centro da cidade de S&atilde;o Jos&eacute;, Costa Rica. Estas localidades    s&atilde;o criadas por atributos temporais e espaciais individuais dos usu&aacute;rios    da pra&ccedil;a cujas atividades e movimentos di&aacute;rios define este espa&ccedil;o.    As crescentes diferen&ccedil;as destes locais em termos de seus usu&aacute;rios,    classes, g&ecirc;neros e idade, bem como de suas correspondentes atividades    sociais, s&atilde;o refor&ccedil;adas pelas diferen&ccedil;as das interpreta&ccedil;&otilde;es    locais do conceito de cultura. Estas diferen&ccedil;as sociais, comportamentais    e ideol&oacute;gicas criaram limites espaciais de tal maneira que as pessoas    n&atilde;o cruzam de um local para outro; os usu&aacute;rios n&atilde;o se justap&otilde;em,    e suas representa&ccedil;&otilde;es de vida cultural expressam a competi&ccedil;&atilde;o    e a exclus&atilde;o. Baseada em evid&ecirc;ncia etnogr&aacute;fica, sugiro que    esta diferencia&ccedil;&atilde;o &eacute; uma representa&ccedil;&atilde;o espacial    constru&iacute;da que simboliza a natureza cambiante da ideologia e da cultura    costarriquenha. As imagens contrastantes e freq&uuml;entemente conflitivas das    duas pra&ccedil;as refletem importantes diferen&ccedil;as de orienta&ccedil;&atilde;o    de classe, identifica&ccedil;&atilde;o de g&ecirc;nero e valores geracionais    que separam os costarriquenhos contempor&acirc;neos do ponto de vista social    e pol&iacute;tico. Em S&atilde;o Jos&eacute;, Costa Rica, a cultura aparece    com freq&uuml;&ecirc;ncia nos discursos como um valor do passado, um ideal cultural    desejado, mas que entra em conflito com aspectos da vida moderna. Para discutir    como a cultura permanece como um tema cultural na pra&ccedil;a urbana, o cotidiano    e os comportamentos sociais no Parque Central e na Pra&ccedil;a da Cultura s&atilde;o    comparados. Nesta compara&ccedil;&atilde;o, tempo, espa&ccedil;o e atividade    social mudam o significado e a interpreta&ccedil;&atilde;o de cultura, refor&ccedil;ando    as met&aacute;foras contrastantes que v&atilde;o expressas no desenho f&iacute;sico    de cada um. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Palavras-chave:</B> an&aacute;lise de espa&ccedil;o,    classe, cultura, espa&ccedil;o p&uacute;blico, g&ecirc;nero, pra&ccedil;as.    </font></p>  <hr size="1"noshade>      <p>&nbsp; </p>      <p>&nbsp; </p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">This article examines the microgeographies of    everyday life in <I>Parque Central</I> and <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>, two plazas    located in the central city of San Jos&eacute;, Costa Rica. These locales are    created by the individual temporal and spatial attributes of plaza users whose    daily movements and activities define these spaces. As Alan Pred has demonstrated:    </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Since each of the actions and events consecutively      making up the existence of an individual has both temporal and spatial attributes,      time-geography allows that the biography of a person may be conceptualized      and diagrammed at daily or lengthier scales of observation as an unbroken      continuous <I>path</I> through time-space subject to times of constraint.      In time-geographic terms a <I>project</I> consists of the entire sequence      of simple or complex tasks necessary to the completion of any intention-inspired      or goal-oriented behavior. (Pred, 1984, p. 256). </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The paths and projects of individual plaza users    are presented as a series of population counts, movement maps, and behavioral    maps organized by time and day within each plaza. The overlap of the movement    and behavior maps combined with ethnographic description identify a series of    distinct locales that are defined by class, age, and gender. </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The growing differences of these locales in terms    of the users' class, gender, and age, and their corresponding social activities,    is reinforced by differences in local interpretations of the concept of <I>cultura.</I>    These social, behavioral, and ideological differences have created spatial boundaries    such that people do not cross from one locale to the other, the users do not    overlap, and their representations of cultural life are seen as competitive    and mutually exclusive. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Based on ethnographic evidence, I suggest that    this differentiation is a constructed spatial representation that symbolizes    the changing nature of Costa Rican ideology and culture. The contrasting and    often conflicting images of the two plazas reflect important differences in    classorientation, gender participation, and generational values that separate    contemporary Costa Ricans socially, and politically. These differences can be    understood through the use of Richardson's concept of <I>cultura</I> in the    plaza and Costa Ricans ongoing public discourse about culture. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In his study of the plaza in Cartago, Costa Rica,    Miles Richardson (1978, 1980) is able to link phenomenologically different places    by contrasting the cultural importance of being "proper" in the plaza    with being "smart" in the marketplace. </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The terms, <I>cultura </I>(culture) and <I>progreso      </I>(progress), which appear frequently in the conversations of people talking      about the qualities of life in small SpanishAmerican towns, come close to      expressing the contrast. <I>Cultura</I> is the victory of SpanishAmerican      civilization over nature and over the bestial aspects of human behavior. The      plaza, by its very greenery and by its behavior, leisurely strolling under      the trees, epitomizes <I>cultura</I>. (Richardson, 1980, p. 226). </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">He resolves the different images of public life    as being separated, yet integrated, by space and experience. Miles Richardson    is concerned with how we know how to behave and experience places differently    while maintaining a sense of continuity of the experiential world. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">This article expands Richardson's analysis of    the plaza as a place of <I>cultura</I> by comparing the two central plazas,    located a block away from one another, as different and competing expressions    of <I>cultura</I> in San Jos&eacute;. The ethnographic examples illustrate the    way in which differences in users, social activities, built environment, and    symbolic intentions reinforce the contrast between the two places. I argue that    it is the difference between the plazas and between the users and their activities    that constructs the perceived boundaries between the two places, and that these    spatial boundaries mark social and political locales which have become naturalized    and "concretized" over time. Even though they are located almost next    to one another, they represent distinct facets of Costa Rican culturethe traditional,    Spanish, hierarchical, predominantly older male, Catholic culture of the past;    contrasted to the modern, younger, male and female, North American culture of    the present. Although symbolic elements of each force their way into both plazas,    the hegemony of the traditional or the modern ideology of <I>cultura</I> remains.    Yet the class and culture tensions, and fears about social contact and public    expression, continue unresolved highlighting the political nature of these cultural    expressions. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In San Jos&eacute;, Costa Rica, <I>cultura</I>    is often discussed as a value from the past, a cultural ideal that is desired,    but that conflicts with aspects of modern life. In order to discuss how <I>cultura</I>    remains a cultural theme in the urban plaza the everyday life and social behaviors    of <I>Parque Central</I> and <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> are compared. In this    comparison time, space, and social activity change the meaning and interpretation    of <I>cultura</I> reinforcing the contrasting metaphors expressed in the physical    design of each. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Rhythms of everyday life </b></font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Three specific kinds of data were collected and    analyzed to describe everyday plaza life: population counts by gender on a typical    (not a holiday or rainy day) week-day and Sunday, movement maps by gender at    two hour intervals on a typical day, and behavioral maps of group activities    by time and place. These counts and maps provide quantitative data and physical    evidence of plaza users' activities supplementing interpretations made based    on qualitative sector observations, participant observation, and unstructured    interviewing. Taken together, these data identify the locales, paths, and projects    that mediate the actions of individual plaza users with the social structural    differences and spatial boundaries observed between the two plazas. Thus, individuals    produce these social and spatial boundaries by their everyday plaza routines    and practices. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Population counts</b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The plazas were counted in fifteen minute intervals    alternating between fifteen minutes before and fifteen minutes after the hour    in each. Counts were recorded on a clipboard, transferred to a summary sheet,    and then added together by category to complete the analysis. Two people counted    at a time, one recording women and the other recording men whenever possible.    The results are presented in the following series of population count charts    and compared by day of the week and by plaza. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In <I>Parque Central</I> there is so much activity    on Sunday that it is hard to see any pattern other than differences in the number    and location of men and women. Men and women are spatially separated into distinct    concentric rings, with women usually seated and men standing (see Plan of<I>    Parque Central</I>, Map 1). On Sundays at 10:00 a.m. the band plays drawing    a large crowd of men, women, and children who stand on the kiosk or sit on benches    to listen. Sunday morning is the only time when there are a large number of    people there, yet compared to the crowd at 4:00 p.m., there are still fewer    women and children present: 30% women at 10:00 a.m. compared to 34% women at    4:00 p.m, and 16% children in the morning compared to 23% children at 4:00 p.m.(<a href="#tab01">See    Table 1</a>). </font></p>     <p><a name="tab01"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03tab01.gif"></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The total number of people in <I>Parque Central</I>    on a Sunday, is twice that of a week-day, composed of families and couples,    rather than single males: 35% women on Sunday as compared to 20% women during    the week (<a href="#tab01">See Tables 1</a> &amp; <a href="#tab02">2</a>). Children    (ages 0-12) make up 10% of the population on Sunday, compared to 3% during the    week, while teen-agers and children together (ages 0-19) make up 23% of the    Sunday population, and only 6% on a week day. The Sunday crowd also fluctuates    widely reflecting the presence or absence of local entertainment such as the    band playing or the "soccer" man bouncing a ball with his head that    attracts spectators (<a href="#tab01">See Table 1</a>). On Sunday there are    women in the park throughout the day, making up as much as 40% of the total    population at 2:00 p.m (<a href="#tab01">See Table 1</a>). During the week,    on the other hand, most women are at home or work in the morning, and do not    go out until after the main noon meal is served. There is a steady increase    in the proportion of women users throughout the day with the largest number    of women (37%) present at 6:00 p.m. (<a href="#tab02">See Table 2</a>).</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><a name="tab02"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03tab02.gif"></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> is spatially organized    quite differently from the concentric circles of separated men and women in    <I>Parque Central</I> (see Plan of<I> Plaza de la Cultura</I>, Map 2). Instead    people arrange themselves in a series of tiers from the most visually exposed    to least visually exposed: the most exposed is highest tier next to the National    Theater and the Gran Hotel, the second is the transitional space between the    main plaza and the lower level, and the third is the grassy area in front of    the lower area where the tourist office, art gallery, and gold museum are located.    The first tier is made up of families, single men and women, and couples; the    second, middle-aged and older men; and the third, young single men. Edge zones    are particularly important and desirable, especially along the railings and    on the pipe benches. The edge along Central Avenue is dominated by teen-agers    at night, but during the day the composition of who occupies it often changes.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">There is also a clear pattern of sun and shade    distribution of users and spectators. On sunny days girls and women eat their    lunches sitting in the shade of the fringe of trees along the side of the National    Theater, while men stand under the trees in the area in front of the National    Theater. Students in uniforms, both male and female, and some men reading papers    occupy the small bench seats in the shade of the fig trees along the shopping    arcade. Only young men sit on the sunny benches along the back ledge watching    those cross the plaza. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">On Sundays <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> is used    by more women than men (52% women overall) even in the early morning (<a href="#tab03">See    Table 3</a>). Children under 12 years of age make up 25% of the total population,    and teen-agers from ages 13 to 19 make up another 33%. This unusual population    pattern of 52% women and 53% teen-agers and children on Sundays, compared to    35% women and 12% teen-agers and children on week days, provides further evidence    that the plaza is perceived as an appropriate and comfortable place for families,    and even more importantly, mothers and children to relax and play when they    have leisure time (<a href="#tab03">See Tables 3</a> and <a href="#tab04">4</a>).    </font></p>     <p><a name="tab03"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03tab03.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab04"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03tab04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">On week days the most dramatic change in population    composition is the appearance of mothers and children in the afternoon (<a href="#tab04">See    Table 4</a>). Mothers are free after lunch and their young children are out    of school, so they bring them to play in the fountain, chase the pigeons, and    then sit on the shaded benches and planter ledges. By 6:00 p.m., on a beautiful    evening, <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> is full of people. On the lowest tier next    to the tourist office, couples sit and hold hands, while a young adult crowd    fills the second and intermediate levels. On the main plaza, teen-agers gather    along the planter edge: boys play soccer interrupted by flirting with girls    or sing accompanied by a blaring radio. Other young people fill the fountain    edges, and a few older men and couples remain seated under the fig trees. The    population counts reflect these changes: the largest percentage of women and    children (46%) can be found at 2:00 p.m., but the plaza remains 37% female even    at 6:00 p.m. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The population patterns found in <I>Plaza de    la Cultura</I> are not unlike that of<I> Parque Central </I>except that there    are many more women and teen-agers and children on a week day afternoon and    on Sunday. In <I>Parque Central</I> the percentage of women and children increases    on Sunday, but not to the degree of <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>, since it is    still perceived as the domain of men and workers. The total population <I>of    Plaza de la Cultura</I> is also much smaller, only a third of the number of    people counted <I>at Parque Central</I> on Sunday (503 compared to 1576), and    half of the number of people counted in <I>Parque Central</I> on a week day    (466 compared to 939). </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Overall, then, <I>Parque Central</I> retains    the largest number of people, both on Sundays and on week days, while <I>Plaza    de la Cultura</I> has the highest percentage of women, teen-agers and children    both during the week and on the week-end. Based solely on the population counts,    gender and age differences by day and time define the two public spaces. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Movement maps</b> </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Pedestrian movement in the two plazas is another    way to describe the rhythms of everyday life. Movement maps were created by    recording the pathway of each pedestrian during a fifteen minute or thirty minute    observation period. Vicky Wulff Risner, a dance ethnologist at the Library of    Congress, worked with me to develop a simplified system of notation based on    her extensive research experience recording dance in its cultural context. She    worked out a system that recorded pathways used as well as gender and estimated    ages of the observed pedestrians. The entrances were rotated throughout the    observation period, and notes were made of who was sitting in the plaza at the    time and other significant behavioral details (e.g. the pedestrian shakes another    man's hand as he walks through). </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Movement maps were collected from 8:00 a.m to    6:00 p.m. in both plazas. Maps 3, 4, and 5 record observations in <I>Parque    Central</I> on Thursday, July 31, 1986, a day that started out cloudy and damp,    but became sunny in the afternoon. At 8:00 a.m. a few men were moving from northwest    to east, and east to west and southwest, while only two women, a young woman    and an elderly woman in a couple, journey in a southernly route across the park.    By 10:00 a.m. more people are crossing and circling moving from the northwestern    to eastern pathway that faces the Cathedral. There are still more men than women,    and only men are exiting at the southwestern corner (See Map 3). By noon the    direction of movement shifts significantly as the majority of people exit at    the southwestern corner: these seem to be men and a few women catching the buses    home that stop along Fourth Avenue (See Map 4). The afternoon is the busiest    time with many more women moving through, mostly in an eastern to southwestern    direction. Between 4:00 and 6:00 p.m. the flow of people reversing their morning    journey reaches its peak. People exit both east and west, but the western exit    is used predominately by young men going to the bars located on the western-northwestern    edge of the park (See Map 5). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The movement maps from Wednesday, June 18, 1986    on <I>the Plaza de la Cultura,</I> Maps 6, 7, and 8 record a similar pattern    with an increase in activity from the morning to the early afternoon. There    is one popular pedestrian pathway from the southwest corner near the entrance    to the Gran Hotel and the National Theater to the northeast corner on Central    Avenue that is used as a shortcut by people moving in either direction (See    Map 6). At 4:00 p.m., however, there is a lull when a sudden rain storm temporarily    stops all activity. Only four young men venture out into the rain during the    half hour observation period (See Map 7). But by 6:00 p.m. activity has picked    up again. A secondary pathway from northwest to southeast emerges with men walking    in either direction, from Pops ice cream store on Central Avenue (northwestern    corner) to the lower level of the plaza and Second Avenue where there is a bus    stop that services the eastern part of the city (See Map 8). </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Comparing the movement maps of <I>Parque Central</I>    and <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> adds another dimension to the way in which the    spaces are used and experienced differently. The maps describe "rivers"    of movement that make up time-geography paths, segregated for the most part    into male and female spheres. When integrated with participant observation field    notes and photographs of people walking, the movement maps indicate that there    are two major types of people in each plaza: those who are traveling through    the space; and those who have taken up residence by sitting on a bench or leaning    on a wall. Many people move from one category to another, of course, but overall    there seems to a residential and a transient population on both plazas. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">What is noteworthy, however, is the manner in    which the two groups interact with each other, which is different in each plaza.    In <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>, people take up residency in large part to watch    the non-residents and other residents move through the rivers and along the    paths. In <I>Parque Central,</I> however, the residents much are less interested    in the non-residents who move through the space. This difference in group interaction    illustrates a kind of "closed-society" versus "open-society"    behavioral ecology. <I>Parque Central</I> with its internally focused groups    of men, talking and reading and not necessarily interacting with passers-by,    could be characterized as a closed-society, socially and spatially bounded by    cultural rules and notions of tradition and <I>costumbre</I> (custom). <I>Plaza    de la Cultura,</I> on the other hand, consists of outwardly focused groups of    men and women, who are constantly looking around, talking to passers-by, and    frequently break out of the group to meet someone or to join another group.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The design of the <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>    certainly reinforces this openness and increases the possibilities of interacting    across groups; while the shaded, enclosed corners of the pre-1994 <I>Parque    Central</I> provide more privacy and seclusion. But the differences observed    in the interaction and movement patterns express more than just the design of    the space: here is an example of the landscape architecture and the cultural    rules reinforcing each, and it is difficult to segment out the extent to which    each playing a determinant role. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Behavioral maps</b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Although the plazas are very different in history,    design, and representation, the daily activities that occur there are similar.    Yet the people who perform these activities are again quite different. These    different groups of people define the public space of the plaza in terms of    their distinct social worlds. This difference is significant in that these users    – and their distinct social worlds – socially construct an "outofawareness"    (nondiscursive) boundary maintaining system. For instance older men and women,    female prostitutes, shoeshine men, and gamblers are almost exclusively found    in <I>Parque Central</I>. On the other hand, tourists, young women and children,    students in uniforms, teen-agers with boomboxes, and North American pensioners    are almost exclusively found on <I>the Plaza de la Cultura</I>. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The following description of a sunny weekday    in January, 1987 illustrates the similarities and differences. Observations    were made continuously and in timed samples recorded on behavioral maps from    8:00 a.m. until 10:00 p.m., although the majority of activity occurred during    the late morning, afternoon and early evening. A few of the behavioral maps    are included to illustrate the points made, however, the bulk of the maps were    used as the data base for this summary. The maps were drawn on 8 &#189; inch    x 11 inch plaza plans using black ink and colored pencils to record various    ongoing behaviors and locations of individuals. Since the colored pencil data    could not reproduced here, circles and written descriptions are used in an attempt    to convey the richer data of the originals. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Parque Central </b></font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the <I>Parque Central</I> morning is a time    for men to sit and read the newspaper. By 10:00 a.m. almost every bench is filled    with an adult man reading his paper (See Map 9). The shoeshine business in the    northeast corner is slow, and vendors of fruit and the lottery are not doing    much business. The passersby are mainly on their way to the bus or shopping.    The most active person is the municipal employee who sweeps the sidewalks and    picks up fallen leaves and trash. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">By noon the tempo has pickedup (See Map 10).    The men on their benches are joined by friends with animated voices as the walkways    fill with men and women meeting for lunch or catching the bus home. The healer    starts his routine in the northwest corner and the missionaries set up under    the arbor. One group of elderly men leave the <I>Parque Central</I> at this    time to go home for lunch and siesta and do not return. Others leave, but will    return after their lunch. As one seventy year old man said: "The plaza    is now my place of employment now that no longer work. I am underfoot at home.    The house is my wife's domain, and I feel better being out of the house during    the day." </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the afternoon, a few older women appear bringing    their children to the library, shopping with friends, or resting from a busy    morning in town (See Map 11). The shoeshine business is at its peak as middleclass    men stop to get their shoes shined on their way back to work. Sometimes, during    the midafternoon, "Vicky" begins his routine with a guitar and hat    telling sordid jokes on the kiosk platform. Vendors of ice cream, peanuts and    snowcones circulate along the edge of the crowd. The police walk by in pairs,    stop and watch for awhile, and then continue on their patrol of the street.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">By 4:00 p.m. most of the older men have left    and young and middleage couples meet in <I>Parque Central</I> for coffee and/or    to take the bus home. The number of women is the highest at this time, still    only making up about twenty to thirty percent of the population, but very different    from the all male reading period of the morning. At 6:00 p.m. the light begins    to fade and the air is cooler (See Map 12). A new group of vendors with carts    of hot corn or skewered beef appear on the edge of the sidewalk. As couples    circumambulant around the kiosk, they stop to buy food and talk to the vendors    drawn by the smell of the sizzling grilled beef. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">At 7:00 p.m. it becomes quiet. The shoeshine    men have left for the day, and only a few couples, some single young men and    the vendors remain. If it is a nice evening, more people will wander by on their    way to the Rex Cinema or to have drink in the Soda Palace. A small group of    street kids run by trying to beg money from a passing <I>gringo </I>and tired    young prostitutes sit under the arbor waiting for business. By now the lines    of the buses are not as long and tired workers wait in groups talking about    the day or buying lottery tickets from the corner vendors. Later in the evening,    between 9:00 and 10:00 p.m., <I>Parque Central</I> is almost completely deserted    except for one or two solitary men sitting on the benches or walking slowly    down the paths. Even later, men from the countryside, drunk and sleepy may find    their way from the cheap bars surrounding the central market to sleep relatively    undisturbed on the park benches until morning. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Plaza de la Cultura</b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> the day also    starts slowly. During the morning there are very few people, usually just a    couple of men or male tourists reading a newspaper in the sun, and a group of    green uniformed plaza employees who sweep and empty the trash cans. Sunday is    a little busier with the artisan market for the tourists, but even then there    is little activity. </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">About noon the older North Americans, known as    <I>gringos verdes</I>, or "green" Yankees, appear in their baseball    hats, sunburns and smiles (See Map 13). They will stay for most of the afternoon    waiting for girls or watching those that walk by. These men are a mixture of    regular tourists who come each winter to enjoy the weather and <I>pensionados</I>,    North Americans who have elected to retire to Costa Rican fulltime, and who    claim tax and other benefits from the Costa Rican government with their guaranteed    monthly pension from the United States or Canada. Students, young office workers,    and friends sometimes stop to have their lunch in the plaza or buy ice cream    at the nearby Pops and sit a moment to finish eating. Tourists are in the cafe    having lunch or wandering in front of the National Theater buying souvenirs    or taking pictures. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">By 2:00 p.m. the pace quickens as more and more    office workers return to work walking through on their way from the bus stop.    Young mothers and children stop to look at the fountain or to play with the    pigeons during a shopping outing. Students, finished with classes stop to meet    friends while they are still in their school uniforms. On some afternoons a    clown and his wife/assistant, or a Peruvian musical group may come by. The clown    performs almost in the center of the plaza attracting children and their parents    as well as the downtown office crowd. The Peruvian singers play in the tourist    area and draw a crowd of tourists and young adult Costa Ricans. Later an evangelical    group with guitars, singing popular songs in praise of Jesus might entertain    a bored teen-age crowd. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">At 4:00 p.m. the <I>gringos</I> leave for their    afternoon coffee and rest, and many of the families start on their way home    (See Map 14). By 5:00 p.m. or so, however, teen-agers in blue jeans begin to    appear (See Map 15). They play music on portable radios or tapedecks, dance,    and even start soccer games on the far end of the main open space. They are    the major occupants until the National Theater opens at 8:00 p.m. Sometimes    there are special evening events, such as a tribute to local high school bands    or a radio interview of teenages who are there. If there is no performance at    the National Theater, the plaza becomes quiet by 8:00 p.m. as the teen-agers    leave to go on their evening destinations. Later in the evening, after 9:00    p.m. single men, gather on the lower plaza near the theater ticket window to    meet and talk. Groups of young men often wander by, or stop to smoke marijuana.    In a few cases policemen passed by and arrested one of the young men either    for drinking or having drugs on him. The encounters, however, were brief and    carried out in hushed tones. The atmosphere in the lower plaza is more relaxed    than frightening, as the men share their thoughts and wait to meet friends.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">It is apparent from these two descriptions that    the activities of reading, talking, eating, and meeting friends are the same.    Both plazas are dominated by men and their related activities of reading, sitting,    watching and talking in the morning, and accommodate women, families and children,    and couples in the afternoon. They both have vendors who sell flowers, food    and trinkets; people who provide personal services; entertainers who sing or    clown; and preachers of various denominations. They are both surrounded by cafes    where users can go to get inside from the rain or sun or where nonusers can    simply survey the scene. They both have a small number of people who want to    lay claim to the space, but who are considered by some to be undesirable occupants    of the space such as beggars, prostitutes, homeless people, drug dealers and    gamblers. Police who patrol and maintenance people who clean up the trash are    also there representing the municipal social order. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">What seems more important, however, is not that    the activities are the same – although this sameness may indicate some common    cultural response to the use of public space – but that the activities take    on such different forms and meanings, and are performed by such different people.    For example, the cafes of <I>Parque Central</I> are populated only by menwhen    a woman enters one of these cafes it cases a minor stir. The cafes on the <I>Plaza    de la Cultura</I>, on the other hand, are frequented by both men and women,    usually tourists and upper or middle class Costa Ricans. The prostitutes in    <I>Parque Central</I> are young female Costa Ricans who are professionals and    who solicit men of all ages and nationalities. The young women who meet men    in <I>the Plaza de la Cultura</I>, however, call themselves <I>tourras</I>,    which I was told means that they engage sex for a nice meal or clothes, but    not for money or as a professional occupation. The <U>tourras</U> are involved    mostly with older men, often North American pensioners or tourists, who come    to Costa Rica searching for very young women, and for a sexual, and sometimes    loving relationship. The expectations of both older men and young women vary    from romantic to mercenary, and the reality of the relationships vary as well.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Other examples of the contrast in the expression    of social activities include what is sold: tourist items, popcorn, and balloons    in the <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> and lottery tickets, food and newspapers in    <I>Parque Central</I>; the difference in the green uniformed maintenance men    in the plaza and the municipal maintenance man's rag shirt in the <I>Parque    Central</I>; the presence of a large number of foreigners in the <I>Plaza de    la Cultura</I> and the absence of many foreigners in <I>Parque Central</I>.    The contrast can be summarized as the emerging social divisions of young and    old, foreign and local, lower and middle class, and male and female now spatially    and temporally distributed across the two plazas. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">These differences in expression reiterate the    historical and physical comparison, that of the separation of an identification    with modern North American or international culture in the <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>    and the maintenance of a more traditional Costa Rican identity in the <I>Parque    Central</I>. Taken together, yet separated and bounded by their difference,    the two plazas express the contemporary dimensions, contradictions, and tensions    of Costa Rican culture. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The new plaza built only one block northeast    of <I>Parque Central</I> was to be a reflection of contemporary culture, based    on different values and by its difference created a "symbolic space,"    a "spatial boundary" between the images of Costa Rican <I>cultura    </I>produced in these two places. The social boundary that separates these two    worlds is one that is constructed more by the contrast than by any physical    or social barrier that exists between the two plazas. In fact, one would think    that the shoeshine men, the pensioners, the couples and the vendors would travel    between the two plazas depending on weather, business and amount of crime or    disturbance that might exist in <I>Parque Central</I>. Yet, the residents of    <I>Parque Central</I> remain firmly in place and regard the new plaza as suspect.    They say that the new plaza is an uncomfortable place where the "wrong"    people hang out, while the residents of the <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> describe    <I>Parque Central</I> as dark and dangerous. One explanation of this separation    of the two places is that the new plaza, in fact, was created to reconstitute    Costa Rican culture with a different image in an attempt to disenfranchise the    older more traditional representation of social life presented daily in <I>Parque    Central</I>. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Thus, the contrast between the two plazas is    significant; their histories, design, and users are in many ways distinct. Within    the <I>Parque Central</I> there is very little contested space in that a long-term    pattern of users and activities has built up over the years. New activities    such as the Christian healing are accommodated either at the edges of the plaza    or through the reallocation of space in time. The <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I>,    however, is still a highly contested arena; tourism and the Costa Rican image    of <I>cultura </I>conflict with the nightly appropriation by "cruising."    The separation between the two plazas is a cultural gulf with older retired    and working men dominating one scene and students, young women, women and children,    tourists and teen-agers recreating on the other. Both are Costa Rican representations    of <I>cultura</I>, however, they represent different versions of that cultural    goal. There is an invisible boundary between them, yet, their commonalities    link them. Culture is not some homogeneous set of rules for life, but is made    up of conflicting and fluctuating images and aspirations. </font></p>      <p>&nbsp; </p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Conclusion</b></font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The behavioral maps complete the time-space descriptions    begun with the population counts and movement maps. While the movement maps    describe paths that link individuals walking with gender segregation in the    <I>Parque Central</I>, the behavioral maps record individual projects such as    men shining shoes, elderly pensioners meeting to talk, or teen-agers playing    soccer. The accretions of multiple paths and projects located in space and time    link the individual activities to age, gender, and class differences found in    the two plazas. Over time these differences become naturalized, as has been    argued by Bourdieu (1977), and perceived as social reality. Thus, individual    paths and projects are transformed into cultural norms for behavior re-enacted    in daily social practices. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">These microgeographies help to demonstrate how    plaza meanings are socially constructed through historically constituted social    practices, political ideologies, users' behaviors, group activities, and urban    design to represent and reproduce different aspects of Costa Rican culture.    This social construction occurs through the historical and sociopolitical forces    that created each plaza and through the paths and projects that create the distinct    social worlds presented here. These differences are reinforced by the social    practices of the people who inhabit these spaces. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The social and spatial boundaries that separate    these two spheres that are so physically close, yet so culturally different,    are social constructions and meaningful at the level of lived experience of    everyday life. They provide clues as to the significant schisms in what otherwise    seems like a very homogeneous culture. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">For example, culturally ideal gender roles in    which the woman/housewife stays at home, and the man/provider goes out to work    and to the public realm of the plaza are breaking down with women needing and/or    wanting to work in response to changes in the political economy. The cultural    norms of <I>Parque Central</I> restricted women's attendance to Sundays and    late afternoons accompanied by their partners or children, leaving them without    a public space. Thus, <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> has become an important alternative    space and a means of expressing this new cultural definition of gender roles.    </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In a similar vein, the social status of being    a teen-ager has become more important with the influx of North American capital    and culture that includes age-specific modes of dress, music, and behavior.    Before the 1970's most teen-agers were working adults. I remember interviewing    adolescents from 1972 through 1974 who said that after the sixth grade (age    12 or 13), that they were expected to go to work. In the countryside and in    very poor urban households this expectation may still hold, but in the city    most San Jos&eacute; teen-agers go to school and many hang-out to meet their    friends. The <I>Plaza de la Cultura</I> provides the new public space necessary    for this change in culturally proscribed behavior, and its open design allows    for the possibility of dancing and playing soccer in the urban center. </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The increasing social divisions and socioeconomic    inequality resulting from the impact of global market forces, the influx of    North American capital, local economic crises, and shifts in modes of production    also have resulted in segmenting and redefining the Costa Rican class system.    This segmentation can be seen in the differences in cultural ideals reflected    in the notion of <I>cultura</I>. The traditional myth that <I>Costa Rica es    diferente</I>, that Costa Rica was historically a country of small farmers that    produced an egalitarian class structure, has been disrupted by obvious differences    in wealth, increasing segregation of residential neighborhoods, increasing unemployment    and underemployment, and dismantling of the legislated safety net of social    security, basic food subsidies, and other social welfare programs. Older Costa    Ricans will still tell you that "we are all middle-class" if you ask    about class structure, but increasingly young people and the disenfranchised    point out that things are changing, and that while everyone may be the same    politically, that they no longer are in terms of wealth. These changes in class    are also expressed in the discourse concerning behavior and activities in the    plazas and are captured in the cultural metaphor, and social sanction, of <I>cultura.</I>    Thus, class, gender, and age differences separate these two social and spatially    bounded domains, as well as the cultural notion of <I>cultura</I>. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Acknowledgements</b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The research for this article was made possible    by a Fulbright Research Fellowship, a grant-in-aid from the Wenner Gren Foundation    for Anthropological Research, and a fellowship from the John Simon Guggenheim    Foundation. I would like to thank Vicky Risner for her help both in the field    and in conceptualizing the movements maps. I would also like to thank Stephane    Tonnelat for producing the maps for this publication. Parts of this analysis    are discussed in my just published book, On the Plaza: The Politics and Culture    of Public Space by the University of Texas Press. I would like to thank Ruben    Oliven for his interest and support of my plaza work over the past fifteen years.    </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp; </p>      <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>References</b> </font></p>      <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">BOURDIEU, Pierre. <I>Outline of a Theory of Practice</I>.    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000105&pid=S0104-7183200000010000300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>      <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">PRED, Alan. Structuration, biography formation,    and knowledge.<I> Environment and Planning D. Society and Space</I>, v.<I> </I>2,    p. 251-275, 1984.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000107&pid=S0104-7183200000010000300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>      <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">RICHARDSON, Miles. La plaza como lugar social:    el papel del lugar en el encuentro humano. <I>Vinculos</I>: Revista de Antropolog&iacute;a    del Museo Nacional de Costa Rica, v. 4, p. 1-20, 1978.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000109&pid=S0104-7183200000010000300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>      <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">RICHARDSON, Miles. Culture and the urban stage:    the nexus of setting, behavior, and image in urban places. In: ALTMAN, I.; RAPOPORT,    A.; WOLHWILL, J. F. <I>Human behavior and environment</I>. 1980. p. 209-242.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000111&pid=S0104-7183200000010000300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref -->    </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">RICHARDSON, Miles. Being-in-the-market and being-in-the-plaza:    material culture and the construction of social reality in Spanish America.    <I>American Ethnologist</I>, v. 9, p. 421-436, 1982.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000113&pid=S0104-7183200000010000300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>        <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig01.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig02.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig03.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig04.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig05.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig06.jpg"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig07.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig08.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig09.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig10.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig11.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig12.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig13.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig14.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/ha/v6n13/a03fig15.jpg"></p>       ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BOURDIEU]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Pierre.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Outline of a Theory of Practice]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PRED]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Alan.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Structuration, biography formation, and knowledge]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Environment and Planning D. Society and Space]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<page-range>251-275</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RICHARDSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Miles.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[La plaza como lugar social: el papel del lugar en el encuentro humano]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Vinculos: Revista de Antropología del Museo Nacional de Costa Rica]]></source>
<year>1978</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<page-range>1-20</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RICHARDSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Miles.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Culture and the urban stage: the nexus of setting, behavior, and image in urban places]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ALTMAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RAPOPORT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WOLHWILL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Human behavior and environment]]></source>
<year>1980</year>
<page-range>209-242</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RICHARDSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Miles.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Being-in-the-market and being-in-the-plaza: material culture and the construction of social reality in Spanish America]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[American Ethnologist]]></source>
<year>1982</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<page-range>421-436</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
