<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032006000300005</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032006000300005</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Agricultural subsidies in the United States and their effect on two annual Chilean crops: corn and wheat]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Osorio]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[José Díaz]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Rojas]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Roberto Jara]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidad de Talca Departamento de Economia Agrária ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Chile</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2006</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2006</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<fpage>437</fpage>
<lpage>466</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000300005&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000300005&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032006000300005&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[The development strategies for Chile have been oriented toward a greater commercial openness. Chile and the United States signed a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) that has triggered controversies between producers directed to the internal market due to the production and export subsidies that this country carries out. This study analyzed the effect of subsidies granted by the United States to wheat (Tritricum aestivum) and corn (Zea mays) growers (Farm Bill 2002). For the study, Technical Standard sheet were drawn up, from which were determined the direct production costs and the gross margins. The variables used (market prices, subsidies, freight costs and tariffs) and determining the average variable costs allowed us to do a sensitivity analysis, thus establishing the minimum level of production that national farmers must achieve in order to maintain competitiveness while a free trade is in force. The signing of a trade agreement could provoke the eventual withdrawal of many Chilean producers from the business arena while at the same time, favoring consumers with lower prices for the goods derived from these grains.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Subsidies]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Protectionism]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Traditional Crops]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Free Trade Agreement]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[competitiveness]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font size="4" face="verdana"><b>Agricultural subsidies in the United States    and their effect on two annual Chilean crops: corn and wheat</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Jos&eacute; D&iacute;az Osorio<sup>I</sup>;    Roberto Jara Rojas<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><sup>I</sup>Professor do Departamento de Economia    Agr&aacute;ria da Universidad de Talca, Chile. <a href="mailto:jdiazoso@utalca.cl">jdiazoso@utalca.cl</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Departamento de Economia Agr&aacute;ria, Universidad de Talca,    Chile. <a href="mailto:rjara@utalca.cl">rjara@utalca.cl</a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The development strategies for Chile have been    oriented toward a greater commercial openness. Chile and the United States signed    a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) that has triggered controversies between producers    directed to the internal market due to the production and export subsidies that    this country carries out. This study analyzed the effect of subsidies granted    by the United States to wheat (<i>Tritricum aestivum</i>) and corn (<i>Zea mays</i>)    growers (Farm Bill 2002). For the study, Technical Standard sheet were drawn    up, from which were determined the direct production costs and the gross margins.    The variables used (market prices, subsidies, freight costs and tariffs) and    determining the average variable costs allowed us to do a sensitivity analysis,    thus establishing the minimum level of production that national farmers must    achieve in order to maintain competitiveness while a free trade is in force.    The signing of a trade agreement could provoke the eventual withdrawal of many    Chilean producers from the business arena while at the same time, favoring consumers    with lower prices for the goods derived from these grains.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B>Key words: </b>Subsidies, Protectionism, Traditional    Crops, Free Trade Agreement, competitiveness    <br>   <B>JEL Classification: </b>Q 18</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Introduction</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">A country with a limited internal market such    as that of Chile requires an active participation in the international market    in order to maintain a sustained rhythm of growth. Approximately 50% of the    goods and services that are transacted in the country in one year form part    of Chile’s foreign trade (Pro Chile, 1995). In agreement with the policy of    international insertion propounded by Chile, the country has underwritten in    the last decades various multilateral or bilateral agreements tending to generate    a gradual commercial openness, translating into a reduction of tariffs or custom    duties. As of 2002, and after a long and difficult negotiation, Chile and the    United States signed, in 2003, a Free Trade Agreement, which came into effect    in 2004 (Silva, 2003). </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This fact has far reaching consequences given    that an agreement has been signed with the main economic power in the world,    which signifies access to a market of 284 million people with a high power of    consumption and a <i>per capita</i> GDP reaching US$35,300 (ODEPA, 2003). However,    this event has generated more than one controversy, especially in the traditional    agricultural sector of our country. Without a doubt the main discussion is about    the effect that the American government’s agricultural subsidies will have on    Chilean agriculture, specifically on the so-called traditional crops. As a result    of this new development, the objective of this study is to quantify the effect    of certain types of farm subsides granted by the U.S. on traditional crops in    Chile, measured through the production of two important grains.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>The farming sector in the United States</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">According to the information from the World Trade    Organization (WTO, 2000) the U.S. is the biggest importer and exporter in the    world given that it alone has 12% of the world trade. By comparison, Chile participates    in only 0.2% of the world trade.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">According to the American Agricultural Census,    the most relevant aspects of this sector would be:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Of the 377.09 million arable hectares, 174.48    million are dedicated to annual crops and fruit (47.3%).    <br>   • Under a system of special programs for annual land retirement (Acreage Reduction    Program), there are 11.93 million hectares in fallow (3%).    <br>   • Forestry occupies a surface area of 28.92 million hectares.    <br>   • Land for haying or grazing amounts to a surface area of 160.92 million hectares.    <br>   • The average size of farming operations is about 197.09 hectares.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>The United States Farm Bill 2002</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The new American agricultural law, Farm Security    and Rural Investment Act, was passed the 13<SUP>th</SUP> of May in 2002, and    replaced the FAIR Act of 1996. The application of this law came into force in    2002 and will extend until 2007 (Methol, 2002). This bill, reaching at $248.6    billion dollars, means an 80% increase in agricultural subsidies over those    of the FAIR Act of 1996 (Mittal, 2002). </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"> The principal objectives of this law are:</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• To generate adequate income for farmers.    <br>   • To supply food at reasonable prices    <br>   • Maintain a competitive international position.    <br>   • Support the conservation and protection of the environment.    <br>   • Maintain the viability of the product industry.    <br>   • Maintain an adequate level of reserves in case of production problems.    <br>   • Reach all the previous objectives at the lowest possible cost to the American    government.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Although the new law is organized in ten Titles,    only the first three (Commodities Program, Conservation and Trade) have direct    impact on the trade of agricultural goods (Basco, 2002). The same author indicates    that the most important title and the one to which the greater part of the budget    is assigned, is the Commodities article. This includes diverse support programs    for the following products: wheat, corn, rice, sorghum, barley, forage crops,    oats, soybeans and cotton.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The Commodities Programs are:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">- Guaranteed Loan Rates    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   - Compensatory Payments    <br>   - Fixed or Direct Payments    <br>   - Guaranteed Real Price    <br>   - Target Price    <br>   - Counter-cyclical Payments</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The guaranteed loan rate and fixed payment plans    existed in the 1996 law, consequently the most relevant change is the counter-cyclical    payment program that reestablishes target prices with the objective of maintaining    the income of the producers.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">While the Farm Bill of 1996 established maximum    annual amounts of direct payments, the new agricultural law does not. The direct    payments vary between US$ 5.8 billion in 1998 and 4 billion in 2002 of which    nearly 85 % of these amounts were distributed among wheat (26 %), corn (46 %),    and cotton (12 %). Nevertheless, the new Farm Bill establishes specific amounts    per ton of produce. That is to say, there is no established total annual maximum    amount of aid, but rather;- it depends on the levels of production (Basco, 2002).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Economic relations between Chile and the United    States</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Trade negotiations bring together two countries    that are significantly unequal in terms of size, economic development and political    power. This inequality is expressed in the first place by the <i>per capita</i>    income (US$ 35,300 in the U.S. versus US$ 4,500 in Chile). In the second place,    although the U.S. is the number one trade partner of Chile, our country occupies    the 38<SUP>th</SUP> place among the U.S. foreign trade partners.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The trade balance between the two economies presents    a historically unfavorable deficit for Chile even though in the last two years,    this situation has turned around (see <a href="#tab03">Table 3</a>).</font></p>     <p><a name="tab03"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05tab03.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Chilean exports to the U.S. come principally    from the exploitation of natural resources. In 1996, the 37.3% of these exports    came from raw materials and 55% from natural resources with some level of processing.    These percentages did not change significantly during the nineties and the beginning    of the year 2000. During 2002, raw materials represented 31% of the total exports    while processed natural resources reached 59.1%. As of this year, industrial    goods have maintained a 7-10% part of the total exports to the U.S. On the other    hand, the exports from the U.S. to Chile are principally made up of intermediate    goods such as petroleum, lubricants and other fuels. In 1996, these represented    51% while in 2001 they reached 53% of the imports. Capital assets participated    in1996 with 40% of total imports and in 2001 this amount decreased to 38% (Silva,    2003).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Chile – U.S. Free Trade Agreement: case history    for wheat and corn</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In overall terms, at the end of twelve years    100% of the trade between Chile and the U.S. will be free. However, it is important    to mention that a large percentage of products will be able to be traded without    tariffs as soon as the FTA comes into force.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to imports, 88.5% of the American    products will immediately have lowered tariffs and, in the case of Chilean exports,    87% of the products will be able to enter on the American market in the same    manner.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Concerning the farming sector, 87% of the produce    exported by Chile will remain with zero tariffs at the moment of confirming    the treaty while only 62% of the products sent to our country from the U.S.    will obtain this freedom from duties (ODEPA, 2003).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For wheat, the main supplying countries in order    of importance are: the United States, Argentina and Canada. In order to export    wheat to Chile, these countries are currently subject to an <i>ad valorem</i>    tariff of 8%, to which must be added the specific right or from which must be    subtracted the discount in accordance with the current price list. However,    with Argentina there is a Chile-MERCOSUR trade agreement that will allow the    entrance of this commodity free from the <i>ad valorem</i> tariff only in 2014.    As for Canada, the signing of the FTA with Chile will allow the free entrance    of this grain as of the year 2014 (ODEPA, 2001). In agreement with the treaty    with the U.S., the tariff reduction corresponds to a non linear type in 12 years,    from a tariff of 31.5% (consolidated maximum in the WTO). In the following four    years, the tariff is reduced to 21% to later become duty free (Ministerio de    Econom&iacute;a, 2002).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Concerning corn, the principal suppliers are    Argentina and the U.S. For the first country there is a real tariff of 4% but    in accordance with the agreement Number 35 Chile-MERCOSUR, corn <U>will enter</u>    duty free as of 2006. On the other hand, corn coming from the U.S. is subject    to a tariff of 8%, but when the FTA comes into force, corn will immediately    be totally duty free (ODEPA, 2001).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Objectives</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>General Objective</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• To quantify the effect that applying American    agricultural subsidies has on two Chilean agricultural products, wheat and corn.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Specific Objectives</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Determine, according to the Farm Bill 2002,    the subsidy contribution granted by the U.S. government to its farmers for these    two products.    <br>   • Determine, for different scenarios, the effect of importing wheat and corn    from the U.S. on the degree of competitiveness of Chilean producers.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Materials and Methods</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The information used in carrying out this study    comes mainly from two sources:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Background statistics obtained from the United    Nations Organization for Food and Agriculture (FAOSTAT); from the United States    Department of Agriculture (USDA); from the Oficina de Estudios y Pol&iacute;ticas    Agrarias (Office of Agricultural Research and Policy) (ODEPA) and from the Banco    Central de Chile. In addition to these sources, information was compiled about    cultivated surface areas, production volume, yields, prices and the trade balance    between Chile and the U.S.    <br>   • Bibliographic information obtained from reviewing magazine articles, research    and publications on the FAIR Act of 1996 and the Agricultural Farm Bill of 2002.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In order to prepare the technical data about    crops, research and articles from the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA),    Departmento de Econom&iacute;a Agraria de la Universidad de Talca (Agricultural    Economics Department), the Instituto de Investigaciones Agropecuarias (INIA)    (Agricultural Research Institute), and Fundaci&oacute;n Chile.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">From the American market prices for wheat and    seed corn in the 2002-2003 season, subsidies granted by the American government    to its farmers under Title 1 (referring to commodities) of the Farm Bill were    determined.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This law establishes the following prices and    payments as detailed below:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Guaranteed Loan Rates.    <br>   • Compensatory Payments    <br>   • Fixed or Direct Payments    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   • Guaranteed Real Price, which corresponds to loan rates plus fixed payments    <br>   • Target price, which is the minimum amount farmers received per ton of produce.    <br>   • Counter-cyclical payments, which are activated when the income of the producers    falls below the Target Price, which is determined for each crop.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Guaranteed loan rates and the target prices are    fixed by the American government, while the fixed payments are determined based    on the sown surface area and the yields obtained corresponding to the 1998 –    2001 period. The compensatory payments are paid out only when the market price    falls below the guaranteed loan rates. The counter-cyclical payments are activated    when the producers’ income falls below the target price, that is, when the market    price plus the fixed payment is inferior to the target price. In the case where    the market price was less than the guaranteed loan rate, the counter-cyclical    payment would correspond to the following equation:</font></p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05frm01.gif"></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">All the prices and payments previously detailed    were calculated in dollars per 100 kilograms (US$/100 kg.).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The wheat and corn technical data for Chile,    as well as the U.S., are found in the attached tables. For the latter country,    a standard data card for both grains was considered, where the items for production    factors and items are grouped together, but not so for farm labor. In addition,    considering that the biggest and best producers in the U.S. receive a greater    amount of subsidies, a high technological level for both countries was assumed.    On the other hand, given the differences between the crop data cards for each    country, a standard card was adapted for these which included all the items    in the production process (see <a href="#tab04">Table 4</a>). The above-mentioned    card allowed a more homogeneous comparison and analysis of the competitive position    in which the Chilean producers for both crops find themselves.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab04"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05tab04.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">According to <a href="#tab04">Table 4</a>, the    production costs in the U.S. for both crops consider: seeds, fertilizers, pesticides.    In addition, the item "Agricultural machinery expenses" includes diesel    oil, oil and repairs; the item "Other Costs" includes water rights    payments; the item "Labour" includes personal and contracted hours    of work. The items "harvest and freight" were not included as direct    production costs due to the following suppositions:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The big agricultural producers in the U.S.    have their own machinery and transport.    <br>   • Wheat farmers cultivate on average 30% of their total lands to this grain.    That is why that percentage is associated with machinery depreciation as a direct    production cost, allowing a more homogeneous comparison with Chilean producers    that posses a high level of technology.    <br>   • In the case of corn producers, 40% of the total cost of machinery depreciation    was considered as a direct production cost, since these farmers dedicate, on    average, this percentage of their total cultivation area to this cereal.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The production costs for wheat and seed corn    in Chile, include seeds; fertilizers; pesticides (herbicides, fungicides and    insecticides); for the item "Agricultural machinery costs", the cost    of the payment for such services was considered (that is, machinery depreciation    is not included); other costs (unexpected items which correspond to 5% of the    total direct cost); labor, harvest costs (equivalent to the cost of the service    of an automotive harvester) and finally, freight. For this last item the following    suppositions are made:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">- Wheat freight costs: $350 pesos/100 kg (4.99    US$/ton).    <br>   - Corn freight costs: $430 pesos/100 kg (6.13 US$/ton).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The technical data cards for both countries were    valued in dollars per hectare (US$/h.), using the average price of the dollar    in July of 2003.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The Gross margin per hectare was also calculated    using the following equation:</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05frm02.gif"></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In the case of the U.S., the payments made by    the Government through the Farm Bill 2002 (Title I) were added, and those payments    were added to the Gross Margin. Determining wheat and seed corn production costs    for both Chile and the U.S. allowed making a comparison between the Gross Margin    and Average Cost Variables for both countries.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">To determine the import costs to Chile of wheat    and corn coming from the U.S., the market prices of these products for the 2002-03    season, plus the freight, insurance and current tariffs were considered.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">As well, the effect of importing wheat and corn    from the U.S. on the national agricultural market was analyzed, which permitted    us to measure the degree of competitiveness for the Chilean producers of these    grains.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The latter was done through a sensitivity analysis    with respect to the import cost (measured in US$/100 kg) of wheat and corn,    compared with the variable average cost for national producers. The sensitivity    analysis in the case of corn was done considering two types of producers: those    using their own fields for their productive process and those who do the process    in rented fields, which currently represent a significant percentage of the    total cultivated surface area.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following scenarios were studied:</font></p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05img01.gif"></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The terms are defined as:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">- Fixed Payment, determined by the Farm Bill    2002 for wheat and corn in the 2002/03 season.    <br>   - Counter-cyclical Payments (Title I, Farm Bill 2002).    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   - Export Subsidies: Amount assumed by the U.S. government, to finance part of    the costs associated with the marketing of export goods among which freight    and insurance costs are highlighted.    <br>   - Tariff: Tax which affects the importing of wheat and corn from the U.S.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Results</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Agricultural production subsidies in the    United States</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The main peculiarity of the new Farm Bill is    its counter-cyclical character establishing the target prices, this is, payments    in direct relation to production levels. Until the year 2001, producers were    receiving direct payments calculated according to the cultivated surface area    in the middle of the 90’s and the yields obtained in the decade of the 80’s.    The Farm Bill 2002 updates to the 1998 – 2002 period the surface areas on which    the direct payments are based, and updates the yields to the same period for    the counter-cyclical payments. Those farmers, who cultivated their fields more    intensively from 1996 on, expecting their representatives to lobby Congress    to increase the amounts of the subsidies to be paid, managed to increase their    incomes coming from the payments based on the prior law.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Direct production subsidies for wheat.</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In Figure 5.3 the following subsidies for the    period 2002-2003 are observed:</font></p> <table width="580" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="350" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Guaranteed loan        rates</font></td>     <td width="230" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">US$10.29/ 100        kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="350" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Fixed payments</font></td>     <td width="230" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">1.91/ 100 kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="350" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The sum of the        guaranteed loan rates and the fixed payments corresponds to the guaranteed         real price</font></td>     <td width="230" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">12.19/ 100 kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="350" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Target price</font></td>     <td width="230" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">14.18/ 100 kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="350" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The difference        between the target price and  the guaranteed real price corresponds to        the  maximum counter-cyclical payment</font></td>     <td width="230" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">1.98/ 100 kg</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The counter-cyclical payments depend on the market    price of wheat, which is not the case for fixed payments. If the market price    falls lower than the guaranteed loan rate (zone 1 in <a href="#fig03">Figure    3</a>) there is a compensatory payment in order to reach the guaranteed loan    rate, after which the fixed payment and the maximum counter-cyclical payment    are made in order to arrive at the target price (US$/100 kg – 14.18 in the 2002-03    season). The agricultural law established a limit of US$ 75,000 per farmer for    the compensatory payments.</font></p>     <p><a name="fig03"></a></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05fig03.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">If the market price is located in zone 2, the    fixed payments and the counter-cyclical payments (not maximum) are made in order    to reach the target price.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">When the market price is located in zone 3, the    fixed payments are made and the counter-cyclical payments are activated only    when the market price plus the fixed payment do not reach the target price.    Finally, if the market price is greater than the target price (zone 4) the fixed    payments are still made but the counter-cyclical payments are not.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Wheat production subsidies for the period 2004-2007    had an established guaranteed loan rate of 10.10 US$/100 kg, a guaranteed real    price of 12.01 US$/100 kg (the fixed payment was maintained at 1.99US$/100 kg)    and a target price of 14.40 US$/100 kg, with which the maximum counter-cyclical    payments arrived at 2.39 US$/100 kg.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The price given to the producer by the USDA in    July of 2003 was 12.19 US$/100 kg. If the target price was fixed at 14.18 US$/100    kg, the difference (1.99 US$/100kg) would be contributed by the Farm Bill (1.91US$/100    kg by fixed payment and 0.08US$/100 kg by counter-cyclical payments).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Production for the 2002/03 season was estimated    at 51.32 million tons, where each ton would cost the American government US$19.90    in direct subsidies, which means that the annual contribution to wheat farmers    via the Commodities Program of the Farm Bill 2002 would be slightly over 1.021    billion dollars. Since the surface area sown with wheat in the 2002/03 season    was 18,542,000 hectares involving an average yield of 2,800 kg/h., each hectare    should receive a payment of US$55.06. If we consider the yields (3,500 kg/h.)    obtained by farmers possessing a high level of technology, these farmers would    receive US$ 69.65 per hectare by way of direct subsidies.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Direct production subsidies for corn</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Just the same as for wheat, there are two periods    where the subsidies granted by the U.S. government to corn producers vary. For    the period 2002-2003, the following values were established for subsidies:</font></p> <table width="580" border="0" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Guaranteed loan        rate  </font></td>     <td width="280" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">7.80 US$/100        kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Fixed payment        </font></td>     <td width="280" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">1.10 US$/100        kg </font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Guaranteed real        price</font></td>     <td width="280" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">(GLR +FP) 8.90        US$/100 kg </font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Target price</font></td>     <td width="280" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">10.24 US$/100        kg</font></td>   </tr>   <tr>      <td width="300" valign="top"><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Maximum counter-cyclical        payment</font></td>     <td width="280" valign="bottom"><font size="2" face="Verdana">1.34 US$/100        kg</font></td>   </tr> </table>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In the same manner as shown in Figure 5.3, if    the market price for corn corresponds to Zone 1 (below the guaranteed loan rate),    the compensatory payments are activated, then the fixed payments and the maximum    counter-cyclical payments until reaching the target price of 10.24 US$/100 kg    for the 2002/03 season. When the market price is in Zone 2, the fixed payments    and the counter-cyclical payments (not maximum) are made in order to arrive    at the target price. If the market price is located in Zone 3, the fixed payments    and the counter-cyclical payments come into effect only if the market price    plus the fixed payments do not reach the target price. If the market price exceeds    the target price (Zone 4) only the fixed payments are made.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For the period 2004-2007 a guaranteed loan rate    was fixed at 7.68 US$/100 kg; the guaranteed real price was 8.78 US$/100 kg    (the fixed payment was maintained at 1.10 US$/100 kg); the maximum counter-cyclical    payment was established at 1.57 US$/100 kg; and finally, the target price reached    10.35 US$/100 kg, 0.11 US$/100 kg more than the 2002-2003 period.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The price of corn granted to the producer by    the USDA in July of 2003 was 8.65 US$/100 kg. If the target price was fixed    at 10.24 US$/100 kg, the difference (1.59 US$/100 kg) would be contributed by    the Farm Bill (1.10 US$/100 kg by fixed payment and 0.49 US$/100 kg via the    counter-cyclical payments).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The production for the 2002/03 season was estimated    at 225.54 million tons therefore each ton would cost the U.S. government US$    15.90 in direct subsidies which means that the annual contribution through the    commodities program of the Farm Bill 2002 would be 3.586 billion dollars for    corn. Since the surface area sown with corn in the 2002/03 season was 28,050,000    hectares involving an average yield of 8,040 kg/h., each hectare should receive    a payment of US$127.83. Considering the yields (9,000 kg/h.) obtained by farmers    possessing a high level of technology, these farmers would receive US$143.10    per hectare by way of direct subsidies.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Analysis of the competitiveness of Chilean    corn and wheat producers. Comparison of direct production costs between Chilean    and American wheat and corn growers</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to wheat, <a href="#tab05">Table    5</a> presents a comparison of the direct costs of production in Chile and the    U.S. for the year 2003. As well, this Table shows the gross margins (US$/h.)    for yields produced with a high level of technology, that is, 6,500 kg/h. for    Chile and 3,500 kg/h. for the U.S. The prices used in this analysis (July 2003)    were 17.68US$/100kg in the case of Chile (ODEPA, 2003) and 12.19US$/100kg for    the U.S.(price estimated by the USDA). This table also shows the subsidies granted    to American farmers via the Farm Bill 2002 whose amount corresponds to the difference    between the market price (12.19US$/100 kg) and the target price-2003 (14.18US$/100    kg); that is 1.99US$/100 kg. Said amount multiplied by the quantity of grain    produced gives rise to a subsidy of US$69.65/ hectare. Variable average costs    (US$/100 kg) were lower in the U.S., however the great difference in yield and    price per hundredweight, resulted in Chile’s gross margin being 138% greater.    This percentage would increase to 229% if the government of the U.S. did not    directly subsidize the production of agricultural goods.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab05"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05tab05.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In Chile, the direct production costs for corn    reached US$1,006.83 / h., (US$415.80/h. more than in the U.S.). However, the    variable average costs are slightly lower in Chile mainly due to its yield levels    (15,500kg/h. versus 9,000 kg/h. in the U.S.).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Direct subsidies for the production of corn in    the U.S. correspond – as do those for wheat – to the difference between the    market price (8.65US$/100kg) and the target price-2003 (10.24US$/100 kg), that    is 1.59 US$/100 kg. Said amount multiplied by the yield (9,000 kg/h.) gives    us a total subsidy of US$ 143,10/h.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The differences between gross margins, without    considering subsidies, are greater in Chile by US$574.25/ h. than in the U.S.    Upon inclusion of the subsidies, the difference between gross margins lowers    to US$431.10/h. In other words, through subsidies alone, the corn producers    in the U.S. increase their gross margin by 76.33%, reflecting the great influence    that subsidies have on agricultural production, which in this case corresponds    only to Title 1 of the Farm Bill 2002.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In Chile, when the rent of land is included in    the direct production costs, they increase to US$1,231.47 per hectare; therefore    the variable average costs also increase. The gross margin is US$ 537.53 per    hectare, that is, 29% less than that of the producers who do not rent land.    Nevertheless, considering the market prices of 2003, this gross margin remains    competitive compared to that obtained by American producers (330.57 US$/h.).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In this scenario, the Chilean producers’ gross    margin exceeds by US$206.96/h. that obtained by their American counterparts    even with the subsidies that they receive. Without taking into consideration    the item "rent of land", the difference in these gross margins is    US$270.46/h., 52% greater.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For both wheat and corn production the differences    in the use of agricultural products for production of these grains in the two    countries call our attention:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">- Seeds: Chilean producers use a significantly    greater amount of seeds than the U.S. producers, which is reflected in the density    of plants per hectare permitting higher yields.    <br>   - Fertilizers: For both crops, a great difference in the use of these products    is shown. It could be thought of as excessive fertilization in Chile; however    the difference clearly points out the strength/density of the crops. While in    Chile there is a very intensive crop growing, the producer in the U.S. opts    for much more extensive crops corresponding to the size of the properties and    the availability of labour. The quantity of fertilizer used is also evident    in the crop yields in each country.    <br>   - Agricultural chemical products: In the case of wheat, the use of a greater    quantity of these products is observed in Chile mainly due to continuously planting    the same crop (one-crop systems), of which the consequence is an increase in    plant diseases. In the case of corn, the U.S. shows a higher level of use of    agricultural chemicals, nevertheless they are considered within the normal range    and, as in Chile, a reasonable use is made of them.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Wheat Producers</i></b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The difference between the FOB and CIF prices    in 2003 was 17.50 US$/ton. It can be assumed that this difference corresponds    to marketing costs, especially maritime freight plus the cost of insurance.    However, the values given by the Compa&ntilde;&iacute;a Sudamericana de Vapores    (CSAV) indicate that the cost of transporting grain from the east coast of the    U.S. to the port of San Antonio, Chile was US$ 1,575 per container (40-foot,    maximum weight of 26.681 tons); that is, 59.03 US$/ton. Consequently it is assumed    that there would be an export subsidy that would cover 70.33% of the costs associated    with exporting goods (freight and insurance, f+i) between the U.S. and Chile.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The tariff on wheat coming into our country from    the U. S. corresponds to an 8% <i>ad valorem</i> the sum of which should be    adjusted to the price list in force. On average, up to August 2003, the CIF    value of a ton of wheat coming from the U.S. reached US$ 148.52. If we add the    8% tariff to this amount, we arrive at a total of 160.40 US$/ton, a value very    close to the floor of the list in force for wheat (161 US$/ton).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following sensitivity analysis makes reference    to the cost of importing 100 kg of wheat from the U.S. according to the various    scenarios mentioned in the methods section. These values are compared with the    cost of producing 100 kg in Chile (AVC, Average Variable Cost) for producers    with a high level of technology, that is, those who produce 6,500 kg/h. and    whose direct production costs are 548.17US$/h. (AVC = 8.43US$/100 kg). The fixed    payments and the counter-cyclical payments correspond to direct production subsidies    for agriculture in the U.S. The fixed payment was 1.91US$/100 kg, while the    counter-cyclical payment corresponds to the difference between the target price    – 14.18 US$/100 kg in the 2002/03 season – and the market price (12.19 US$/100    kg) plus the fixed payment. That is to say, CCP = TP – (market price +FP). According    to this formula, the counter-cyclical payment was 0.08 US$/100 kg.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In the scenarios where the fixed payments and    the counter-cyclical payments are included, these will be discounted from the    direct production costs and will be seen reflected in a decrease in the AVC    (<a href="#fig04">Figure 4</a>). As previously mentioned, the subsidy associated    with marketing export products plus the cost of insurance covers 70.33% of the    freight costs. In the cases which include an export subsidy, the cost of freight    and insurance will be 1.75 US$/100 kg, while in the cases where there is no    export subsidy, these costs will be 5.90 US$/100 kg. The <i>ad valorem</i> tariff    of 8% represents an additional cost of 1.19 US$/100 kg and it is calculated    using the average CIF value (August 2003) for a ton of wheat coming from the    U.S. (148.52 US$/ton).</font></p>     <p><a name="fig04"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05fig04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Case 1 of <a href="#fig04">Figure 4</a> shows    a favourable scenario for the national producers who possess an AVC of 8.43    US$/100 kg, given that the cost of importing one 100 kg of wheat from the U.S.    is 14.06 US$/100 kg without considering subsidies and including the tariff.    The American export subsidy greatly affects the lowering of import costs per    100 kg of wheat if we compare the costs where an export subsidy is granted to    those where only the direct production subsidy is applied (case 6 versus case    4).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Currently the import cost per 100 kg of wheat    coming from the U.S. is US$ 7.92 (case 8), an amount which leaves the national    producers unable to compete. To obtain the AVC they would have to increase their    yields from 6,500 to 6,852 kg/h. or else, reduce their direct production costs    by 5.3%. Case 9 graphs a situation that includes the opening of the wheat market    facing subsidized agriculture where the import cost per 100kg of wheat is US$6.73.    In this case, in order to maintain their competitiveness the Chilean producers    would have to obtain a yield over 8,000 kg per hectare (obtaining an AVC of    6.73 US$/100 kg) or, reduce their direct costs by 20.19%.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>Corn producers</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The difference between the CIF and Fob prices    in 2002 reached 9.09 US$/ton. For the year 2003, the CIF price (without tariff)    for one ton of grain coming from the U.S. was estimated at 124 US$/ton, while    the Golfo FOB value was 109.10 US$/ton, making a difference of 14.90 US$/ton.    As previously mentioned, the cost of freight plus insurance between the U.S.    and Chile was 59.03 US$/ton, estimating a 74.75% subsidy for freight and insurance    (f+i) from the U.S. government. Hence the explanation of why grains sent from    the U.S. arrive in our country at price ranges that are competitive with, or    even inferior to, the price of grain from other countries that have lower freight    costs such as Argentina. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The tariff on corn shipments from the U.S. corresponds    to 8% <i>ad valorem</i>. With the coming into force of the FTA, an immediate    tariff reduction would take place. If the tariff is discounted from the entry    price of corn (134.06 US$/ton in July 2003) imported from the U.S., it would    fall to 124 US$/ton, which would be lower than the current price of corn imported    from Argentina (128.36 US$/ton).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following sensitivity analysis makes reference    to the import cost per 100 kg of corn from the U.S. assuming the same scenarios    that were used for the wheat analysis. These values are compared with the cost    of producing 100 kg of corn in Chile (AVC) for producers with a high level of    technology, producing 15,500 kg/h. and whose direct production costs are 1,006.83    US$/h., that is with an AVC of 6.50 US$/100 kg.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The fixed payments and the counter-cyclical payments    correspond to direct agricultural subsidies for corn production in the U.S.,    with the fixed payment being 1.10 US$/100 kg while the counter-cyclical payment    corresponds to the difference between the target price – which was 10.24 US$/100    kg in the 2002/03 season- and the market price (8.65 US$/100 kg) plus the fixed    payment, arriving at a counter-cyclical payment of 0.49 US$/100 kg.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In cases where fixed payments and counter-cyclical    payments are included, these will be deducted from the direct production costs    and will be seen reflected in a decrease in the AVC (see <a href="#fig05">Figure    5</a>). The export subsidy covers 74.75% of the costs associated with trading    this product (freight and insurance, f+i). Thus, in cases where the export subsidy    is included the cost of freight and insurance will be 1.49US$/100 kg, while    in the cases not including the export subsidy, the cost will be 5.90 US$/100    kg.</font></p>     <p><a name="fig05"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05fig05.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The 8% <i>ad valorem</i> tariff represents an    additional cost of 0.99 US$/100 kg and is calculated on the estimated CIF value    in January – August of 2003 for one ton of corn coming from the U.S. (124.00    US$/ton).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">As in the nine cases previously analyzed, <a href="#fig05">Figure    5</a> graphs the different import costs for 100 kg of corn coming from the U.S.    in terms of AVC, freight + insurance, and tariffs. In Case 1, a scenario where    there are tariffs but no subsidies, the cost of importing corn is 13.45 US$/    100 kg, which is a very favouable for national corn producers possessing an    AVC of 6.50 US$/100kg. Just as for wheat, the export subsidy has a greater percentage    of influence on the import value than the direct product subsidy has. That is    to say that the export subsidy on 100 kg of corn coming from the U.S. is more    detrimental to national producers than the second subsidy mentioned (Case 6    versus Case 4).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For the year 2003, the cost of corn coming from    the U.S. was 7.45 US$/100 kg (Case 8), which allowed national corn producers    to still be competitive.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Case 9 graphs a scenario where corn is imported    from the U.S. with the corresponding subsidies granted by the U.S. but without    tariffs. Here, the cost of importing corn is 6.46 US$/100 kg, a value lower    than the AVC of national producers. This case makes clear the effect of the    current tariff on corn imported from the U.S. (8% <i>ad valorem</i>). </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It must be noted that with the coming into force    of the FTA, this product will have an immediate tariff reduction, a situation    as presented in Case 9. In this scenario, producers find themselves in a rather    unfavourable position for maintaining adequate competitiveness (measured by    the AVC, they will have to produce a minimum of 15,585 kg/h.).</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">For Chilean producers who rent land, which today    is a very common practice involving a large surface area of corn (Departamento    de Econom&iacute;a Agraria, 2001), the AVC increases from 6.50 to 7.94 US$/100    kg. In this case, so that these farmers can maintain their competitiveness,    they would have to produce 19,000 kg/ h. or else reduce their production costs    by 18.7%.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">After having done this analysis, we can firmly    state that with respect to shipments from the U.S. the loss of competitiveness    for the corn producers in our country (whether they rent the land or not) is    due to the large quantity of subsidies involved. Seen in this manner, one form    of confronting this type of distortion existing in international trade would    be to apply tariffs. However, as previously mentioned, these tariffs will be    eliminated.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Conclusions</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to the American Food Security and    Rural Investment Act or Farm Bill 2002 (Title 1), the following can be concluded:</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• In the 2002/2003 season each hectare of wheat    received an average of US$55.06. The farmers with a high level of technology    (3,500 kg/h.) would have received through direct subsidies 69.65 US$/h. In the    case of the corn producers, each hectare received, on average, a payment of    US$ 127.83 and farmers with a high level of technology (9,000kg/h. yield) would    have received a subsidy of 143.10 US$/h. It’s mean that the U.S. the direct    subsidies increase the gross margin of the wheat and corn producers by 30.64%    and 76.33%, respectively.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to the comparison between Chilean    and American direct production costs and gross margin for wheat and corn, the    following could be concluded:</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The direct costs of wheat production in Chile    are greater than those of the U.S. by 127.7% (548.17 US$/h. versus 244.11 US$/h.)    On the other hand, the wheat yields in Chile reached 6,500 kg/h. exceeding those    of the U.S. by 116.6% (3,500 kg/h.), considering similar technological conditions.    <br>   • The gross margin for national wheat supersedes that of the U.S. by 229%, but    when the direct production subsidies to American farmers are included, the difference    diminishes to 138%. The direct subsidies granted by the U.S. to its farmers    enable them to increase the gross margin by 38.16%, considering the aforementioned    production rate.    <br>   • With reference to corn, the total direct costs in Chile are 1,006.83 US$/h.,    while in the U.S. they reach 591.03 US$/h. However, the yield from farmers with    a high level of technology is 15,500 kg/h. and those of the U.S. only reach    9,000 kg/h.    <br>   • The gross margin for corn in the U.S. is 330.57 US$/h. including direct subsidies,    whereas that of the Chilean producers is 761.72 US$/h. By eliminating the direct    subsidies for corn production in the U.S., the gross margin for Chilean producers    exceeds that of their U.S. counterparts by 306.09%. Considering the previously    indicated production rate, the American farmers obtain 187.47 US$/h. in direct    subsidies, which increase their gross margin by 76.33%.    <br>   • By including land rent in the direct production costs for Chilean corn producers,    the gross margin decreases by 29%. The difference in gross margin compared with    that of the U.S. decreases from 431.15 to 206.96 US$/h.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to the competitiveness of national    wheat and corn producers the following is concluded: </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• The cost of importing wheat from the U.S. with    a 0% tariff, export subsidies and direct production subsidies is 6.73 US$/100    kg, a value less than the AVC (8.43 US$/100 kg) incurred by the Chilean producers    with a high level of technology.    <br>   • The cost of importing corn from the U.S. with a 0% tariff, export subsidies    and direct production subsidies is 6.46 US$/ 100kg, a value very similar to    the AVC (6.50 US$/100 kg) incurred by the Chilean producers with a high level    of technology. However, in order to achieve this level of AVC, it is necessary    to obtain yields superior to 15,500kg/h.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With respect to the grain trade between Chile    and U.S. the following can be concluded: </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">• Both Corn and Wheat production in Chile does    not have influence on the international trade and world-wide prices, because    Chile is an import country of these goods, and its internal prices of market    are based on international prices. If the prices of grains drop given by a gradual    diminish in the applied tariffs, then the viable option for these producers    -to medium and long term- is the to change his production to other agricultural    goods such as fresh fruits or other raw materials for food industries. These    kinds of goods have real opportunities of international trade due to the commercial    agreements that Chile has signed in the last years.    <br>   • In Chile, habitually the wheat producers do not rent land; only the corn producers    do it, because this type of producers has lower land. Therefore, if the price    of corn is high, then the corn producer makes the decision to rent land. On    the other hand, if the price is low these growers would not rent land, as answer    to a probable diminution of the yield of corn. That is to say, the opportunity    cost of land is a short term decision, based on the corn price of the previous    season.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>References</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">ACTIONAID. 2002. Rentabilidad en la agricultura.    Available in <A HREF="http://www.actionaid.org/" target="_blank">http://www.actionaid.org</A>.    &#91;20 March, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000198&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">BANCO CENTRAL DE CHILE, 2003. Bases de datos    econ&oacute;micos, Indicadores del d&iacute;a. Available in <A HREF="http://www.bcentral/basedatosecon&oacute;micos" target="_blank">http://www.bcentral/basedatosecon&oacute;micos</A>.    &#91;6 August, 2003&#93;</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000199&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">BASCO, C; BUCCELLATO, I; DELICH, V; TUSSIE, D.    2002. La nueva Farm Bill. Ley de seguridad agr&iacute;cola e inversi&oacute;n    rural de los Estados Unidos.. Available in <A HREF="http://www.latn.org.ar/articles/farm_bill_2002.htm" target="_blank">http://www.latn.org.ar/articles/farm_bill_2002.htm</A>.    &#91;4 May, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000200&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">DEPARTAMENTO DE ECONOM&Iacute;A AGRARIA. 2001.    Econom&iacute;a Agraria de la producci&oacute;n de ma&iacute;z en la VI regi&oacute;n.    Universidad de Talca. 117 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000201&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">DIRECCI&Oacute;N DE PROMOCI&Oacute;N DE EXPORTACIONES    (ProChile). 1995. New York. 39 p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000202&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">EL MERCURIO. Insumos agropecuarios. En: Revista    del campo. Nº 1.408. Cuerpo B, p.5. &#91;7 July, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000203&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">INSTITUTO NACIONAL DE ESTAD&Iacute;STICA (INE),    2003. Estad&iacute;sticas Agropecuarias. Available in <A HREF="http://www.ine.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.ine.cl</A>    &#91;20 September, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000204&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">METHOL, M. 2002. Nueva Ley agr&iacute;cola de    Estados Unidos: algunos aspectos destacados. ODYPA-ANUARIO. 5p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000205&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">MITTOL, A. 2002. Perdiendo nuestra tierra: La    Ley Agr&iacute;cola del 2002. Food First Institute for food and development.    Policy, USA. Available in <A HREF="http://www.foodfirst.org/pubs/backgrdrs/2002/leyagr&iacute;cola.html" target="_blank">http://www.foodfirst.org/pubs/backgrdrs/2002/leyagr&iacute;cola.html</A>.    &#91;16 March, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000206&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA). 2001. Condiciones de ingreso para los productos silvoagropecuarios    importados por Chile. Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;21 May, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000207&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2002. Situaci&oacute;n del mercado del ma&iacute;z. Ministerio de Agricultura,    Gobierno de Chile. Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;14 March, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000208&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2002. Mercado del trigo. Ministerio de Agricultura, Gobierno de Chile.    Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;23 April, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000209&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA). 2003. El tratado de libre comercio entre Chile y EE.UU. Available in    <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>. &#91;5 March,    2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000210&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2003. El mercado del ma&iacute;z. Ministerio de Agricultura, Gobierno    de Chile. Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;2 August, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000211&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2003. Precios de Insumos y productos agropecuarios. Ministerio de Agricultura,    Gobierno de Chile. Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;15 July, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000212&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2003. Precios mayoristas: trigo y ma&iacute;z. Precios reales sin IVA    con IPC de 07/2003. Ministerio de Agricultura, Gobierno de Chile. Available    in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>. &#91;15    de August, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000213&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POL&Iacute;TICAS AGRARIAS    (ODEPA), 2003. Precios Internacionales: trigo y ma&iacute;z, nominales sin IVA.    Ministerio de Agricultura, Gobierno de Chile. Available in <A HREF="http://www.odepa.cl/" target="_blank">http://www.odepa.cl</A>.    &#91;15 de August, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000214&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">ORGANIZACI&Oacute;N MUNDIAL DE COMERCIO (OMC).    2000. El Comercio Mundial en el a&ntilde;o 2000. Visi&oacute;n general. Available    in <A HREF="http://www.wto.org/spanish/res_s/statis_s/its.2001_s/chp-1.pdf" target="_blank">http://www.wto.org/spanish/res_s/statis_s/its.2001_s/chp-1.pdf</A>.    &#91;2 June, 2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000215&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">SILVA, C. 2003. Notas acerca del Tratado de Libre    Comercio entre Chile y Estados Unidos. Santiago de Chile. 21 p. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000216&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA).    2001. Characteristics and Production Costs of U.S. Corn Farms. Electronic Report    from the ERS. Available in <A HREF="http://www.ers.usda.gov/" target="_blank">http://www.ers.usda.gov</A>.    &#91;23 June, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000217&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA).    2002. Direct payments for wheat, feed grains. Available in <A HREF="http://www.ers.usda.gov/Features/FarmBill/analysis/directpayments2002act.htm" target="_blank">http://www.ers.usda.gov/Features/FarmBill/analysis/directpayments2002act.htm</A>.&#91;8    May, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000218&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA).    2002. Farm Characteristics, Farm Financial Indicators. Economic Research Service,    USDA, Washington DC. 2002. Available in <A HREF="http://www.ers.usda.gov/" target="_blank">http://www.ers.usda.gov</A>.    &#91;20 August, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000219&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA),    2003. World Agricultural Supply And Demand Estimates (WASDE-96). Available in    <a href="http://www.usda.gov" target="_blank">http://www.usda.gov</a>. &#91;13 May,    2003&#93;. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000220&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA),    2003. World Agricultural Supply And Demand Estimates (WASDE-401). Available    in <A HREF="http://www.usda.gov/oce/waob/wasde/latest" target="_blank">http://www.usda.gov/oce/waob/wasde/latest</A>.    &#91;28 August, 2003&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000221&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">VELASCO, R; GONZ&Aacute;LEZ, J; CRUZ, J. 1996.    Costos directos de producci&oacute;n de cultivos VII y VIII regi&oacute;n, Instituto    de Investigaciones Agropecuarias (INIA), Centro Regional de Investigaci&oacute;n    Quilamapu, Ministerio de Agricultura. Bolet&iacute;n Nº71. 254 p. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000222&pid=S0103-2003200600030000500025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Recebido em abril de 2005 e revisto em junho    de 2006</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Annex</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05anx01.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05anx02.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05anx03.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v44n3/a05anx04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><SUP>A</sup> Source: created by the author, 2003.    with information from the ODEPA, INIA, Departamento de Econom&iacute;a Agraria    Universidad de Talca, Banco Central de Chile and Revista del Campo.    <br>   <SUP>B</sup>Source: USDA, 2003.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   (1) Cost of purchased irrigation water.    <br>   (2) Costs of Depreciations: In the case of corn producers, 40% of the total    cost of machinery depreciation was considered as a direct production cost, and    30% in the case of wheat producers.    <br>   (3) Total Directs Costs = Operating Costs plus 30-40% of the total cost of machinery    depreciation (wheat and corn respectively).    <br>   (*) These items were not considered for comparisons with the Chilean producers.    <br>   1 hectare = 2.4710 acres. 1 US$ = 701.14 Chilean pesos.</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>ACTIONAID</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Rentabilidad en la agricultura]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>BANCO CENTRAL DE CHILE</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Bases de datos económicos, Indicadores del día]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BASCO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BUCCELLATO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DELICH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TUSSIE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[La nueva Farm Bill. Ley de seguridad agrícola e inversión rural de los Estados Unidos]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>DEPARTAMENTO DE ECONOMÍA AGRARIA</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Economía Agraria de la producción de maíz en la VI región]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Universidad de Talca]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>DIRECCIÓN DE PROMOCIÓN DE EXPORTACIONES (ProChile)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>EL MERCURIO</collab>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Insumos agropecuarios]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revista del campo]]></source>
<year></year>
<numero>1.408</numero>
<issue>1.408</issue>
<page-range>5</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>INSTITUTO NACIONAL DE ESTADÍSTICA (INE)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Estadísticas Agropecuarias]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[METHOL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Nueva Ley agrícola de Estados Unidos: algunos aspectos destacados]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ODYPA-ANUARIO]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MITTOL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Perdiendo nuestra tierra: La Ley Agrícola del 2002. Food First Institute for food and development]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Condiciones de ingreso para los productos silvoagropecuarios importados por Chile]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Situación del mercado del maíz]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Mercado del trigo]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[El tratado de libre comercio entre Chile y EE.UU]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[El mercado del maíz]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Precios de Insumos y productos agropecuarios]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Precios mayoristas: trigo y maíz. Precios reales sin IVA con IPC de 07/2003]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OFICINA DE ESTUDIOS Y POLÍTICAS AGRARIAS (ODEPA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Precios Internacionales: trigo y maíz, nominales sin IVA]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministerio de AgriculturaGobierno de Chile]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>ORGANIZACIÓN MUNDIAL DE COMERCIO (OMC)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[El Comercio Mundial en el año 2000: Visión general]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SILVA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Notas acerca del Tratado de Libre Comercio entre Chile y Estados Unidos]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Santiago de Chile ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Characteristics and Production Costs of U.S. Corn Farms]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Direct payments for wheat, feed grains]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Farm Characteristics, Farm Financial Indicators]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<month>20</month>
<day>02</day>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Economic Research ServiceUSDA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[World Agricultural Supply And Demand Estimates (WASDE-96)]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>UNITED STATED DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE (USDA)</collab>
<source><![CDATA[World Agricultural Supply And Demand Estimates (WASDE-401)]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VELASCO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GONZÁLEZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CRUZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Costos directos de producción de cultivos VII y VIII región, Instituto de Investigaciones Agropecuarias (INIA)]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Centro Regional de Investigación QuilamapuMinisterio de Agricultura]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
