<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032003000100001</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032003000100001</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Use of crops and livestock futures contracts in portfolios: an analysis of feasibility]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Mattos]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Fabio L.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ferreira Filho]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Joaquim Bento de Souza]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Master in Applied Economics  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidade de São Paulo Escola Superior de Agricultura Luiz de Queiróz ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[Piracicaba SP]]></addr-line>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<fpage>117</fpage>
<lpage>138</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100001&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[According to Portfolio Theory, by combining assets that show a correlation inferior to one (1) among their individual returns, it becomes possible to create portfolios that reduce risk without damaging expected return. Crop and livestock futures contracts and company stocks show such a characteristic, which signals potential benefits when forming portfolios combining these two types of assets. This investment strategy is not often utilized in Brazil. The purpose of our research was to assess whether such an asset combination is actually advantageous to those creating investment portfolios in the Brazilian market. Our evaluation used instruments of analysis developed by Markowitz in Portfolio Theory and data about the return from crop and livestock futures contracts and stocks. The data was gathered from the Brazilian Futures and Commodities Exchange (BM&F) and Brazil’s National Association of Open Market Institutions (ANDIMA) between July 1994 and December 1998. The results of this work showed that the combination of these two types of assets in investment portfolios can be an interesting portfolio management alternative.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[portfolio]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[crops]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[livestock futures contracts]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Markowitz]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <P><font face="Verdana" size="4"><b>Use of crops and livestock futures contracts    in portfolios: an analysis of feasibility</b></font></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Fabio L. Mattos<sup>I</sup>; Joaquim Bento    de Souza Ferreira Filho<sup>II</sup></b></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><sup>I</sup>Master in Applied Economics. Email:<a href="mailto:fmattos@uiuc.edu">fmattos@uiuc.edu</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Professor at ESALQ/USP. Piracicaba - SP. Brazil. 13418-900. B.O.Box    9. Email: <a href="mailto:jbsferre@carpa.ciagri.usp.br">jbsferre@carpa.ciagri.usp.br</a>    <br>   </font> </P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P>&nbsp;</P> <hr size="1" noshade>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2"> According to Portfolio Theory, by combining    assets that show a correlation inferior to one (1) among their individual returns,    it becomes possible to create portfolios that reduce risk without damaging expected    return. Crop and livestock futures contracts and company stocks show such a    characteristic, which signals potential benefits when forming portfolios combining    these two types of assets. This investment strategy is not often utilized in    Brazil. The purpose of our research was to assess whether such an asset combination    is actually advantageous to those creating investment portfolios in the Brazilian    market. Our evaluation used instruments of analysis developed by Markowitz in    Portfolio Theory and data about the return from crop and livestock futures contracts    and stocks. The data was gathered from the Brazilian Futures and Commodities    Exchange (BM&amp;F) and Brazil’s National Association of Open Market Institutions    (ANDIMA) between July 1994 and December 1998. The results of this work showed    that the combination of these two types of assets in investment portfolios can    be an interesting portfolio management alternative.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Key words:</b> portfolio, crops and livestock    futures contracts, Markowitz</font></P> <hr size="1" noshade>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>1. Introduction</b></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The purpose of this work was to analyze the use    of crop and livestock futures contracts to reduce stock portfolio risk and to    determine the advantages and disadvantages of such a combination in Brazil.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Chance (1994) notes that the world’s financial    markets went through a period of significant evolution in early 1980s that included    an increase in the popularity of futures contracts as investment instruments.    In the specific case of crop and livestock <I>commodities</I>, Chance (1994)    gives the example of a portfolio manager who decides that the incorporation    of soybeans in his asset portfolio could increase his return without significantly    modifying his risk. Unfortunately, the acquisition of a physical product would    incur various warehousing costs and involve difficulty in finding a buyer for    the product in the future. A soybean futures market would solve these problems,    since it allows such a manager to add the product to his portfolio (with expected    advantages) without need of physical possession.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">When emphasizing the significance of futures    markets, Chance (1994) points out that their main advantage lies in the fact    that the returns from commodities futures contracts, a distinct type of asset,    show a low correlation with the returns from other types of assets. A correlation    inferior to 1 between the returns from two assets means, roughly speaking, that    the assets’ returns do not show the same behavior. The further this correlation    is below one, the less similar will be the development of these two assets’    returns over time. If the return correlation is less than one, a decreasing    return from one asset does not imply that the other asset’s return is also decreasing.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">According to Portfolio Theory, by adding assets    to a portfolio that show a return correlation inferior to one with the portfolio’s    existing assets, it is possible to reduce the portfolio’s risk without damaging    its expected return. It is worth pointing out that investors and portfolio mangers    prefer more return and less risk (Markowitz, 1952). </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In one study of the financial markets in the    United States, France, Germany, Japan, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom between    1989 and 1998, Allen (1999) found that the correlations between the returns    from future contracts, stocks, and bonds were close to zero. The same author    prepared various portfolios combining futures contracts, stocks, and bonds from    the markets under analysis and verified that such a combination increased the    efficiency of the portfolios<a name="volta1"></a><a href="#nota1"><sup>1</sup></a>    in all situations studied. Works carried out by Bodie &amp; Rosansky (1984),    Lee et al. (1985), Herbst &amp; McCormack (1986 e 1987), Elton et al. (1990),    Irwin et al. (1993), Edwards &amp; Park (1996), Lintner (1997) and Schneeweis    &amp; Spurgin (1997) proved that such strategy could be successfully adopted    in various situations.</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">It was not possible to find analyses that assess    the validity of this strategy in the Brazilian market. In addition, crop and    livestock futures contracts are a very minor participant in the Brazilian financial    market, accounting for about 1% of the Brazilian Futures and Commodities Exchange’s    (BM&amp;F) trading. Nevertheless, this type of study would be of a great value    for the Brazilian economy as, by exposing the value of commodity futures contracts,    it could develop alternative sources of agricultural funding, such as private    investors and portfolio managers The strengthening of private investment in    Brazilian agriculture is especially relevant under the current environment of    tight government agricultural expenditures and reduced government incentives    directed toward the support of agricultural markets.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The present work was designed to answer the question,    is the combination of Brazilian equity assets with Brazilian crop and livestock    <I>commodity </I>instruments advantageous when creating investment portfolios    in Brazil? In other words, is there empirical evidence capable of proving the    advantages of such a combination in Brazil?</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">To answer this question, we analyzed the performance    of one portfolio composed of stocks only and other portfolios composed of different    combinations of stocks and crop and livestock futures contracts. This process    was carried out in four phases: (a) analysis of the return/risk ratio of a stock    portfolio and of Brazilian crop and livestock futures contracts; (b) assessment    of correlation between the returns from futures contracts and from stocks, which    signals the potential of diversifying a stock portfolio through the inclusion    of commodities futures contracts; (c) comparison of the performance of all constructed    portfolios; and (d) an assessment of the feasibility of creating efficient portfolios    through the combination of stocks and crop and livestock futures contracts.</font></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>2. Methodology</b></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Ibovespa, an index that reflects the price    behavior of the more traded stocks in the S&atilde;o Paulo Stock Exchange (Bovespa)    was used to represent the all stock portfolio’s assets and the stock portion    of all other portfolios. The Ibovespa was chosen as it answers for approximately    85% of total volume traded in the Brazilian stock market and is considered representative    of the exchange’s average performance. In the case of crops and livestock futures    contracts, we used coffee, cotton, corn, live cattle, and soybean contracts    traded in the BM&amp;F over the period under consideration. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Data used in this work refer to the period between    July 1994 and December 1998: 54 months. This choice was made for two reasons:    (a) prior to this period, few crop and livestock futures contracts were continuously    traded, and (b) various asset price distortions between the mid 1980s and mid    1990s, which were the result of a sequence of economic stabilization programs.    Within our study period, various sub-periods are also considered. The sub-periods    were to analyze the results obtained by strategies based on crop and livestock    futures contracts drawn up at the beginning of 1995, 1996, and 1997 and maintained    until the end of period covered by this work (December 1998). We suppose here    that investors review their investment approach at the beginning of each year,    after the close of annual planning and accounting.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">It is worth pointing out that only the Ibovespa    stocks and coffee and live cattle contracts were being traded at the beginning    of the study period. In the case of sugar and soybean futures contracts, we    used 38 observations taken from November 1995 to December 1998; and for corn    and cotton futures contracts, we used 25 observations from December 1996 to    December 1998. All data were obtained from the National Association of Open    Market Institutions (ANDIMA) and the BM&amp;F.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The crop and livestock <I>commodities</I> futures    market in Brazil accounts for only 1% of the total trade in the Brazilian futures    market. From this 1%, only coffee and live cattle contracts show significant    liquidity (although their liquidity is still far behind the liquidity of interest    markets, the currency exchange, and the stock index). The other contracts, sugar,    soybean, corn and cotton, form a low liquidity market, which may have important    consequences on this study.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The evolution of futures contract prices may    be influenced by the level of market liquidity; hence, the behavior of these    prices may suffer alteration as significant changes occur in the liquidity level    of such markets. The conclusion reached from the analysis of an illiquid commodity    market may be drastically adjusted if data related to higher liquidity markets    are used. Anyway, we opted to use all crops and livestock futures contracts    traded over the period under consideration, as they represent the reality found    by investors interested in this type of Brazilian market.</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The analysis presented in this work was constructed    in four phases. In the first phase, return rates from crop and livestock futures    contracts and the Ibovespa stocks were calculated. The Ibovespa return rate    is given by the variation of its value over time. Bawa and Chakrin (1979) point    out that various authors have verified that financial asset prices are very    similar when distributed lognormally, and such distributions are still often    employed to model asset returns. Hence, the return rate adopted for this analysis    was given by the natural logarithm of monthly asset value variation (Elton et    al., 1990):</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image49.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(1)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image104.gif"> is the return rate from    the Ibovespa in the month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image105.gif"> is the Ibovespa quotation    in the last day of month t; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image106.gif"> is the Ibovespa quotation    in the last day of month t-1.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Similarly, the calculation of return rate for    long position future contracts is given by (Bodie &amp; Rosansky, 1984):</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image53.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(2)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image108.gif"> is the return rate from    a long position in future contract j in month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image109.gif">is the settlement price    of a future contract j on the last day of month t; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image110.gif"> is the settlement price    of a future contract j on the last day of month t-1.</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the case of short positions, it is possible    to adapt the same principle:</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image57.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(3)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image112.gif"> is the return rate from    a short position in future contract j in month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image109.gif"> is the settlement price    of a future contract j on the last day of month t; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image110.gif"> is the settlement price    of a future contract j on the last day of month t-1.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">All settlement prices considered are related    to the first maturity of the future contract, which is the date with the highest    trading volume and open interest<a name="volta2"></a><a href="#nota2"><sup>2</sup></a>.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Finally, the return rate of a portfolio that    combines stocks and futures contracts is given by the weighted average return    of each of such assets (Markowitz, 1952 and 1959):</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image59.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(4)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image113.gif"> is the return of P portfolio    in the month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image114.gif"> is the participation    of Ibovespa in the portfolio;</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image115.gif"> is the return of Ibovespa    in the month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image63.gif"> is the participation    of future contract j in the portfolio;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image116.gif"> is the return of future    contract j in the month t; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image117.gif"> is the number of different    future contracts in the portfolio.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Markowitz (1952 and 1959) demonstrated that the    standard deviation of an asset’s return can be used to measure the asset holder’s    exposure to uncertain change in the value of the asset: the asset’s &quot;risk.&quot;    The risk of each asset analyzed by this work was given by its deviation of return    in relation to its average value, that is to say, by the standard deviation    of its return:</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center" height="37"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image66.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right" height="37"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(5)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image119.gif"> is the standard deviation    of asset j return;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image120.gif"> is the return rate of    asset j in the month t;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image121.gif"> is the return expected    for asset j; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image117.gif"> is the total number    of days of the month.</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the case of a portfolio, the calculation of    risk follows the same reasoning, i.e., the risk of a portfolio is given by standard    deviation of its return. Hence, the standard deviation of portfolio returns    is equivalent to (Markowitz, 1952 and 1959):</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image70.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(6)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image123.gif"> is the standard deviation    of portfolio return;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image124.gif">is the square of standard    deviation of asset i return composing such portfolio;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image125.gif"> is the participation    of asset i in the portfolio;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image126.gif"> is the co-variance between    the return of assets which compose the portfolio; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image127.gif"> is the number of portfolio    assets.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Therefore, a portfolio’s risk depends not only    on the deviation of the returns from its assets but also on the co-variance    between the assets.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The second phase of this work was the determination    of the correlation coefficient between the returns from stocks and the returns    from crop and livestock futures contracts. Such a coefficient plays an important    role in Portfolio Theory since a strategy of scientific investment diversification    is only feasible if there is a combination of assets whose returns show a correlation    inferior to 1 (Markowitz, 1952 and 1959). </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The scientific diversification suggested by Markowitz    consists of composing an investment portfolio with types of assets that respond    differently to the same event. The basic principle is that the behavior followed    by each asset’s return cannot be equal. Therefore, if a certain event lowers    the return from portfolio asset X, the returns from other portfolio assets would    not be similarly affected, offsetting the decreased return from X. It is important    that a portfolio be composed of assets that show a correlation of returns inferior    to 1 if risk is to be minimized. </font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">To reduce the possibility that our sample coefficient    estimates lead to the wrong conclusions, we made use of a statistical test to    determine if the correlation could be equal to zero (Hoel, 1971). We tested    the significance of correlation by assuming that it is null in population and    by carrying out a t test (Hoel, 1971):</font></P>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"></font></p> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image76.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image77.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(7)</font></td>   </tr> </table> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image78.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(8)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">t is the statistics used in the test;</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">r is the sample correlation coefficient; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">n is the number of sample observations. Given    a certain level of significance, the assumption of a null correlation cannot    be rejected if the value calculated for t is lower than its critical value (listed).</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The third phase of this work consisted of analyzing    the performances of the portfolios that combined stocks with differing percentages    of crop or livestock futures contracts and a portfolio composed entirely of    stocks. This comparison was made as follows: from a portfolio composed only    of stocks (100% Ibovespa), we started to gradually include a futures contract,    allowing the participation of this contract to grow progressively while the    participation of Ibovespa stocks diminished (1% futures contract and 99% Ibovespa,    2% futures contract and 98% Ibovespa, and so on until there was no stock in    the portfolio, i.e. 100% futures contract).</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">This process gave rise to an assembly of points    representing the returns from portfolios with various combinations of stocks    and futures contracts. It was then possible to calculate the return and the    risk of each portfolio according to equations (4) and (6). In order to properly    assess the assembly of points, we applied a performance measure to the portfolios    created. The measure chosen was the Sharpe Index (SI), which measures the return    obtained above the risk free interest rate by unit of risk assumed by the investor    (Tobin, 1958; Sharpe, 1966):</font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image79.gif"></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(9)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">where </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">E(R<SUB>i</SUB>) is the expected return of portfolio    i;</font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">R<SUB>F</SUB> is the risk free rate; and</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image132.gif"> is the standard deviation    of the return of portfolio i.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Selic rate, which represents the return from    Brazilian government bonds, was used to represent the risk free rate (Securato,    1999). The risk free rate for a given period was deemed as the simple arithmetic    average of the bond return values during the period analyzed. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">A positive Sharpe Index means that a certain    asset offered a premium for the risk assumed. If the index is above 1, the premium    offered was proportionally higher than the risk assumed. For values between    0 and 1, the index indicates that the premium offered was proportionally lower    than risk assumed. Therefore, assets with higher Sharpe Index values are preferable    than those with lower values. At the end of this phase, it was possible to verify    the point at which the inclusion of futures contracts in stock portfolios was    able to increment the portfolio return/risk ratio.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the fourth phase of this work, the feasibility    of building efficient portfolios through a combination of stocks and crop or    livestock futures contracts was assessed by means of an algorithm developed    by Markowitz (1952 e 1959). An efficient portfolio is one that shows the lowest    possible level of risk for a given return or the highest possible return for    a given level of risk (Markowitz, 1952 and 1959). It is assumed that investors    try to minimize investment risk at a certain level of expected return or maximize    expected return given a certain level of risk. Therefore, for the case of N    assets, we have:</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">minimize<IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image81.gif"></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">subject to<IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image82.gif"></font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image83.gif" align="absmiddle">        e <img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image84.gif">, i = 1, ... , N</font></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(10)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">or then</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">maximize<IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image85.gif"></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">subject to<IMG SRC="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image86.gif"></font></P> <table width="100%" align=center>   <tr>      <td width=95% align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image87.gif" align="middle">        e <img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/Image88.gif">, i = 1, ... , N</font></td>     <td wifth=5% align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2">(11)</font></td>   </tr> </table>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">At the end of this phase, we could verify if    it is possible to generate efficient investment frontiers through a combination    of stocks and crop and livestock futures contracts in portfolios. It was also    possible to verify if such combinations would be able to produce more efficient    portfolios than portfolios made up of only the Ibovespa stocks.</font></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>3. Results</b></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Analyses of the various rates of return for the    period between July 1994 and December 1998 verified that the Ibovespa tended    to produce higher returns than the both long and short crop and livestock futures    contracts, returns from which were very modest (<a href="#quad1">Chart 1</a>).    In addition, analysis of the futures contracts’ returns over the period reveals    that better opportunities for gain were verified in specific sub-periods, i.e.,    there was not a consistent return from these assets over the entire period,    July 1994 to December 1998. Therefore, an investor would not be motivated to    search for crop and livestock futures contracts if his purpose is higher portfolio    returns. As the return from a portfolio is the weighted average of the returns    from the assets composing the portfolio, the combination of futures contracts    and stocks in investment portfolios during the period analyzed would present    a return inferior to those a portfolio composed of only the Ibovespa stocks.</font></P>     <P><a name="quad1"></a></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q01.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In relation to the risk of each asset, it was    possible to verify that crop and livestock futures contracts were riskier than    the Ibovespa over the majority of the sub-periods analyzed (<a href="#quad2">Chart    2</a>). The Ibovespa showed higher standard deviation of returns values than    most futures contracts. Anyway, all assets revealed a high associated risk,    suggesting that a strategy of investment diversification could be attempted    as a way of reducing the total risk assumed by the investor.</font></P>     <P><a name="quad2"></a></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P>&nbsp;</P>     <P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q02.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>      <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The relatively high risk associated with the    assets analyzed tends to reduce their Sharpe Index values, which in the case    of futures contracts is aggravated by their low rate of return (which ultimately    turn these indexes negative in the majority of sub-periods). The Ibovespa is    distinguished for presenting higher Sharpe Indices in the majority of cases    studied. Therefore, as was suggested in prior analyses, the Sharpe Index shows    that the futures contracts are less attractive assets if taken on an individual    basis.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The results from the second phase of this work    show that sample correlation coefficients between returns from the Ibovespa    and from each of the crop and livestock futures contracts always have values    close to zero. The results from statistical verification of these values, with    a level of significance equal to 0.01, do not allow the rejection of the null    assumption of no correlation between their the two types of assets’ returns    (<a href="#quad3">Charts 3</a> and <a href="#quad4">4</a>). Therefore, it is    possible to accept that the correlation coefficient between the Ibovespa’s returns    and the returns from each of the six futures contracts is equal to zero, confirming    the feasibility of a scientific investment diversification strategy based on    the combination of stocks and a crop or livestock futures contract.</font></P>     <P><a name="quad3"></a></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q03.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><a name="quad4"></a></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P>&nbsp;</P>     <P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q04.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>                <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the third phase of this work, we analyzed    the effect the addition of a futures contract had on the return and risk of    an all stock portfolio. In most cases, as the futures contract’s participation    in the portfolio increased, the portfolio’s risk and return diminished. In 75%    of the situations analyzed, the allocation that gave highest return was that    with all funds invested in the Ibovespa stocks (<a href="#quad5">Charts 5</a>    and <a href="#quad6">6</a>)<a name="volta3"></a><a href="#nota3"><sup>3</sup></a>.    The addition of a futures contract reduced risk in all but two situations, the    inclusion of a long position in cotton in 1997 and a long position in coffee    in 1996.</font></P>     <P><a name="quad5"></a></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q05.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><a name="quad6"></a></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p01q06.gif"></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">As overall return and risk were generally reduced    by the inclusion of a futures contract in a previously all stock investment    portfolio, it was necessary to use the Sharpe Index to assess if the lower portfolio    risk was sufficient to offset the loss of return. It was verified that in 73%    of the situations analyzed, the portfolios that showed higher Sharpe Index values    were those composed of stocks alone (<a href="#quad5">Charts 5</a> and <a href="#quad6">6</a>).    This means that the inclusion of a futures contract in an all stock portfolio    tends to diminish the Sharpe Index, making it impossible to affirm that the    reduction of risk was sufficient to offset the loss of portfolio return in most    cases. However, it is worth pointing out that in a not insignificant 27% of    the cases studied, the portfolio with the higher Sharpe Index was composed of    stocks and a futures contract. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">There is a caveat worth noting: use of the Sharpe    Index alone may lead to distorted conclusions when return from the asset under    consideration is negative or inferior to the free-of-risk interest rate, for    example, the portfolio formed by stock and a cotton futures contract in 1998.    In that year, the average return from long and short positions in cotton and    the Ibovespa were, –0.28%, +0.28% and –3.39% respectively. The risk of these    assets in the period was 4.33% for the futures contracts and 19.26% for the    Ibovespa. A simple observation of these numbers would suggest that the option    that includes a cotton futures contract is the more advantageous as it revealed    higher return and inferior risk than the Ibovespa. Nevertheless, the Sharpe    Index signaled the Ibovespa as the best investment alternative. This type of    situation occurred in very few cases analyzed, i.e., it appears that this problem    does not compromise this work’s general conclusions. Therefore, by means of    the exercise carried out in this phase, it was verified that the inclusion of    a crop or livestock futures contract would reduce an all stock portfolio’s risk    but not sufficiently to offset the loss of return arising from such strategy.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the fourth phase of this work, an algorithm    developed by Markowitz (1952 &amp; 1959) was employed to verify the feasibility    of building efficient frontiers by merging Ibovespa stocks with various combinations    of six crop and livestock futures contracts. The basic idea was to determine    if portfolios combining stocks and futures contracts would be more efficient    than portfolios composed only of stocks. We tested possible combinations of    stocks and both long and short futures contracts for six commodities over the    period between July 1994 and December 1998, which was again divided into various    sub-periods. The six commodities were coffee, corn, cotton, live cattle, soybeans,    sugar, and coffee. In total, we tried to build 272 efficient frontiers of which    230 attempts succeeded (it was not possible to find a solution for the other    42 combinations using Markowitz’s algorithm).</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Among the 230 efficient frontiers built<a name="volta4"></a><a href="#nota4"><sup>4</sup></a>,    114 showed combined portfolios that were more efficient than the Ibovespa stocks.    This suggests that diversified portfolios could be created that show a higher    return and the same risk or the same return and lower risk than the Ibovespa.    For example, in 1997, a portfolio composed of long positions in live cattle    (28.640%), long positions in coffee (38.785%), short positions in corn (6.141%),    and the Ibovespa (26.434%) would have obtained an average return equal to that    of the Ibovespa (3.1%) while the risk from this portfolio would have been 6.9%    as compared with 12.4% from the Ibovespa alone.</font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">It is worth pointing out that portfolios diversified    with assets other than those employed in this study could show a better efficiency    than an Ibovespa portfolio during the period of study. In addition, we call    attention to the fact that the Ibovespa stocks cannot be deemed to comprise    an efficient portfolio (Nakamura, 1998). Therefore, the determination that portfolios    made up of a combination of Ibovespa stocks and crop and livestock futures contracts    are more efficient than Ibovespa stocks alone, does not mean that this combination    is the only mix of assets with this characteristic.</font></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>4. Conclusions</b></font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The results of tests carried out according to    our proposed methodology allow us to reach two general conclusions regarding    the use of crops and livestock futures contracts in stock portfolios: (a) from    a theoretical basis, there are advantages in such strategy since it can be assumed    that the correlation between Ibovespa returns and returns from each of six future    contracts is null; and (b) there is empirical evidence showing that in certain    situations there are advantages to be gained by combining crop and livestock    futures contracts with stocks in investment portfolios, but these advantages    did not appear on a regular basis over the period analyzed by this study. </font></P>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<P><font face="Verdana" size="2">It was also possible to verify that over the    period analyzed crop and livestock futures contracts were not good investment    alternatives to the Ibovespa stocks; however, these contracts offered benefits    when combined with the Ibovespa stocks in an investment portfolio. The analysis    of portfolios combining the Ibovespa and a futures contract proved that this    strategy can effectively reduce portfolio risk, although this risk reduction    does not always offset the accompanying reduced portfolio return. In addition,    we found that it would be possible to build portfolios that combined stocks    and crop and livestock futures contracts that were more efficient than a portfolio    made up the Ibovespa stocks alone. If, in certain situations, benefits can be    obtained by adding crop and livestock futures contracts to stock portfolios,    we ask why this strategy is not so used in the Brazilian financial market. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">One problem that may reduce the use of crop and    livestock futures contracts in investment portfolios is this market’s low liquidity,    which creates price formation difficulties and reduces investor flexibility.    With few agents active in the Brazilian commodity futures market, prices are    more sensitive to specific trading moves: manipulation. Illiquidity reduces    investor flexibility when it comes time to trade: can the trade be made. Of    course, no investor wants to encounter either of these market problems. The    reduced liquidity still existing in this market also impedes investment by fund    managers, who find that the crop and livestock futures contracts market is insufficient    for their portfolio demands. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">The growth of Brazil’s crop and livestock futures    market is further hindered by specific characteristics that complicate investment    in this market. As opposed to stock transactions, where the great investor concern    is price, futures market investors must also focus on contract maturity dates    and operational expenses. </font></P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2">Low liquidity and somewhat complicated trading    strategies are two of possibly numerous possible explanations for the low demand    for crop and live stock futures contracts in the Brazilian financial market.    A more comprehensive analysis of the issue will be incumbent upon future works.</font></P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>References</b></font></P>     <!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">ALLEN, M. <B>Diversifying a typical investment    portfolio with managed futures:</B> country overviews. RXR Capital Asset Management,    1999.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000139&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">BAWA, V.S.; CHAKRIN, L.M. Optimal portf&oacute;lio    choice and equilibrium in a lognormal securities market. In: ELTON, E.J.; GRUBER,    M.J. (Ed.) <B>Portfolio theory, 25 years after</B>. North-Holland Publishing    Company, 1979, p. 47-62.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000140&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">BODIE, Z.; ROSANSKY, V.I. Risk and return in    commodity futures. In: PECK, A.E. (Ed.) <B>Selected writings on futures markets:</B>    research directions in commodity markets, 1970-1980. Board of Trade of the City    of Chicago, 1984. Section 2, cap.5, p.159-176.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000141&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">CHANCE, D.M. <B>Managed futures and their role    in investments portfolios</B>. The Research Foundation of the Institute of Chartered    Financial Analysts, 1994.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000142&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">EDWARDS, F.R.; PARK, J.M. Do managed futures    make good investments?. <B>The Journal of Futures Markets</B>, v. 16, n. 5,    p. 475-517, 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000143&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">ELTON, E.J.; GRUBER, M.J.; RENTZLER, J. The performance    of publicly offered commodity funds. <B>Financial Analysts Journal</B>, July    – August, 1990.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000144&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">HERBST, A.F.; McCORMACK, J.P. <B>An examination    of the risk-return characteristics of portfolios combining commodity futures    contracts with common stocks</B>. Working paper, Center for the Study of Futures    Markets, Columbia University, January 1986.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000145&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">HERBST, A.F.; McCORMACK, J.P. <B>A further examination    of the risk-return characteristics of portfolios combining commodity futures    contracts with common stocks</B>. Working paper, Center for the Study of Futures    Markets, Columbia University, January 1987.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000146&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">HOEL, P.G. <B>Introduction to mathematical statistics</B>.    4<SUP>th</SUP> ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1971.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000147&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">IRWIN, S.H.; KRUKEMYER, T.R.; ZULAUF, C.R. Investment    performance of public commodity pools: 1979-1990. <B>The Journal of Futures    Markets</B>, v.13, n.7, p.799-820, 1993.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000148&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">LEE, C.F.; LEUTHOLD, R.M.; CORDIER, J.E. The    stock market and the commodity futures market: diversification and arbitrage    potential. <B>Financial Analysts Journal</B>, p. 53-60, July-August 1985.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000149&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">LINTNER, J. The potential role of managed commodity-financial    futures accounts (and/or funds) in portfolio of stocks and bonds. In: PETERS,    C.; WARWICK, B. (Ed.) <B>The handbook of managed futures:</B> performance, evaluation    and analysis. Rev. ed. Irwin Professional Publishing, 1997. Part one, chapter    5, p. 99-138.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000150&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">MARKOWITZ, H.M. Portfolio selection. <B>The Journal    of Finance</B>, v.VII, n.1, p.77-91, March 1952.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000151&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">MARKOWITZ, H.M. <B>Portf&oacute;lio selection:    </B>efficient diversification of investments. New York. John Wiley &amp; Sons,    1959.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000152&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">NAKAMURA, W. T. <B>Efici&ecirc;ncia da carteira    te&oacute;rica do &iacute;ndice Bovespa no contexto da moderna teoria de carteiras</B>.    S&atilde;o Paulo, 1998. 344 p. Tese (Doutorado) – Faculdade de Economia, Administra&ccedil;&atilde;o    e Contabilidade, Universidade de S&atilde;o Paulo.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000153&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">SCHNEEWEIS, T.; SPURGIN, R. The benefits of managed    futures. In: PETERS, C.; WARWICK, B. (Ed.) <B>The handbook of managed futures:    </B>performance, evaluation and analysis. Rev. ed. Irwin Professional Publishing,    1997. Part one, chapter 2, p. 17-48.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000154&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">SECURATO, J.R. <B>C&aacute;lculo financeiro das    tesourarias</B>: bancos e empresas. S&atilde;o Paulo: Saint Paul, 1999.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000155&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">SHARPE, W. Mutual fund performance. <B>Journal    of Business</B>, p.119-138, January 1966.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000156&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><P><font face="Verdana" size="2">TOBIN, J. Liquidity preference as behavior towards    risk. <B>The Review of Economic Studies</B>, n.67, p.65-86, February 1958.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000157&pid=S0103-2003200300010000100019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><P>&nbsp;</P>     <P>&nbsp;</P>     <P><font face="Verdana" size="2"><a name="nota1"></a><a href="#volta1">1</a> Allen    (1999) analyzes the efficiency of a portfolio by means of its return/risk ratio,    i.e., when the return from a portfolio is higher, its risk is higher.    <br>   <a name="nota2"></a><a href="#volta2">2</a> The sum of all long positions (or    all short positions) in the futures market.    <br>   <a name="nota3"></a><a href="#volta3">3</a> We show only the results for addition    of cotton and corn contracts due to space considerations. The results of the    other contracts may be obtained from the authors upon request.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="nota4"></a><a href="#volta4">4</a> The results referring to the composition    of these portfolios are not included in this work due to space constraints.    They can be obtained directly with authors, upon request.</font></p>       ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ALLEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Diversifying a typical investment portfolio with managed futures: country overviews]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[RXR Capital Asset Management]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BAWA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHAKRIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[L.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Optimal portfólio choice and equilibrium in a lognormal securities market]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ELTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GRUBER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Portfolio theory, 25 years after]]></source>
<year>1979</year>
<page-range>47-62</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[North-Holland Publishing Company]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BODIE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Z.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ROSANSKY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.I.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Risk and return in commodity futures]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PECK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Selected writings on futures markets: research directions in commodity markets, 1970-1980]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<page-range>159-176</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[Board of Trade of the City of Chicago]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHANCE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Managed futures and their role in investments portfolios]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The Research Foundation of the Institute of Chartered Financial Analysts]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[EDWARDS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PARK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Do managed futures make good investments?]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Journal of Futures Markets]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<numero>5</numero>
<issue>5</issue>
<page-range>475-517</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ELTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GRUBER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RENTZLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The performance of publicly offered commodity funds]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Financial Analysts Journal]]></source>
<year>July</year>
<month> -</month>
<day> A</day>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HERBST]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McCORMACK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[An examination of the risk-return characteristics of portfolios combining commodity futures contracts with common stocks]]></source>
<year>Janu</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>y </day>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Working paperCenter for the Study of Futures Markets, Columbia University]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HERBST]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McCORMACK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[A further examination of the risk-return characteristics of portfolios combining commodity futures contracts with common stocks]]></source>
<year>Janu</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>y </day>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Working paperCenter for the Study of Futures Markets, Columbia University]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Introduction to mathematical statistics]]></source>
<year>1971</year>
<edition>4</edition>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[John Wiley & Sons]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[IRWIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.H.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KRUKEMYER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ZULAUF]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Investment performance of public commodity pools: 1979-1990]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Journal of Futures Markets]]></source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>7</numero>
<issue>7</issue>
<page-range>799-820</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LEE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LEUTHOLD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CORDIER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The stock market and the commodity futures market: diversification and arbitrage potential]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Financial Analysts Journal]]></source>
<year>July</year>
<month>-A</month>
<day>ug</day>
<page-range>53-60</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LINTNER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The potential role of managed commodity-financial futures accounts (and/or funds) in portfolio of stocks and bonds]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PETERS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WARWICK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The handbook of managed futures: performance, evaluation and analysis]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<page-range>99-138</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[Irwin Professional Publishing]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MARKOWITZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Portfolio selection]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Journal of Finance]]></source>
<year>Marc</year>
<month>h </month>
<day>19</day>
<volume>VII</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>77-91</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MARKOWITZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Portfólio selection: efficient diversification of investments]]></source>
<year>1959</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[John Wiley & Sons]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[NAKAMURA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W. T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Eficiência da carteira teórica do índice Bovespa no contexto da moderna teoria de carteiras]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São Paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SCHNEEWEIS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SPURGIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The benefits of managed futures]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PETERS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WARWICK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The handbook of managed futures: performance, evaluation and analysis]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<page-range>17-48</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[Irwin Professional Publishing]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SECURATO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Cálculo financeiro das tesourarias: bancos e empresas]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São Paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Saint Paul]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SHARPE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Mutual fund performance]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Business]]></source>
<year>Janu</year>
<month>ar</month>
<day>y </day>
<page-range>119-138</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TOBIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Liquidity preference as behavior towards risk]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Review of Economic Studies]]></source>
<year>Febr</year>
<month>ua</month>
<day>ry</day>
<numero>67</numero>
<issue>67</issue>
<page-range>65-86</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
