<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032003000100002</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032003000100002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Financial risk monitoring and transaction costs in coffee & soybean trading companies and processors]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bignotto]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Edson Costa]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Azevedo Filho]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Adriano]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of São Paulo Superior School of Agriculture Luiz de Queiróz Department of Economics, Business Administration and Rural Sociology]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>03</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>152</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032003000100002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[This study characterizes the use of risk monitoring mechanisms by coffee and soybean trading and processing companies. It also investigates the role these mechanisms play in the mitigation of certain transaction costs associated to bounded rationality, information asymmetry, and business opportunism in negotiations involving derivatives. The results presented are based on literature and original research, which consisted of interviews with 19 coffee and soybean trading and processing company agents that deal with the management and execution of derivatives trades. The interviews suggest that the interest in formal risk monitoring mechanisms depends strongly on the organizational structure of the business. In family businesses, in which the owner participates actively in negotiations, the interest is limited. In non-family businesses, where there is a clear separation between supervisory upper-management and agents involved with trading, the interest in risk monitoring systems is more evident. This result seems to indicate that the mitigation of transaction costs associated with information asymmetry and opportunism might be stronger motivations for interest in risk monitoring mechanisms than the costs resulting from bounded rationality.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[transaction cost]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[financial risk]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[coffee]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[soybeans]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font face="Verdana" size="4"><b>Financial risk monitoring and transaction    costs in coffee &amp; soybean trading companies and processors</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p ALIGN="RIGHT"></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Edson Costa Bignotto<sup>I</sup>; Adriano    Azevedo Filho<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><sup>I</sup>M.Sc.Economics, ESALQ-USP; Financial    Analyst &#151; MAPS Risk Management Solutions; <a href="mailto:ecbignotto@yahoo.com.br">ecbignotto@yahoo.com.br</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>PhD in Economics; Assistant Professor, Department of Economics,    Business Administration and Rural Sociology at ESALQ-USP. Piracicaba - SP -    Brazil. 13418-900. B.O.Box 9    <br>   </font> </p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p ALIGN="CENTER">&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">This study characterizes the use of risk monitoring    mechanisms by coffee and soybean trading and processing companies. It also investigates    the role these mechanisms play in the mitigation of certain transaction costs    associated to bounded rationality, information asymmetry, and business opportunism    in negotiations involving derivatives. The results presented are based on literature    and original research, which consisted of interviews with 19 coffee and soybean    trading and processing company agents that deal with the management and execution    of derivatives trades. The interviews suggest that the interest in formal risk    monitoring mechanisms depends strongly on the organizational structure of the    business. In family businesses, in which the owner participates actively in    negotiations, the interest is limited. In non-family businesses, where there    is a clear separation between supervisory upper-management and agents involved    with trading, the interest in risk monitoring systems is more evident. This    result seems to indicate that the mitigation of transaction costs associated    with information asymmetry and opportunism might be stronger motivations for    interest in risk monitoring mechanisms than the costs resulting from bounded    rationality.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Key-words:</b> transaction cost, financial    risk, coffee and soybeans</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>1. Introduction</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Brazilian coffee and soybean processing and trading    are responsible for a large part of the country’s agricultural export revenues:    Currently, Brazil’s soybean exports are the second largest in the world, and    its coffee bean production and exports lead the world. Trading companies and    processors often use derivative markets to hedge positions taken in commodities    markets. These hedging operations, in spite of allowing reduced risk from negative    price movements, expose organizations to the so-called &quot;financial risk&quot;    that originates from the unpredictability of economic systems.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">There are evidences that these organizations    encounter transaction costs related to operation with derivatives. These transaction    costs are generated by behavioral postulates inherent to the economic agents,    such as bounded rationality and opportunism, which, in turn, can be motivated/enhanced    by environmental conditions, such as information asymmetry. The use of formal    risk monitoring mechanisms, a practice suggested by many authors, can assist    in the economic mitigation of some of these transactional costs.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The present article is intended to characterize    the use of risk monitoring mechanisms by coffee and soybean trading and processing    companies, as well as the role these mechanisms have in the mitigation of transaction    costs generated by company derivatives trading. Important parts of our results    are based in original research. A large part of this research was in the form    of interviews with a sample of 19 professionals, mostly from coffee trading    and soybean processing companies, who are employed to deal with risk management    and derivatives trading.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">This study has five sections, the first being    the introduction. In the second section, we discuss the theoretical framework    and present brief summaries of several authors’ understandings regarding the    link between transaction costs and operations with derivatives. In addition,    the second section contains a discussion of the advantages and disadvantages    of current risk monitoring mechanisms, such as the VaR (Value at Risk) risk    measure. The third section presents the methodology underlying our empirical    research. This methodology depends on interviews with professionals involved,    direct or indirectly, with financial operations in the companies under analyses.    The fourth section contains the main results obtained from our empirical research,    and the last section is this study’s conclusion.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>2. Transaction Cost and Financial Risk Management</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A large number of empirical studies of the decision    process, in fields such as psychology and business administration&#151;summarized    in studies by Tversky &amp; Kahneman (1974), Hammond et al. (1998) and in the    references cited within these work, support the existence of important transaction    costs that are incurred when businesses face complex situations involving risk.    These costs arise from an incomplete understanding of the situation and communication    problems, two difficulties that characterize aspects of bounded rationality.    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The implications of bounded rationality on businesses    have been previously suggested and analyzed by Simon (1957) and, more recently,    made popular by Williamson (1975). Bounded rationality, a non-intentional characteristic    of human behavior, acting in an environment of asymmetric information between    agents can lead to intentional opportunistic behavior, which can cause business    losses. These notions are summarized by Williamson (1975) and by Milgrom &amp;    Roberts (1992) in a more systematic formal discussion of agent theory. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">From the studies mentioned above, one can conclude    that mechanisms for monitoring risk, which use risk measures intelligible to    businesses agents, may facilitate the reduction of transaction costs associated    to bounded rationality. By alerting management of potential risk, risk monitoring    mechanisms would help to reduce information asymmetry, thereby minimizing clearly    inappropriate decisions and blatant opportunism. The use of such monitoring    mechanisms, in the context mentioned, could expedite the design of control mechanisms    and facilitate decision making more consistently compatible with the business’s    interests.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The practical importance of the problems described    above is illustrated by the case of <I>Barings Bank</I>. In 1995, the British    bank <I>Barings</I> suffered losses of close to US$ 1.3 billion in the Japanese    currency and stock markets, caused mostly by decisions made by the agent responsible    for the bank’s front and back office operations in Asia (Jorion 1997). The losses    were conditioned, on one hand, by clearly inadequate decisions made by that    sole agent who believed them to be beneficial to the bank and to himself (bounded    rationality/opportunism), and, on the other hand, by the bank’s board of directors’    who did not understand the consequences of the agent’s decisions, consequences    which resulted in the bank’s expressive losses (asymmetrical information motivated    by lack of adequate monitoring).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Another example of the importance of risk monitoring    measures, discovered during an interview conduced in connection with the present    study, relates to the possibility of uncontrolled agent opportunism creating    business losses. In this case, the possibility of individual self-interest creating    undesired business results was brought about by the inadequate design of incentives    to promote optimal trading operations: traders received commissions from profits    but did not always share losses and were not properly monitored in regards to    the increment of company exposure to losses arising from their actions. The    use of appropriate risk monitoring mechanisms would have led to the design of    more appropriate incentive mechanisms.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the late 1980s, losses suffered by businesses    engaged in derivatives trading motivated the search for risk measures and risk    monitoring mechanisms that could be more easily understood by investors and    staff with a less sophisticated quantitative background. Many of the mechanisms    developed since then have been based on the quantification of risk through measures    such as Value at Risk&#151;VaR. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Formally, VaR can be understood as an estimated    value for losses established in a distribution of expected rates of return from    a portfolio of financial assets that is not to be equaled or exceeded with a    determined critical probability over a given period of time. In many contexts,    as, for example, under the assumption of normality, the information in the VaR    is equivalent, from the logical point of view, to risk measures based on variance    or on standard deviation. Nevertheless, market agents with no background in    statistical methodology seem to understand the risk information contained in    the VaR more easily than that presented by more conventional statistical measures.    The VaR tries to capture events that occur on the edges of the portfolio’s return    distribution.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Manfredo &amp; Leuthold (1998) suggest that the    advantages of VaR are associated to the possibility of its being reported in    a currency unit while serving as:</font></p> <OL TYPE="i"><font face="Verdana" size="2">       ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<LI>          <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">a tool used to spread information to control        personnel, traders, operators, risk managers, directors, shareholders as        an aid in their investment decisions;</font></p>   </LI>       <LI>          <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">a tool to help business and investment funds        determine resource allocation; and</font></p>   </LI>       <LI>          <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">a tool for performance evaluation, used to        compare results with some pre-established performance parameter, such as        a benchmark.</font></p>   </LI></font>     </OL>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Due to the meaningful volatility of commodity    spot market prices and the exchange rates risk of dealings in the international    market, the use of such risk measures by agribusinesses can be advisable. Risk    measurement and monitoring is called for by the complex derivatives trading    frequently employed by these organizations to hedge their investments and to    obtain financial gain through arbitrage and speculation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Danielsson et al. (1998) observe that regulatory    considerations also provide a strong incentive for the use of risk monitoring    mechanisms by members of the financial system. Implementation of risk monitoring    mechanisms, based in risk measures such as the VaR, demands investments in equipment,    software, changes in administrative procedures, and training. Without the pressure    of legal requirements, the magnitude of this investment leads organizations    outside the financial sector to question if these costs are merited by the magnitude    of the benefit </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">As a last comment, the results obtained in the    present study and reported in the following sections suggest that the degree    of the interest in risk monitoring mechanisms can be strongly affected by the    structure of the agribusiness organization.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>3. Methodology</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The empirical segment of the present study involved    the analysis of qualitative primary information obtained from interviews with    people involved, direct or indirectly, with financial decision making in the    soybean and coffee complexes’ processing and trading sectors. These two types    of Brazilian agribusinesses were chosen for study because they have substantial    economic importance in Brazil, operate in domestic and international derivatives    markets, and, most importantly, show differences in hierarchy and financial    management.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">To facilitate this presentation, the agribusiness    organizations researched have been classified into two stereotypical categories:</font>  </p> <OL TYPE="i"><font face="Verdana" size="2">       <LI>          <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><U>family businesses under the owners’ financial        management (FBUOFM)</u> – the majority of these businesses are capitalized        by domestic sources, controlled through inheritance or otherwise family        directed, and are financially managed directly by members of the family.        Although many of these companies are small, several of the major coffee        exporters are quite large, economically important FBUOFMs </font></p>   </LI>       <LI>          <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><U>businesses under hired professional financial        management (BUHPFM)</u> – the majority of these companies are big international        players dealing in Brazil. This category includes large domestic agribusiness        companies, some family-owned, which are financially administered by hired        agents who are not the owners.</font></p>   </LI></font>    </OL>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02t01.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The relatively small number of accessible businesses    and confidentiality issues associated with the required research information    greatly restricted the number of people willing to participate in this study.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The comprehensive and open interviews were intended    to capture not only experiences of the person interviewed regarding their own    companies but also their knowledge about similar organizations. These interviews    were held in person or via e-mail. The personal interviews involved 2 to 3 hour    contacts, which were recorded for accuracy. The e-mail interviews were initiated    through telephone contact and conducted over several e-mail exchanges.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Interviewees were asked about (a) the processes    that lead to financial decisions; (b) the relationship among agents within their    business’s several hierarchical levels; (c) existing interest in operations    that might reduce the impact of financial risk, such as hedging; and, (d) their    perception of the advantages and disadvantages of risk monitoring mechanisms,    essentially VaR. For the most part, the questions were intended to characterize    the process that results in operations/transactions involving hedges, speculation,    and arbitrage in the spot and futures markets. The professionals interviewed    have been listed according to their position and the scope of their business,    as shown in <a href="#tab2">Table 2</a>.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab2"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02t02.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>4. Results and Discussion</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Analysis of the material collected in the interviews    suggests that a company’s use of more formal risk monitoring mechanisms is determined    by its dimension and the amount of direct owner participation in the execution    of operations.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In FBUOFMs, more typical of coffee bean export    companies, the owners actively participate in operations, acting as traders    or directly monitoring other agents’ performance at the operations desk. In    these companies, employed traders usually have little autonomy, reporting their    decisions directly to company owners. FBUOFMs do not use formal risk monitoring    processes and/or specialized agents to supervise these processes. The proximity    of company owners is felt to reduce the need for the strict gathering, processing,    and analyses of information that characterizes the executed operations and the    risks derived from these operations.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The important decisions regarding Brazilian FBUOFM    financial operations are made directly by the business’s owners, generally using    intuition and practical rules largely inferred from experience. These owners    are quite afraid of introducing methodologies they perceive as costly, whose    benefits are not clear, and that are dependent on unfamiliar concepts. As the    owners are involved in all important decisions, the problem of agent (trader)    opportunism is relatively controlled. Decision making through intuitively learned    methods can, nevertheless, generate losses associated due to the agents’ bounded    rationality. Decisions based on intuition and practical rules (heuristic) can    be useful in a general way but result in severe and systematic mistakes in many    cases, especially in an environment strongly characterized by complexity and    uncertainty (Tversky &amp; Kahneman 1974 and Hammond et al. 1998).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The BUHPFMs examined in our study are typically    soybean processors and soybean trading organizations. The salient feature that    distinguishes BUHPFMs from FBUOFMs is the clear separation of owners from company    operations, monitoring, and decision making. BUHPFM owners are removed from    company administrators, the latter being hired professionals. Job positions    in BUHPFMs are filled by specialized agents, and job responsibilities are more    clearly defined than in FBUOFMs. BUHPFM operations and their monitoring are    under the charge of different agents who report to the company board of directors    and owners through management. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In FBUOFMs, the relationship between owners and    traders is direct and informal: there is no go-between. Decisions regarding    financial operations and their monitoring are broadly discussed, although the    final decision is the owner’s. Thus, the connection between the board of directors    and traders is close and operations often conducted jointly; in many cases the    owner working directly with the brokers.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In BUHPFMs, the relationship between the board    and traders is intermediated by the back office, which has the risk manager    as its main agent. These businesses try to formalize the need for hedging, the    limits of exposure, and the danger associated with derivative contracts in reports.    These reports are periodically presented to the board of directors and the operations    desk by the back office staff. Respecting their superior’s decisions, traders    strive to meet specified goals while adhering to defined stop loss parameters,    even when they disagree with those decisions. This is not to say that company    boards of directors reject the idea of trader speculation. Most boards accept    and even encourage their traders to speculate knowing that monitored speculation    by informed traders can provide valuable experience and ultimately is good for    the company. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The existing organizational structure of the    two types of businesses described above is summarized in <a href="#fig1">Figure    1</a>. The Figure diagrams the relationships among different hierarchical levels    within FBUOFMs and BUHPFMs. <a href="#tab3">Table 3</a> presents a synthesis    of this information gathered through this study’s empirical research.</font></p>     <p><a name="fig1"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a href="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02f01.gif"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02f01t.gif" border="0"></a></p>     <p align="center"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Figure 1</b> - Click to enlarge</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab3"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02t03.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Interest in the use of formal methods to measure    and report financial exposure from operations is much more evident in BUHPFMs    than in FBUOFMs. The use of formal methodologies to monitor and measure risk    was found useful to both communicate business exposure to losses at several    decision levels and to support the design of mechanisms that motivate traders    to make decisions more aligned with organization goals. In businesses where    formal risk monitoring mechanisms are used, traders whose operations may cause    an exposure to risk above established levels can be chastised and even dismissed.    These businesses found that the frequent need to generate the operations reports    that formal risk monitoring demands acted as a control mechanism in itself,    minimizing potential problems arising from bounded rationality.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>5. Conclusion</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The BUHPFMs described in the previous section    showed strong interest in the improvement of risk measurement and inter-company    communication. This is most likely motivated by the significant potential for    information asymmetry, a result of their hierarchic structure that clearly separates    upper administration from derivatives operations. Such a situation motivates    these organizations to seek more efficient mechanisms to facilitate the rationalization    of information flow, despite the related costs. Risk monitoring mechanisms based    on VaR were perceived as a useful auxiliary tool to insure the proper relationship    between economic agents involved in the business’s decision phases and agents    working in the business’s financial operations and execution phases.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In FBUOFMs, the closeness of owners to operations    tends to minimize the formal flow of risk monitoring information. Unfortunately,    this can lead to potential business failures brought about by the agents’ bounded    rationality and the use of intuition rather than data as the main guide for    decision-making &#91;Hammond et al. (1998) provide a more detailed description of    the problems caused by the dependence on intuition for business success&#93;. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The potential for transaction costs resulting    from the behavioral postulates and environmental conditions previously discussed    in this study is summarized in <a href="#tab4">Table 4</a>.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab4"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v41n1/p02t04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Finally, the difference in interest in risk monitoring    mechanisms demonstrated by FBUOFMs and BUHPFMs suggests that the mitigation    of transaction costs associated to information asymmetry/opportunism is a stronger    motivation for interest in these mechanisms than the costs resulting from bounded    rationality. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">DANIELSSON, J.; DE VRIES, C. G.; HARTMANN, P.    <B>The cost of conservatism: </B>extreme returns, value-at-risk, and the Basle    ‘multiplication factor’. Londres: London School of Economics, Jan. 1998. 10p.    (Working Paper)</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000093&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">HAMMOND, J. S.; KEENEY, R. L.; RAIFFA, H. The    hidden traps in decision making. <B>Harvard Business Review, </B>p.3-9, Sep./Oct.    1998. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000094&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">JORION, P. <B>Value at risk:</B> the new benchmark    for controlling derivatives risk. Chicago: Irwin Professional Publishing, 1997.    332p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000095&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MANFREDO, M. R.; LEUTHOLD, R. M. <B>Agricultural    application of value at risk analysis: </B>a perspective. Urbana-Champaign:    University of Illinois, 1998. 14p. (Working Paper)</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000096&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MILGROM, P.; ROBERTS, J. <B>Economics organization    and management.</B> New Jersey: Prentice Hall, 1992. 621p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000097&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">SIMON, H. <B>Models of man</B>: social and rational.    New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1957. 279p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000098&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">TVERSKY, A.; KAHNEMAN, D. Judgment under uncertainty:    heuristics and biases. <B>Science,</B> v.185, p.1124-1131, 1974.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000099&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">WILLIAMSON, O. <B>Markets and hierarchies:</B>    analysis and anti-trust implications. New York: The Free Press, 1975. 286p.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000100&pid=S0103-2003200300010000200008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DANIELSSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DE VRIES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HARTMANN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The cost of conservatism: extreme returns, value-at-risk, and the Basle ‘multiplication factor’]]></source>
<year>Jan.</year>
<month> 1</month>
<day>99</day>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Londres ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[London School of Economics]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HAMMOND]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KEENEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. L.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RAIFFA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The hidden traps in decision making]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Harvard Business Review]]></source>
<year>Sep.</year>
<month>/O</month>
<day>ct</day>
<page-range>3-9</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JORION]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Value at risk: the new benchmark for controlling derivatives risk]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Chicago ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Irwin Professional Publishing]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MANFREDO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LEUTHOLD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Agricultural application of value at risk analysis: a perspective]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Urbana-Champaign ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Illinois]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MILGROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ROBERTS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Economics organization and management]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New Jersey ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Prentice Hall]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SIMON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Models of man: social and rational]]></source>
<year>1957</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[John Wiley & Sons]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TVERSKY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KAHNEMAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Judgment under uncertainty: heuristics and biases]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Science]]></source>
<year>1974</year>
<volume>185</volume>
<page-range>1124-1131</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WILLIAMSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[O.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Markets and hierarchies: analysis and anti-trust implications]]></source>
<year>1975</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The Free Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
