<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0103-2003</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Revista de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Rev. Econ. Sociol. Rural]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0103-2003</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sociedade Brasileira de Economia e Sociologia Rural]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0103-20032007000400003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-20032007000400003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Impacts of a liberalization in the USA market for Frozen Concentrated Orange Juice: why Florida's producers are so afraid?]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Fracalanza]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Paulo Sérgio]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ferreira]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Adriana Nunes]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Neves]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Marcos Fava]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A03"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Unicamp Instituto de Economia ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,Unicamp Instituto de Economia ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<aff id="A03">
<institution><![CDATA[,USP FEARP ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>45</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<fpage>855</fpage>
<lpage>877</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0103-20032007000400003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0103-20032007000400003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0103-20032007000400003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[This study aims at examining the resource allocation and welfare implications of the reduction of barriers in the United States market for Frozen Concentrated Orange Juice (FCOJ) imported from Brazil. The present paper is organized as follows: section 2 presents an overview of the main features of the market and current trade regime for orange juice, as well as the possible impacts of liberalization within FTAA and with the European Union; section 3 describes the partial equilibrium model of imperfect substitute goods used to estimate the impact of trade liberalization in the United States, on prices and quantities and on welfare; in section 4 two possible scenarios for liberalization are designed using the large country model. The last section summarizes the main conclusions.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Este artigo tem por objetivo contribuir para o exame das implicações em termos da alocação de recursos e de bem-estar de uma eventual redução das barreiras tarifárias no mercado dos EUA de suco de laranja concentrado e congelado (FCOJ) importado do Brasil. Depois da introdução, uma segunda seção apresenta uma visão geral das principais características do mercado e do regime de comércio para o suco de laranja, bem como uma avaliação preliminar dos possíveis impactos da liberalização comercial dentro do quadro de acordos comerciais com o NAFTA e com a União Européia. A terceira seção descreve os modelos de equilíbrio parcial com bens substitutos utilizados para o exame dos impactos em termos de quantidades, preços e bem-estar da redução tarifária nos mercados de FCOJ dos EUA. A quarta seção apresenta dois possíveis cenários da liberalização comercial usando o modelo de «país grande». A última seção sumariza os principais resultados.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Commercial liberalization]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[reduction of trade barriers]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[partial equilibrium models]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[frozen concentrated orange juice (FCOJ)]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Liberalização comercial]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[redução de barreiras tarifárias]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[modelos de equilíbrio parcial]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[suco de laranja concentrado e congelado]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font size="4" face="verdana"><b>Impacts of a liberalization in the USA market    for Frozen Concentrated Orange Juice: why Florida's producers are so afraid?</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Paulo S&eacute;rgio Fracalanza<sup>I</sup>;    Adriana Nunes Ferreira<sup>II</sup>; Marcos Fava Neves<sup>III</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><sup>I</sup>Professor Doutor no Instituto de    Economia da Unicamp e nas Faculdades de Campinas (FACAMP). Pesquisador do N&uacute;cleo    de Economia Industrial e da Tecnologia (NEIT) do IE/Unicamp. <a href="mailto:fracalan@gmail.com.br">fracalan@gmail.com.br</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Professora Doutora no Instituto de Economia da Unicamp e Pesquisadora    do N&uacute;cleo de Economia Industrial e da Tecnologia (NEIT) do IE/Unicamp    <br>   <sup>III</sup>Professor Livre-Docente na FEARP/USP</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This study aims at examining the resource allocation    and welfare implications of the reduction of barriers in the United States market    for Frozen Concentrated Orange Juice (FCOJ) imported from Brazil. The present    paper is organized as follows: section 2 presents an overview of the main features    of the market and current trade regime for orange juice, as well as the possible    impacts of liberalization within FTAA and with the European Union; section 3    describes the partial equilibrium model of imperfect substitute goods used to    estimate the impact of trade liberalization in the United States, on prices    and quantities and on welfare; in section 4 two possible scenarios for liberalization    are designed using the large country model. The last section summarizes the    main conclusions.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Key words:</b> Commercial liberalization,    reduction of trade barriers, partial equilibrium models, frozen concentrated    orange juice (FCOJ).    <br>   <b>JEL Classification:</b> F13 - Commercial Policy; Protection; Promotion; Trade    Negotiations </font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Este artigo tem por objetivo contribuir para    o exame das implica&ccedil;&otilde;es em termos da aloca&ccedil;&atilde;o de    recursos e de bem-estar de uma eventual redu&ccedil;&atilde;o das barreiras    tarif&aacute;rias no mercado dos EUA de suco de laranja concentrado e congelado    (FCOJ) importado do Brasil. Depois da introdu&ccedil;&atilde;o, uma segunda    se&ccedil;&atilde;o apresenta uma vis&atilde;o geral das principais caracter&iacute;sticas    do mercado e do regime de com&eacute;rcio para o suco de laranja, bem como uma    avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o preliminar dos poss&iacute;veis impactos da liberaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o    comercial dentro do quadro de acordos comerciais com o NAFTA e com a Uni&atilde;o    Europ&eacute;ia. A terceira se&ccedil;&atilde;o descreve os modelos de equil&iacute;brio    parcial com bens substitutos utilizados para o exame dos impactos em termos    de quantidades, pre&ccedil;os e bem-estar da redu&ccedil;&atilde;o tarif&aacute;ria    nos mercados de FCOJ dos EUA. A quarta se&ccedil;&atilde;o apresenta dois poss&iacute;veis    cen&aacute;rios da liberaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o comercial usando o modelo de    «pa&iacute;s grande». A &uacute;ltima se&ccedil;&atilde;o sumariza os principais    resultados.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><B>Palavras-chave:</b> Liberaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o    comercial, redu&ccedil;&atilde;o de barreiras tarif&aacute;rias, modelos de    equil&iacute;brio parcial, suco de laranja concentrado e congelado.    <br>   <B>Classifica&ccedil;&atilde;o JEL:</b> F13</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>1. Introduction</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Together, Brazil and the USA comprise over 90%    of world output of orange juice. Both countries are large producers, but the    Brazilians have reached levels of production costs that the US producers cannot    match. Currently, Brazilian exports face high barriers in the USA, and this    has led Brazil to lodge complaints at the WTO.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The combination of large efficiency gaps between    producers and high barriers make the orange juice industry one of the loci of    strong resistance to trade liberalization either in a MERCOSUR-NAFTA agreement    or in FTAA.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">As a matter of fact, the degree of support for    or resistance to reductions in trade protection varies from sector to sector,    depending on the gaps in competitiveness and on the existing levels of protection,    among other factors. Sectors in which producers perceive competitive gaps as    being relatively small and where trade is already intense will probably resist    liberalization less than other sectors. Sectors where competitive gaps are large    and where trade barriers are currently high are natural candidates to show strong    resistance. The sectoral perspective is therefore essential in order to identify    potential business support for and/or resistance to further progress in current    trade negotiations.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Thus, this study aims at examining the resource    allocation and welfare implications of the lowering of barriers in the United    States market for frozen concentrated orange juice (FCOJ) imported from MERCOSUR,    specifically from Brazil. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The article is organized as follows: section    2 presents an overview of the main features of the market and current trade    regime for orange juice, as well as the possible impacts of liberalization within    FTAA and with the European Union; section 3 describes the partial equilibrium    model of imperfect substitute goods used to estimate the impact of trade liberalization    on domestic production in the United States, on prices and quantities and on    welfare; in section 4 two possible scenarios for liberalization are designed    using the version of a large country model. The last section summarizes the    main conclusions.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>2. Trade flows and trade policy</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>2.1. Supply and demand in the international    market of FCOJ</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The world market for fruit juice is very dynamic.    Sales, which showed an average annual growth rate of 5%, reached $31 billion    in 1998. Approximately half of that amount results from sales of orange juice.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">World orange production is concentrated in four    countries. Brazil is the major producer with about 27 thousand rural production    units, and is responsible for 34% of world orange production and 47% of the    total orange juice production. The USA is the second largest producer. <a href="#tab01">Table    1</a> shows data on the principal producers of oranges and Frozen Concentrated    Orange Juice in 1999/2000.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><a name="tab01"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab01.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The Brazilian orange juice industry is acknowledged    as being the most competitive in the world. Production costs in Brazil are lower    than in other countries. The average productivity of the orange groves in Brazil    has grown 30% over the last decade, reaching 599 boxes per hectare in 2002,    well above levels achieved in several countries.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">However, it is important to point out that average    farm productivity in Brazil is lower than in the USA. In Brazil, the yield is    around 2 boxes (40.8kg)/tree, while in the USA it is around 3.5 boxes/tree.    There are two main reasons for this: firstly, the area used in the USA is almost    100% irrigated, which means increased land productivity; and secondly, the USA    produces more Hamlin fruit than Brazil (53% of the USA area, against 13% in    Brazil), this being a kind of orange that permits greater volume of juice production,    although the quality of the juice is inferior. There are no significant differences    in productivity between the Brazilian and US orange juice industries because    the equipment used is the same.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Hence, the lower Brazilian production costs are    not due to a higher productivity. The main reasons for the superior competitiveness    of Brazilian orange juice production are smaller farm inputs, and lower land    and labor (used for picking the oranges) costs.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following table shows the compared structure    of operational costs in Sao Paulo – the main Brazilian orange juice producing    state – and Florida.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Operational costs are significantly higher in    Florida than in Sao Paulo. Brazilian orange production does not utilize irrigation    and involves lower labor costs (which also help to explain lower operation costs).    In spite of being 90% higher than Sao Paulo’s operational costs when measured    per hectare, Florida’s costs differ only 47% from Sao Paulo’s when measured    per box. This is explained by the above-mentioned superior productivity per    tree of Florida’s production.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab03">Table 3</a> shows comparative    picking and transportation costs for Sao Paulo and Florida orange production.    It is clear that these are the main items responsible for the considerably higher    orange production costs in Florida. There is a scarcity of local workers for    the job and the severe government restrictions on hiring foreign workers raises    the cost of labor, so the costs of orange picking and transportation in Florida    are even greater than operational costs.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab02.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab03"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab03.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Finally, <a href="#tab04">table 4</a> shows the    comparison of a third important element in orange production costs in Sao Paulo    and Florida: tax payments.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab04"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab04.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The most important differences have to do with    property, water management and DOC assessment<a name="tx01"></a><a href="#nt01"><sup>1</sup></a>    taxes; these are not paid by Brazilian producers but they are a heavy burden    in Florida. Brazilian taxes on rural property and to the Citric Producers Association    together only add $0.09 per box to the total cost.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In spite of operating with much lower productivity    per tree, Brazilian orange producers have huge cost advantages over producers    in Florida. The most important factors are operational differences in the cost    of picking and transportation, which are mostly due to different prices for    labor. This is why, in 2001/2002, with prices per box of $3.54, Florida producers    faced a loss of $0.68 per box, while Brazilian producers, with sale prices of    $2.75, made a profit of $0.84 per box. Florida producers are investing heavily    in picking mechanization in order to reduce that cost disadvantage, but results    will not immediately be apparent.<a name="tx02"></a><a href="#nt02"><sup>2</sup></a></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Brazilian orange juice producers have used their    cost advantages to become important players in world trade. Brazil is the absolute    leader in FCOJ world exports. 80% of FCOJ world exports (which amounted to 1.4    million metric tons in 2001) are Brazilian. <a href="#tab06">Table 6</a> shows    the volume of FCOJ exported by the main international trade players. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab05.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab06"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab06.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Orange products are an important item in Brazilian    exports and make a significant contribution to earnings of hard currency. <a href="#tab07">Table    7</a> shows the share of orange products in total Brazilian exports, in 2000/2001    and 2001/2002. In 2000/2001, orange products contributed 2% of the total value    of Brazilian exports. It is worth noticing that 93.6% of total orange products    are FCOJ. In 2001/2002, despite the fact that the volume of orange product exports    in general (and of FCOJ in particular) grew, the share of those products in    total exports, in value terms, went down (from 2% to 1.6%). The fall in the    international price for FCOJ helps to explain this. Indeed, FCOJ has been facing    low quotations, high stocks and excess of supply in recent years. </font></p>     <p><a name="tab07"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab07.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The European Union is the main market for Brazilian    FCOJ exports. Exports to Europe amount to 69% of the total, and the USA market    accounts for the another 21% of Brazilian FCOJ exports. The share of the US    market fell during the 90s as a result of competition from Mexican exports,    which benefited from lower barriers established within the NAFTA agreement.    <a href="#tab08">Table 8</a> shows the destination of Brazilian FCOJ exports.</font></p>     <p><a name="tab08"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab08.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Finally, it should be added that Brazilian imports    of orange products are almost nil. In 2001, these imports were only $1.4 million    and 1.1 million tons. Orange essential oils amount to 65% of the value of orange    product imports. Brazil is therefore the leading net exporter country in the    orange juice market, and about one fifth of its exports go the USA market.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The USA is the largest market for orange juice    and the second largest producer. USA producers export part of their output,    mainly to Europe, but domestic consumption requires imports of FCOJ, mainly    from Brazil and from Mexico. In 2001, USA were responsible for 41.3% and 33.6%    of world-wide FCOJ imports, in terms of quantity and value, respectively. Overall,    the trade balance for orange juice in the USA is negative.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Lastly, <a href="#tab09">table 9</a> shows the    countries of origin of US FCOJ imports. For the purposes of this study, the    most important point to note is the importance of Brazil as a source of the    USA’s FCOJ imports. Mexico is also an important player, and, as mentioned above,    it has benefited from import tax reductions within NAFTA. </font></p>     <p><a name="tab09"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab09.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>2.2. FCOJ protection in MERCOSUR and the    USA</i></b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">MERCOSUR's common external tariff (CET) for orange    juice is currently 15%. However, given the high competitiveness of Brazilian    production, tariff protection is not really necessary to prevent imports of    orange products. This means that the lowering of tariffs can be used by Brazil    as an important bargaining instrument in current trade negotiations.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">On the other hand, in the European Union, the    tariff applied to FCOJ imports originating from Brazil is around 35%. Brazil    also faces high trade barriers on its FCOJ exports to the US market. FCOJ imported    from Brazil faces barriers in the form of a per unit tax equivalent to a 56.7%    <I>ad valorem</I> tax.</font></p>     <p> <font size="2" face="Verdana">It may be useful to explain how per unit tax    adopted by the USA is translated into a percentage of the price of FCOJ, or    into an <I>ad valorem</I> tax. The <I>ad valorem</I> tax imposed by the USA    on the orange juice imported from Brazil is calculated from the per unit tax    levied on the <I>reconstituted</I> orange juice. In the American market, per    unit tax is $0.0785 per liter of <I>reconstituted</I> orange juice ready for    consumption. This tax does not change when there are fluctuations in the prices    of the product, therefore its <I>ad valorem</I> equivalent is higher when prices    are low. The calculation of the <I>ad valorem</I> equivalent factor is based    on two parameters: 1) the average price of orange juice, and 2) the conversion    factor of <I>concentrated</I> for <I>reconstituted</I> juice. In this study,    Hemispheric Database/FTAA V.1.0. parameters were adopted, generating an <I>ad    valorem</I> equivalent factor of 56.7% for FCOJ.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In addition, in the State of Florida, the Brazilian    product had to pay another excise tax of 0.027 dollars per gallon ($40/ton)    as an equalization tax. The tax imposed by the State of Florida was challenged    in court by importers, and as a result, in April 2002, the Florida Citrus Commission    was ordered to propose a remedy in the equalization tax case. The court ruled    that the equalization tax was unconstitutional because it illegally discriminated    against foreign citrus products imported into Florida while exempting juice    products imported from other states, mainly from California. As a result of    the court’s ruling, the Florida legislature abolished tax exemption for domestic    juice, with the new law taking effect in July 2002. Brazil asked for consultations    under the WTO, and discussions were opened between Brazilian and US officials.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Brazilian FCOJ competes directly with Mexican    exports in the USA market. The FCOJ imports from Mexico pay taxes equivalent    to a 30.7% <I>ad valorem</I> tax.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The most probable outcome of barrier reductions    resulting from negotiations within FTAA and/or with the European Union would    be an increase in international prices and an increase in FCOJ imports. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The impact of liberalization should be different    in the European market and in the USA. The European market is already saturated,    and Brazil accounts for almost all FCOJ imports in that continent. On the other    hand, in the USA market there will be room for a considerable increase in the    Brazilian share of FCOJ sales, after US and Mexican output adjust to the new    situation. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Overall, the global market for FCOJ can be considered    as a textbook case of the impact of trade barriers on output, on trade and on    international price formation. In particular, a reduction in the trade barriers    faced by Brazilian exporters in the North American FCOJ market would induce    an increase in international prices and imports. As a result, Brazilian exporters    would benefit from higher prices and from an increase in their share of the    American market.<a name="tx03"></a><a href="#nt03"><sup>3</sup></a> These issues    will be addressed in the sections below, in a simulation using a partial equilibrium    model.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>3. The theoretical model and methodological    aspects</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>3.1. Overview of the partial equilibrium    approach</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In order to calculate the welfare and distributional    effects of a reduction in trade barriers in the American FCOJ market, and, for    our purposes, the potential rise in Brazilian FCOJ exports to the USA, a version    of Hufbauer and Elliot’s<a name="tx04"></a><a href="#nt04"><sup>4</sup></a>    partial equilibrium model of imperfect substitutes with perfect competitive    markets is used.</font> </p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Compared to computable general equilibrium models,    the partial equilibrium models have two evident advantages: they are less complex    and more transparent. Moreover, when the goal is the treatment of a single market    at a very detailed level, a partial equilibrium model is often the only feasible    way to proceed. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The different generations of partial equilibrium    models share at least two common assumptions. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Firstly, in a partial equilibrium model, the    impact of a change in the market under investigation is assumed not to disturb    related markets. However, this is not to say that the related markets are solemnly    ignored. As Francois (1997) rightly stated, the price elasticity of demand included    in these models is conceived to reflect underlying linkages between related    markets, even though in the implementation of a partial equilibrium model such    linkages are sterilized.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Secondly, in a partial equilibrium model, the    income effects that arise from a trade policy change are not considered. As    a consequence, the demand functions used in these models are represented as    being dependent only on prices and not on income, which is treated as an exogenous    variable. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Broadly speaking, partial equilibrium models    can be classified according to: a) the degree of substitutability of the domestic    and imported good; b) the specification of the import supply function; c) the    choice of implementation of the model in a linear or non-linear form.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The first distinction divides partial equilibrium    models according to the degree of substitutability of the domestically produced    and imported good in perfect substitutes and imperfect substitutes models.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">On the one hand, in the less complex perfect    substitutes model, the imported and domestic goods are considered to be perfectly    homogeneous from the consumers’ point of view. In this case, the import demand    function is simply defined as the difference between consumption and domestic    production, and therefore all the analysis is conducted in the import market.    Nevertheless, as suggested by Bowen (1998), in spite of the attractiveness of    these models, the assumption of perfect substitutes is generally not consistent    with empirically estimated values of the price elasticity of demand.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">On the other hand, in the imperfect substitutes    model, the domestic and imported goods are considered to be non homogeneous    in the eyes of the consumer. The practical consequence of this notion is that    in these models there are two different demand functions, one for the domestically    produced good and another for the imported good, both dependent on the internal    prices of the domestic and imported goods. Therefore, when analyzing the impact    of the reduction in tariffs, it is necessary to take into account the repercussion    in the two connected markets.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p> <font size="2" face="Verdana">The second important distinction in the context    of partial equilibrium models has its roots in the assumption of the importance    of the foreign exporter country. If the exporter is a big player in the domestic    and international market, it is tempting to assume that its supply schedule    is flat, i.e. perfectly elastic. Such a model is known as a <I>small country</I>    model because it is understood that the importer country is unable to influence    the prices of the imported good. In contrast, in a <I>large country </I>model,    it is assumed that the importer country is large and therefore able to influence    the prices of goods on world markets. If this is the case, the import supply    function will be positively sloped, and thus the magnitude of the change in    world price and volume of imports will depend significantly on the elasticity    of foreign export supply. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Finally, the last difference between partial    equilibrium models has to do with the particular mode of their computational    implementation. Generally, the functions used in these models are supposed to    have constant elasticity. All that has to be done is to solve the system of    equations for prices and then use the solution to solve them for quantities.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">If a linear approximation is chosen, all the    equations can be easily derived in log form. This results in a simpler procedure    to solve the problem. However, as Francois &amp; Hall (1997) pointed out, using    a linear model, even in a single market, leads to a linearization error that    becomes larger when policy changes are significant.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The alternative procedure is to solve the equations    in prices and quantities in a non-linear system, i.e. without using the equations    in log form. Although in this way the linearization error is minimized, the    price to be paid for this is a higher degree of computational complexity.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>3.2. The structure and implementation of    large country models</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The next two sections form an introduction to    the structure and procedures of implementation of a partial equilibrium of a    large country model. The main hypotheses, equations and variables are presented    in the first section. Moreover, this section offers a graphic exposition in    the markets under analysis of the standard procedures of welfare evaluation    effects. The second section introduces the steps for estimating elasticities    and the calibration of parameters.</font> </p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>3.2.1. Large country models</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The implementation of a large country model is    very similar to that of small country model. The main difference resides in    the assumption that the importer country is large and hence able to influence    the prices of goods on world markets. If this is the case, the supply function    of the imported good will be positively sloped and therefore the magnitude of    the change in world price and volume of imports will depend significantly on    the price elasticity of the supply of the imported good. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The system of equations is summarized below.    The domestically produced good and its imported substitute are designated by    the indexes <I>d</I> and <I>m</I>.</font></p>     <p ALIGN="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03frm01.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">where <i>D<sub>d</sub></i> and <i>D<sub>m</sub></i>    are the quantities consumed of good <I>d </I>and <I>m</I> respectively; <i>S<sub>d</sub></i>    and <i>S<sub>m</sub></i> are, respectively, the quantities produced of good    <I>d</I> and <I>m</I>; <i>p<sub>d</sub> </i>and <i>p<sub>m</sub> </i>are the    internal prices of good <I>d</I> and <I>m</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>dd    </sub></i>is the own-price elasticity of demand of good <I>d</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>dm</sub>    </i>is the cross-price elasticity of demand of good <I>d</I> in relation to    good <I>m</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>s</sub> </i>is the price    elasticity of supply of good <I>d</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>mm</sub>    </i>is the own-price elasticity of demand of good <I>m</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>md</sub>    </i>is the cross-price elasticity of demand of good <I>m</I> in relation to    good <I>d</I>; <font face="Symbol">e</font><i><sub>sm</sub> </i>is the price    elasticity of supply of good <I>m; p</I><SUP>*</SUP> is the world export price;    <I>t</I> is the level of tariffs.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The first three equations of the model define    demand and supply functions and the equilibrium condition in the market of the    domestically produced good. The fourth equation expresses the internal price    of the imported good. The last three equations represent demand and supply functions    and the equilibrium condition in the market of the imported good. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">This system of seven independent equations can    be easily solved to generate values for seven endogenous variables, <i>D<sub>d</sub>,    S<sub>d</sub>, P<sub>d</sub>, P<sub>m</sub>, P*, D<sub>m</sub></i> and <i>S<sub>m</sub></i>.    A change in the level of the tariff allows the calculation of the new endogenous    variables. Needless to say, if the exercise imposes a complete elimination of    the initial tariff, the value of the final internal price of the imported good    (<i>p</i>*') will be equal to the price received by the importer (<i>p<sub>m</sub></i>')    and in this case, the fourth equation is redundant. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It is important to say that for the implementation    of this model it is crucial to know the values of all exogenous variables, i.e.    the elasticities and initial quantities of domestic production and import, and    the internal prices of the domestic and imported good.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following graph represents the market for    the imported good and the modifications that occur once the tariff is altered.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Equilibrium is achieved at point E when the trade    barrier is placed at its initial value. Since the supply curve is now upward,    a wedge appears between the internal price and the price obtained by the exporter    in this market, respectively <i>p<sub>m</sub></i> and <i>p</i>*. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">When the tariff is completely eliminated, the    subsequent decrease in the price of the imported good induces a fall in the    demand schedule in the market for the domestically produced good. The modifications    in terms of prices, quantities and welfare in the market for the domestically    produced good are the same as before.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Conversely, the consequent decline in the price    of the domestic good causes a shift to the left of and below the demand schedule    of the imported good represented in <a href="#grf01">graph 1</a>, by the new    demand schedule Dm’. The final outcome is an increase in quantity, and the same    price for the exporter and for the American consumer. This new price prevailing    for both the exporter and the American consumer will lie between the initial    prices <i>p<sub>m</sub></i> and <i>p</i>*.</font></p>     <p><a name="grf01"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03grf01.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The final step involves understanding how to    compute the welfare effects in the market for imported good using <a href="#grf01">graph    1</a>. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Once the importer country influences prices on    world markets, the impact in terms of welfare of a tariff reduction will be    distributed between three agents: consumers, government and foreign exporters.    </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">With the complete elimination of a tariff (the    analysis is similar when the tariff is partially reduced), consumers gain with    lower prices and larger quantities. The consumer surplus equals the area of    the trapezium <i>p<sub>m</sub>, E<sub>1</sub>, E</i>'<i>, p</i>*'. Exporters    will also benefit from higher prices and increased quantities, and their surplus    can be measured by the area of the trapezium <i>p</i>*'<i>, E</i>'<i>, E<sub>2</sub>,    p*</i>. Finally, the government loses tariff revenues equal to the area of the    rectangle <i>p<sub>m</sub>, E<sub>1</sub>, E<sub>2</sub>, p</i>*.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b><i>3.2.2. Estimation of elasticities and calibration    of parameters</i></b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In the literature, the lack of estimates for    all the elasticities needed could pose a serious problem in the implementation    of a partial equilibrium model. Nevertheless, this difficulty may be overcome    if at least some data is available. In the case of FCOJ, the price elasticity    of aggregate demand for imports and the domestic good combined, as well as the    elasticity of substitution between the domestic and imported products are available    in the seminal work by Hufbauer and Elliot (1994). Assuming that the demand    structure is of the CES form, the estimates of the own-price elasticities of    demand may be obtained using the following equations:</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03img01.gif"></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">where <i><b>S<sub>1</sub></b></i> is the share    in volume of the domestic product in consumption and <i><b>S<sub>2</sub></b></i>    is the share by quantity of imports in consumption; <b><font face="Symbol">s</font></b>    is the elasticity of substitution between the domestic and imported good; <b><font face="Symbol">e</font><sub><i>T</i></sub></b>    is the price elasticity of total demand.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">After calculating the values of the own-price    elasticities of demand, the cross-price elasticities in the CES case can be    obtained following a methodology proposed by Tarr (1990):</font></p>     <blockquote>        <p><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03img02.gif"></p> </blockquote>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Once all the elasticities are obtained, the next    step can be taken. The calibration of the model consists in calculating the    values of the constants 1n<i>a</i>, 1n<i>b</i>, 1n<i>c</i> and 1n<i>d</i> in    equations (1), (2), (5) and (6). The procedure for calculating the constants    is easily performed with the initial values of quantities and prices assuming    that the start situation expresses an undistorted equilibrium. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Finally, when this task is completed, the model    is ready to be implemented. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>4. Results</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In order to estimate the impact of tariff reductions    in the American FCOJ market in terms of resource allocation and welfare implications,    a partial equilibrium model of imperfect substitutes are used, considering the    domestic American FCOJ market a large country. The results are presented in    the next section. Besides, two different scenarios for the evaluation of the    impact of liberalization in the US FCOJ market were constructed. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The first scenario investigates the effects of    a complete elimination of the per unit tax equivalent to a 56.7% <I>ad valorem</I>    tax. The second scenario evaluates the impact of a partial reduction in the    <I>ad valorem</I> tax to the same level as that applicable on Mexican exports    of FCOJ to the USA. The second scenario is considered to be far more realistic    because by joining the FTAA, Brazil will most probably benefit more from the    same market access conditions than Mexico.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The following table summarizes the initial values    of prices and quantities in the years 1999-2000, and the values of all relevant    elasticities. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It is important to point out that in this study,    the domestic FCOJ price is considered to be the same as the import price, tariffs    included. This is because FCOJ is a relatively homogeneous good, which is extensively    traded in commodity markets. Hence, both the domestic and the import price are    simply the price of FCOJ in commodity markets.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"> <a href="#tab11">Table 11</a> summarizes the    results in the scenario of the complete elimination from the FCOJ market of    the per unit tax equivalent to a 56.7% <I>ad valorem </I>tax, with the estimate    of the welfare effects and the percentage changes in prices and quantities caused    by the elimination of tariffs. It is important to note that in this study, as    a means of comparison, simulations are performed by adopting four different    values for the export supply price elasticity of the imported good. In the following    table, columns A, B, C and D present the results when this elasticity is equal    to 0.5, 1, 2 and 3 respectively.<a name="tx05"></a><a href="#nt05"><sup>5</sup></a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab10.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="tab11"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab11.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a href="#tab12">Table 12</a> shows the welfare    effects and percentage changes in prices and quantities in the scenario of a    partial reduction of barriers to levels equivalent to a 30% <I>ad valorem</I>    tax. It is worth to note that the impacts of a reduction in tariffs are losses    of welfare in the local economy, except in the case of a partial reduction of    the tariff when the export supply price elasticity of the imported good is equal    to 3. The reason for this is straightforward. When the importer country has    the power to affect the world prices, the taxes imposed in the market of imported    good are partially paid by the exporter country. So, in the scenario of complete    elimination of tariffs, the government loses all its revenue, part of which    is driven to the foreign exporter country.<a name="tx06"></a><a href="#nt06"><sup>6</sup></a></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><a name="tab12"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03tab12.gif"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The final result in terms of national welfare    depends on comparing the government’s losses and the gains incorporated by consumers.    As a matter of fact, with unchanged price elasticity of total demand, the more    elastic the supply of the imported good, the smaller the government’s losses    will be and the larger the consumer surplus. There is always a critical point    in terms of the elasticity of supply of the imported good when the losses turn    into gains in terms of welfare. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>5. Conclusions</b></font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The analysis of the potential impact of trade    liberalization suggests that strong resistance to trade liberalization is bound    to arise in the US FCOJ market. Even in the scenario where trade liberalization    maintains the levels of protection currently applied to Mexican exports, the    Brazilian producers’ cost advantages would result in a sharp fall in prices    and, consequently, in domestic producers’ losses. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Moreover, tariff reduction will cause losses    of welfare in the local economy. As explained above, when the importer country    affects world prices, a tariff reduction represents a transfer of revenue from    local government to foreign producers. Thus, in this case, the more inelastic    the supply of the imported good or the greater the tariff reduction, the larger    the exporter’s welfare gain will be. </font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">It is important to point out that the results    in terms of welfare and changes in prices and quantities are very sensitive    to elasticity values. Although this could be thought of as a weakness in partial    equilibrium models, they are still a very important tool for evaluating alternative    commercial policies. The great sensitivity of these models with regard to elasticity    values also suggests that further sectoral studies that emphasize estimating    the elasticities utilized in this kind of model would be valuable. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Finally, as mentioned in the introduction to    this article, sectors in which domestic producers perceive competitive gaps    as being relatively large, and where trade barriers are currently high, are    natural candidates to show strong resistance to trade liberalization. This seems    certainly to be the case for the FCOJ market in the USA. Anticipating such resistance,    Brazilian producers have been investing in the US market, building orange juice    processing capacity to become large buyers of both domestically produced and    imported FCOJ. Foreign direct investment (FDI) is seen by Brazilian producers    as an alternative way of circumventing trade barriers and entering the US market.    FDI in this sector seems to demonstrate that Brazilian FCOJ producers do expect    strong resistance to trade liberalization from their US counterparts.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>6. Bibliography </b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Berlinski, J.(coord) (2001), <b>Sobre el Beneficio    de la Integraci&oacute;n Plena en el Mercosur</b>, Serie Red-Mercosur, Siglo    Veintiuno de Argentina Ed., Argentina. </font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000166&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p> <font size="2" face="Verdana">Bowen, H.P., Hollander, A. and Viaene, J.M.    (1998), <b>Applied International Trade Analysis</b>, Macmillan, UK.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000167&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Camargo Barros, G.S., Bacchi, M.R.P and Burnquist,    H.L. (2002), "Estima&ccedil;&atilde;o de equa&ccedil;&otilde;es de oferta de    exporta&ccedil;&atilde;o de produtos agropecu&aacute;rios para o Brasil, 1992-2000",    IPEA, Texto para Discuss&atilde;o 865, Bras&iacute;lia, Brasil,</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000168&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Francois, J.F. and Hall, H.K. (1997), "Partial    Equilibrium Modeling", in Francois, J. F. and Reinert, K.A. (eds), <b>Applied    Methods for Trade Policy Analysis - A Handbook</b>, Cambridge University Press,    UK.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000169&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p> <font size="2" face="Verdana">Helpman, E. and Krugman, P.R. (1989), <b>Trade    Policy and Market Structure</b>, the MIT Press, USA.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000170&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p> <font size="2" face="Verdana">Hufbauer, G.C. and Elliot, K.A. (1994), <b>Measuring    the Cost of Protection in the United States</b>, Institute for International    Economics, Washington, DC.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000171&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Neves, M.F. and Marino, M.K. (2002), Estudo da    Competitividade de Cadeias Integradas – Impacto das Zonas de Livre Com&eacute;rcio:    cadeia citros, nota t&eacute;cnica final.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000172&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Pozzan, M., Muraro, R. and Ueta, F.Z. (2002),    "Realidades Distintas", <b>Agroanalysis</b>: Revista de Agroneg&oacute;cios    da FVG, agosto.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000173&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Tarr, D. (1990), "A modified Cournot aggregation    condition for obtaining estimates of cross elasticities of demand", Eastern    Economic Journal, 16 (3), 257-264.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000174&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font size="2" face="Verdana">United States International Trade Commission    (1998), "Frozen concentrated orange juice from Brazil", Investigation No. 731-TA-326    (Review).</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000175&pid=S0103-2003200700040000300010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">Recebido em mar&ccedil;o de 2006 e revisto em    outubro de 2006.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><a name="nt01"></a><a href="#tx01">1</a> Tax    paid to the Citrus Department for local citric product marketing.    <br>   <a name="nt02"></a><a href="#tx02">2</a> The reaction of Florida producers may    possibly erode the competitive advantage of Brazilian supply, largely based    on low labour costs.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="nt03"></a><a href="#tx03">3</a> Moreover, in the short run, following    an increase in international prices in the American market, one can imagine    that part of Brazil’s FCOJ production to the EU markets would drift to the USA.    Therefore, the FCOJ international price in EU markets would increase as a consequence    of the supply shortage, and this would benefit Brazilian exporters.    <br>   <a name="nt04"></a><a href="#tx04">4</a> Hufbauer, G.C. and K.A. Elliot (1994).    <br>   <a name="nt05"></a><a href="#tx05">5</a> A recent IPEA's paper is devoted to    estimating the supply export functions of several Brazilian agricultural products.    However, specifically in the case of orange juice, the coefficients of the variables    for explaining export quantities (export prices, the real exchange rate, and    real Brazilian income) were not found to be statistically significant at a 10%    probability level. According to the authors, this is due to the sector’s main    characteristics: the extremely rigid market structure, where supply is organized    on the basis of formal contracts between agricultural producers and industry;    the high degree of market concentration, both on the seller’s and on the buyer’s    side; and the fact that most FCOJ exporters are also traders that deal in the    product in foreign markets. This does not mean that the supply export function    is necessarily price inelastic. On the contrary, it is reasonable to conjecture    that the model utilized by the authors does not fit that specific market, suggesting    that further studies on this topic may be useful.    <br>   <a name="nt06"></a><a href="#tx06">6</a> <a href="#grf1a">Graphs 1</a> and <a href="#grf2a">2</a>    in the appendix show the principal results in terms of welfare and changes in    prices and quantities in the scenarios of partial and complete elimination of    tariffs with two different elasticity values: 0.5 and 2.0 (cases A and D, respectively).</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="verdana"><b>7. Appendix – Results</b></font></p>     <p><a name="grf1a"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03grf1a.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="grf2a"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/resr/v45n4/a03grf2a.gif"></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Berlinski]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Sobre el Beneficio de la Integración Plena en el Mercosur: Serie Red-Mercosur]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Siglo Veintiuno de Argentina Ed.]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bowen]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Hollander]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Viaene]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Applied International Trade Analysis]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Macmillan ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Camargo Barros]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Bacchi]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.R.P]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Burnquist]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA["Estimação de equações de oferta de exportação de produtos agropecuários para o Brasil, 1992-2000"]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brasília ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[IPEA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Francois]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Hall]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA["Partial Equilibrium Modeling"]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Francois]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Reinert]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Applied Methods for Trade Policy Analysis: A Handbook]]></source>
<year></year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Helpman]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Krugman]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Trade Policy and Market Structure]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[the MIT Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Hufbauer]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Elliot]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Measuring the Cost of Protection in the United States]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Institute for International Economics]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Neves]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Marino]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Estudo da Competitividade de Cadeias Integradas - Impacto das Zonas de Livre Comércio: cadeia citros, nota técnica final]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Pozzan]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Muraro]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ueta]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.Z.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA["Realidades Distintas"]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Agroanalysis: Revista de Agronegócios da FVG]]></source>
<year>agos</year>
<month>to</month>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Tarr]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA["A modified Cournot aggregation condition for obtaining estimates of cross elasticities of demand"]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Eastern Economic Journal]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>16</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>257-264</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>United States International Trade Commission</collab>
<source><![CDATA["Frozen concentrated orange juice from Brazil": Investigation No. 731-TA-326]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
