<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0104-7183</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Horizontes Antropológicos]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Horiz. antropol.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0104-7183</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Programa de Pós-Graduação em Antropologia Social - IFCH-UFRGS]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0104-71832003000200010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-71832003000200010</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Ecotourism, environmental preservation and conflicts over natural resources<a name=vnota></a>]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Kent]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Amsterdam  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2003</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<numero>20</numero>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>203</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0104-71832003000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0104-71832003000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0104-71832003000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Ecotourism has profound social impacts through the transformations it generates in the distribution of access to natural resources. At the heart of this transformation stands the paradox of ecotourism: it exploits natural environments while at the same time depending on their preservation. As a result, ecotourism has increasingly become articulated with environmental policies, in particular the creation of protected areas. Such policies have privileged those environments that are of interest to the ecotourism industry. They have also served to restrict competing forms of resource use. Local populations in particular have seen their access to natural resources diminished. This paper explores interest conflicts between local and external user groups in an ecotourism destination in Southern Bahia. Its focus is on strategies through which external groups related to ecotourism and environmental preservation have sought to appropriate control over natural resources.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[O ecoturismo tem implicações sociais de longo alcance devido às transformações que ele gera na distribuição do acesso a recursos naturais. O paradoxo do ecoturismo está no cerne dessas transformações: ao mesmo tempo em que o ecoturismo explora habitats naturais, ele depende da preservação destes. Conseqüentemente, cada vez mais o ecoturismo se associa a políticas ambientais, especialmente aquelas que dizem respeito à criação de reservas naturais. Tais políticas têm privilegiado os habitats que interessam à indústria de ecoturismo e têm restringido outras formas de se fazer uso daqueles recursos naturais. Quem tem cada vez menos acesso, em particular, a esses recursos são as populações nativas. O presente artigo examina os conflitos de interesse entre grupos locais e exteriores de usuários em uma região de ecoturismo no Sul da Bahia. O foco do artigo está nas estratégias relativas ao ecoturismo e à preservação ambiental, acionadas por não-nativos, para ganhar controle sobre recursos naturais.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[ecotourism]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[environmental policy]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[natural resources]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[social conflicts]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[conflitos sociais]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[ecoturismo]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[políticas ambientais]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[recursos naturais]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>ARTIGOS</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="4">Ecotourism, environmental preservation and    conflicts over natural resources<a name="vnota"></a><a href="#nota"><sup>*</sup></a></font>    </b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="2">Michael Kent</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">University of Amsterdam &#150; the Netherlands</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>ABSTRACT</b> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Ecotourism has profound social impacts through    the transformations it generates in the distribution of access to natural resources.    At the heart of this transformation stands the paradox of ecotourism: it exploits    natural environments while at the same time depending on their preservation.    As a result, ecotourism has increasingly become articulated with environmental    policies, in particular the creation of protected areas. Such policies have    privileged those environments that are of interest to the ecotourism industry.    They have also served to restrict competing forms of resource use. Local populations    in particular have seen their access to natural resources diminished. This paper    explores interest conflicts between local and external user groups in an ecotourism    destination in Southern Bahia. Its focus is on strategies through which external    groups related to ecotourism and environmental preservation have sought to appropriate    control over natural resources.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Keywords:</b> ecotourism, environmental policy,    natural resources, social conflicts.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>RESUMO</b> </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">O ecoturismo tem implica&ccedil;&otilde;es sociais    de longo alcance devido &agrave;s transforma&ccedil;&otilde;es que ele gera    na distribui&ccedil;&atilde;o do acesso a recursos naturais. O paradoxo do ecoturismo    est&aacute; no cerne dessas transforma&ccedil;&otilde;es: ao mesmo tempo em    que o ecoturismo explora <I>habitats</I> naturais, ele depende da preserva&ccedil;&atilde;o    destes. Conseq&uuml;entemente, cada vez mais o ecoturismo se associa a pol&iacute;ticas    ambientais, especialmente aquelas que dizem respeito &agrave; cria&ccedil;&atilde;o    de reservas naturais. Tais pol&iacute;ticas t&ecirc;m privilegiado os <I>habitats</I>    que interessam &agrave; ind&uacute;stria de ecoturismo e t&ecirc;m restringido    outras formas de se fazer uso daqueles recursos naturais. Quem tem cada vez    menos acesso, em particular, a esses recursos s&atilde;o as popula&ccedil;&otilde;es    nativas. O presente artigo examina os conflitos de interesse entre grupos locais    e exteriores de usu&aacute;rios em uma regi&atilde;o de ecoturismo no Sul da    Bahia. O foco do artigo est&aacute; nas estrat&eacute;gias relativas ao ecoturismo    e &agrave; preserva&ccedil;&atilde;o ambiental, acionadas por n&atilde;o-nativos,    para ganhar controle sobre recursos naturais.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><B>Palavras-chave:</b> conflitos sociais, ecoturismo,    pol&iacute;ticas ambientais, recursos naturais.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">September 1998. A large and noisy crowd filled    the Municipal Council of Canoas<a name="1n"></a><a href="#n1"><sup>1</sup></a>,    Bahia. Reason for this excitement was that the Municipal Council had summoned    Onda Verde, an environmental NGO. The members of Onda Verde consisted of tourism    entrepreneurs, academics and other liberal professionals that had migrated in    preceding years to Canoas from Sao Paulo, Salvador and other cities. They were    summoned by the Municipal Council to give explanations about a proposed environmental    education programme. This project was part of the Government of Bahia’s strategy    to establish Canoas as a leading ecotourism destination. This strategy had already    resulted in the construction of an asphalt road and the creation of an <I>&Aacute;rea    de Prote&ccedil;&atilde;o Ambiental</I><a name="2n"></a><a href="#n2"><sup>2</sup></a>(APA),    a conservation unit of direct resource use.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Largely represented during the session of the    Municipal Council was the population of the Miranda, an illegal settlement at    the entrance of Canoas, on a hill overlooking the town and ocean. The Miranda    was referred to by people in Canoas as a <I>favela</I><a name="3n"></a><a href="#n3"><sup>3</sup></a>.    Its residents were engaged in a conflict with Onda Verde, whose members lobbied    for its removal, considering the settlement a danger to the environment. Onda    Verde was supported by the tourism sector, fearing for Canoas’ image as an <I>ecological    paradise</I>. The Governor of Bahia had also summoned Canoas’ mayor to move    the settlement elsewhere.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">During this session, the members of Onda Verde    were severely questioned. The Municipal Council demanded more transparency and    local participation in the elaboration of the environmental education programme.    Various councillors and other speakers that took the floor also criticised the    Onda Verde’s attitude towards the local population, which they defined as <I>ill-intentioned</I>    or <I>authoritarian</I>. A resolution was even proposed &#150; and rejected    &#150; to declare its leader <I>persona non grata</I>. Furthermore, councillors    affiliated with the mayor held discourses in favour of the occupation of the    Miranda. People involved in the conflict around the Miranda interpreted this    as a green light to pursue the appropriation of land. The same day, a multitude    invaded the contested area, cut the remaining vegetation and demarcated plots.    By the end of the week, the size of the settlement had tripled. Members of Onda    Verde claim that this was a well-orchestrated move by Canoas’ mayor in order    to break the intervention power of the environmental movement and to settle    his debt with people whose vote he had received in exchange for the promise    of land.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="3">Ecotourism</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">This event forms a powerful illustration of the    entwinements between environmental policies, conflicts over access to land and    local&#150;external antagonisms in the context of ecotourism development. At    the heart of the matter stands the paradox of ecotourism: it claims to support    the preservation of natural environments in the very act of transforming them.    Changes do not occur only through direct impacts of tourism development. They    also take place more subtly, through socio-political and economic transformations    that profoundly alter the balance of power, in particular regarding the access    to natural resources.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Ecotourism functions as a clear catalyst of change,    in the sense that it incorporates new environments into market economies. It    entails a commodification and symbolic reshaping of a variety of natural characteristics,    in order to extract use or exchange value from them. In the process, the quality    of environments can deteriorate through the construction of tourism infrastructure    and over-exploitation of attractions. Still, ecotourism has the pretension of    contributing to the preservation of <I>pristine landscapes </I>or<I> fragile    ecosystems</I>, in other words to secureenvironmental continuity. Moreover,    the auto-definition and marketing strategy of the ecotourism sector evolves    precisely around this pretension. Simultaneously, it is also a basic necessity    of ecotourism that the environments it exploits remain unchanged, in order to    preserve the direct resource base on which it depends and to secure long term    profitability of investments. As a result of this paradox, ecotourism has often    come hand in hand with new environmental legislation, the establishment of protected    areas or the regulation of access to natural resources through environmental    management plans. Such interventions are aimed at mitigating the environmental    impacts of tourism. However, in practice they also serve to restrict competing    forms of natural resource use that might deteriorate them. These consequences    of ecotourism’s paradox are the subject of this paper.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Ecotourism has received many advocates within    the social sciences (Boo, 1990; Eppler-Wood, 1991; Honey, 1999; Khan, 1997;    Place, 1991). It has become an economic justification for the preservation of    the natural environment (Mowforth; Munt, 1998, p. 168). There is evidence that    tourism is one of the most effective strategies to convert use and non-use values    of protected areas into concrete economic benefits (Dharmaratne; Sang; Walling,    2000). In the social sciences, "now the tendency seems to be to applaud tourism    as a panacea for achieving a wide array of social, economic and environmental    goals" (Stronza; 2001, p. 274). Still, as the scene in the Municipal Council    illustrates, not all is sunshine in ecotourism paradise. At best, ecotourism    is a double edged sword.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">One reason for this blind spot in ecotourism    literature is that it is "filled with guidelines and ‘best practices’ for achieving    success &#91;...&#93; The ideas are generally prescriptive" (Stronza, 2001, p.    275). Although such an approach may be useful in guiding policy making, it is    only of limited analytic value, as it does not allow for a processual perspective    to be developed (Galani-Moutafi, 2001, p. 808). Also, much tourism analysis    has played down relationships of power, which remain implicit or are absent    (Mowforth; Munt, 1998, p. 38, 85-90). However, power is present everywhere in    tourism (Cheong; Miller, 2000, p. 372). Ecotourism evolves in a context of great    inequality of wealth and power (Rao apud Mowforth; Munt, 1998, p. 38). Its costs    and benefits are also distributed unevenly between the various social groups    involved. Therefore relationships of power must lie at the heart of the inquiry.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The objective of this paper is to explore interest    conflicts between local and external user groups evolving around the development    of ecotourism and the use of the natural environment. The town of Canoas has    been chosen as a case study for a variety of reasons. It is increasingly establishing    its reputation as an ecotourism destination; it is subject to environmental    regulation through its incorporation in an APA; it has a strong external ecotourism    sector and an active environmental movement; and serious conflicts have emerged    between local and external interest groups over the use of the natural environment.    Fieldwork took place from April to August of 1999. Participant observation,    semi-structured interviews &#150; individual and collective &#150; and the analysis    of documents have been the principal methods of data collection. First, Canoas    and its social context will be briefly introduced.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="3">Ethnographic context</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Canoas is a small town with approximately seven    thousand inhabitants, on the southern coast of Bahia, Brazil. It is the capital    of the district with the same name. Until recently, Canoas’ economy was fully    depending on the cocoa industry. Land use in the region of Canoas, however,    has become subject to an intense process of transformation (SCT, 1996a, p 100).    Since the end of the 1980’s, the cultivation of cocoa has largely become abandoned    due to the fall of prices on the world market and a disease that decimated the    plantations in all southern Bahia. The economic consequences were devastating,    causing large-scale unemployment (SCT, 1996a, p. 118). The ecological impact    has also been profound. Other forms of land usage took the place of cocoa, such    as cattle-breeding and commercial wood extraction, leading to large scale deforestation.    In 1990, 91% of VAT collection in the municipality of Canoas was related to    wood extraction (SCT, 1996a, p. 107). Unemployed former workers of the cocoa    industry massively resorted to subsistence agriculture on illegaly occupied    land, in particular the production of manioc. Slash and burn became a common    practice, adding to environmental destruction. Migration to the urban zone of    Canoas and to Salvador &#150; Bahia’s capital &#150; was also a common response    to the crisis. In the urban zone, public service and fishing remained the only    significant sources of employment.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font size="2" face="Verdana">In response, since 1991 the Government of Bahia    has promoted ecotourism as a solution to economic and environmental problems.    In 1993 it decreed Canoas and its surroundings a State &Aacute;rea de Prote&ccedil;&atilde;oAmbiental    (APA). In all South America, the creation of protected areas has been a central    part of the response to environmental destruction (Painter, 1995, p. 15). The    APA of Canoas embraces thirty kilometres of coast, with a total surface of 149    km<sup>2</sup>. APA is a unit of conservation that permits the continued direct    use of natural resources. Its aim is to reconcile environmental preservation    with economic development. For this purpose, a management is established that    divides the APA into various zones. For each zone specific uses are defined.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">According to a former administrator of the APA    of Canoas, its creation was required as a mitigating measure by the Inter-American    Development Bank (IADB) for financing the asphaltisation of the access road    to Canoas. The management plan of the APA was ratified as municipal law by the    local government of Canoas in 1997. There is evidence to argue that this APA    was created for the purpose of tourism. Simultaneously with its creation, the    Government of Bahia’s Office of Culture and Tourism launched a tourism programme    for the APA with the objective to achieve a capacity of ten thousand beds (CODETUR,    &#91;s.d.&#93;, p. 11.2). As stated in the APA’s management plan, the government’s    priority motive for its creation was <I>the development of low-density tourism    projects</I> (SCT, 1996b, p. 80). Furthermore, the administration of the APA    and the implementation of its environmental regulations were initially assigned    to the Office of Culture and Tourism (SCT, 1996a, p. 94). Only in 1999, responsibility    was transferred to the Centre for Environmental Resources in Rio Claro, the    main town in the region. At the time of fieldwork, this Centre was being restructured    and in practice had not yet factually assumed responsibility. Another actor    of major importance in Rio Claro has been the IBAMA &#150; the Brazilian Institute    for the Environment, the country’s main environmental authority &#150; which    has acted upon denunciations of environmental infringements within the APA.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The most important public investment has been    the construction of an asphalt road, connecting Canoas to Rio Claro. Inaugurated    in 1998, the costs of 16 million US$ were provided by the IADB. One of the IADB’s    conditions was that an Environmental Education Programme (EEP) would be executed,    to mitigate the road’s negative effects on the environment. This programme started    in February of 1999. It is beyond the scope of this paper to explore the processes    leading to the various interventions described above. This brief introduction    will suffice as a background for understanding conflicts occurring at the time    of fieldwork.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The 1990’s have witnessed a rapid expansion of    the tourism industry in Canoas and its surroundings. This expansion has resulted    in the establishment of a new, and relatively affluent, community of immigrant    tourism entrepreneurs and liberal professionals, originating mostly from the    large urban centra of Brazil and from Europe. Most owners of tourism businesses    in Canoas &#150; in particular of the more upper-scale ones &#150; are part    of this migrant community. As a result, a disproportionate share of direct benefits    derived from tourism flow to non-locals. The bulk of the local population are    left with unskilled and badly paid jobs. Most of these jobs, furthermore, are    only seasonal or episodical. However, given the high level of unemployment many    locals still perceived this situation as favourable.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="3">Environmental movement</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Approximately ten members of the migrant community    are involved in environmental activism. With few exceptions, they have recently    migrated from Brazil’s large urban centra, have an academic degree and are between    30 and 50 years in age. Half are tourism entrepreneurs, the others hold liberal    professions, such as architect or lawyer. Canoas’ environmental movement consists    of two platforms, an NGO called<I> Onda Verde</I>, and the executing team of    the Environmental Education Programme (EEP). No local people are represented    in these platforms.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Onda Verde was created in 1987 by local people    from the town of Canoas, to take care of a shoal of dolphins that had washed    ashore. After the group had become non-active due to internal problems a few    years later, its administration was taken over in 1996 by several recent immigrants.    Since then, Onda Verde has known a very active period. Its most significant    accomplishment came in 1996, when it prevented through juridical action the    parcelling and inhabitation of the land adjacent to one of Canoas’ urban beaches.    Onda Verde initially opposed the construction of the asphalt road. Soon, however,    it traded its resistance for an advisory function during the road’s construction    process. Another of the group’s spearheads is the relocation of the Miranda    settlement. In 1997, the status of Onda Verde was changed from <I>Movement of    Ecological Resistance</I> to <I>Environmental Institute</I>, making it possible    to undertake remunerated projects. It entered a partnership with the major environmental    NGO in Rio Claro, in its turn affiliated to the US-based Conservation International    and supported by the Ford Foundation. The actions of Onda Verde have lead to    conflicts with the local population and their leaders. Onda Verde suffered a    significant blow when it was publicly discredited during the already described    session of the Municipal Council. Its activities have remained suspended since    then.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">After this setback, Oscar &#150; the key figure    of Onda Verde &#150; concentrated on acquiring the execution of the EEP. When    the Government of Bahia allocated the project to Onda Verde’s partner NGO in    Rio Claro, these contracted Oscar as co-ordinator. The three other remunerated    members of the project also consisted of immigrants. The entire staff were members    of Onda Verde, three out of four were also owners of tourism facilities. Some    locals of Canoas became involved in the project, but they all worked as volunteers.    Remunerated activities were without exception sub-contracted to other members    of the migrant community.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The main component of the EEP is environmental    education, with the local population of Canoas as the formal target group. Activities    include the organisation of informative meetings, as well as the production    of written and audio-visual informative material. A second component focuses    on ecotourism. Its objective is to make an inventory of potential ecotourism    attractions and to develop a limited number of these. The EEP is another example    of how tourism and environmental preservation measures have become entwined    in the case of Canoas.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The environmental movement may be small numerically,    but it receives considerable support from a number of immigrant tourism entrepreneurs.    Both groups seem united in their project to establish ecotourism as the dominant    economic activity in the region, and to restrict other forms of land use. The    power base of the migrant tourism sector resides mainly in its economic capital    and employment generating capacity. The largest tourism business in Canoas,    Praias de S&atilde;o Jorge, employs an estimated 120 people, making it the second    largest employer of the district, behind the municipality. An important difference    between the two is that Praias de S&atilde;o Jorge paid its employees on time,    while the municipality at times lagged more than a year behind in payment. Partly    sharing the same power base, this makes the tourism sector a serious threat    to the local political elite.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The environmental movement is also vested with    power in other ways than its alliance with the affluent ecotourism sector. It    is backed by formal interventions, such as the establishment of the APA and    its regulation; measures of IBAMA against violators of this regulation; the    attribution of the EEP; and pressure of the governor of Bahia for the displacement    of the Miranda settlement.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Also, its members have more efficient external    networks and access to higher levels of decision making than the local population    have. An example is Onda Verde’s partnership with the NGO in Rio Claro, which    makes it part of Conservation International’s global network. According to the    APA’s former administrator, the management plan of the APA and the terms of    reference of the EEP have been established in close consultation with Onda Verde    and the NGO in Rio Claro. This enabled Onda Verde to incorporate its agenda    in these interventions. Examples are the definition of the already urbanised    part of the Miranda as an area to be reforested and the addition of an ecotourism    component to the EEP, which was not part of the original terms of reference.    Through its external networks, Onda Verde also succeeded in appropriating the    execution of the EEP without prior public tender. The strong contacts of one    member of Onda Verde with regional and national media has helped to mobilise    public opinion outside Canoas for its main causes. These outside networks have    enabled Onda Verde to influence the course of local events, for example by impeding    the aforementioned development of a tourist project on an urban beach and by    altering the planned course of the asphalt road to Canoas.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Finally, environmentalism is mainly professed    in Canoas by actors with a greater economic and cultural capital. There is a    relation of mutual benefit between environmentalism and its advocates. The latter’s    capital, on the one hand, enhances the status of the environmentalist ideal.    On the other hand, adhering to environmentalism has proven to be an effective    strategy to gain access to funds, in particular for the development of socio-environmental    projects. It also increases cultural capital, by creating a social distinction    between adherents and non-adherents. This distinction is hierarchically structured    as it implies the necessity of transmitting the environmentalist ideal upon    non-adherents.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In sum, a new power group is currently establishing    itself in Canoas, consisting mostly of recent immigrants engaged in tourism    and environmentalism. More and more of Canoas’ physical, social and political    space is now being claimed and occupied by this new group. In particular, it    has succeeded in appropriating control over the use of natural resources. Unsurprisingly,    this has resulted in resource conflicts with the local population. These will    be discussed in the following paragraph.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="3" face="Verdana"><b>Resource conflicts</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Some changes have taken place in the urban zone    of Canoas. As often happens in tourism destinations, the centre and seaside    are increasingly being occupied by immigrants. They buy houses from locals,    usually in order to convert them into tourism facilities.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">User conflicts have centred around the Miranda    settlement. In 1992, the municipality of Canoas bought 10 hectares for urbanisation,    in order to cope with increased migration. The land was deforested by the municipality,    in spite of fines from IBAMA. Little by little, settlers moved in. A few years    later, however, the then mayor took juridical steps for the eviction of all    settlers. The eviction was sentenced by court, but only after the 1996 elections,    which saw the election of the same mayor that had initially bought the land.    He withdrew the demand. By that time, the settlement consisted of approximately    100 dwellings, sheltering an estimated 500 people. After the session of the    Municipal Council described at the start of this paper, the size of the settlement    tripled to over 300 dwellings. This means it represents approximately 20% of    the total urban population.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Environmentalists and tourism entrepreneurs struggle    to have the settlement displaced. Their principal argument is that the settlement    &#150; right at the entrance of town &#150; is disastrous for Canoas’ image    as an ecotourism destination. Onda Verde successfully lobbied to have the area    designed as an <I>Agro-Florestal Zone</I> in the APA’s management plan, with    the creation of a<I> Horto Florestal </I>&#150; a forest garden &#150; as specific    use. This legally prohibits its urbanisation. The adjacent area was designed    a <I>Zone of Permanent Preservation</I>. Based on this categorisation, Canoas’    environmentalists have consistently denounced the residents with IBAMA for environmental    infringements, in particular the cutting of trees within the Zone of Permanent    Preservation and the pollution of the river flowing by the Miranda. Other interests    are also at stake. Onda Verde has proposed a project for the conversion of the    area into a Horto Florestal. If the settlers were evicted and the management    of the APA would approve this project, it would mean an important financial    boost for Onda Verde. A significant detail is that Roberto &#150; key figure    of Canoas’ environmental movement &#150; owns a pousada<a name="4n"></a><a href="#n4"><sup>4</sup></a>    on top of the hill overlooking the Miranda. If the area were reforested, this    would significantly increase the value of his pousada.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A plan was elaborated by URBIS &#150; an entity    specialised in urbanisation plans &#150; to displace the settlers to an area    three kilometres outside Canoas. However, the mayor shows no intention to impose    the plan. The alternative location is also rejected by the settlers. According    to Milton, president of the Residents’ Association of the Miranda settlement,    it is too far away from Canoas. Most residents are depending on Canoas for employment    and schooling. Another argument is of an ecological nature. The alternative    is located close to the main source supplying Canoas with potable water, making    its inhabitation a considerable environmental hazard.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Miranda case suggests that what is at stake    is not to maximise the outcome of preservation efforts, but to preserve those    areas which are of major tourism interest. Standing at the entrance of Canoas,    the Miranda is part of the direct resource base of ecotourism. As expressed    by Milton, <I>it is all about hiding the poor from the eyes of the tourist</I>.    This case also exemplifies how environmental laws are strategically activated    in the regulation of other than environmental conflicts. In Brazil, other cases    have been documented in which environmental laws were used to settle conflicts    around land (Menezes, 2002) and favelas (Fuks, 2001).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">It is, however, in the rural zone that the most    significant transformations have taken place, leading to conflicts between the    migrant community and the local population. There are multiple interests regarding    the natural environment of Canoas, its use and its preservation. The conflict    centres around the question who has the right to claim, occupy and exploit physical    spaces of strategic interest.</font></p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana">The natural environment has become Canoas’ principal    economical asset. It serves as a resources base for the region’s most important    economic strategies: ecotourism, subsistence agriculture, cocoa cultivation,    wood extraction and environmentalism. As a consequence, whoever controls the    use of Canoas’ natural environment holds a highly strategic position. The cocoa    boom first resulted in a pattern of land concentration. Canoas’ tourism potential    has served as an even stronger incentive for land appropriation and speculation,    in particular in the coastal zone. The land adjacent to Canoas came to belong    to a sole owner (SCT, 1996a, p. 100). With the increase in tourism, this pattern    has given way to the parcelling of territories into small lots. While a decade    earlier estates in the coastal zone measured between 100 and 1000 hectares,    by 1996 the average size in the southern part of the APA was of 200 m<sup>2</sup>(SCT,    1996b, p. 19). Almost all land between the road and the coast of the APA had    been acquired by external actors (SCT, 1996b, p. 15). Local smallholders have    remained invariably without land titles to their plots.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Inequalities in access to natural resources have    increased with the creation of the APA. The resource uses prioritised by its    management plan are environmental preservation and tourism. The categories of    <I>Preservation</I> and <I>Conservation</I> account for 65,7% of the territory.    12,7% of the APA is reserved for the development of tourism infrastructure.    The <I>Agriculture Zone</I> is limited to 11,7% percent of the APA (SCT, 1998,    p. 15). The latter consists mostly of already deforested land, with considerable    space occupied by cattle-herding. Forms of land use permitted in this zone are    forestry, reforestation, cattle-herding, apiculture, fish farming and "subsistence    agriculture through techniques appropriate to tropical environments" (SCT, 1998,    p. 19). Current practices of subsistence agriculture, in particular slash and    burn techniques, are not compatible with these regulations. They have been strictly    curtailed. The establishment of protected areas often entails an abrupt change    in local rural economies previously based on exploitation of various natural    resources (Place, 1991, p. 187). The implementation of the APA of Canoas has    significantly restricted the rural population’s access to natural resources.    In particular subsistence agriculturists have been affected.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Interventions by IBAMA are the main vehicle through    which restrictions in resource use are imposed. IBAMA only acts upon denunciations.    Roberto, key figure in Canoas’ environmental movement, admits that the lion’s    share of denunciations to IBAMA of environmental infringements in the APA of    Canoas stem from him and his colleagues. This share rises in the case of denunciations    against residents of the Miranda. A common practice is to report by mobile phone    the burning or clearing of rainforest observed while driving on the road to    Rio Claro. The majority of the written denunciations by Onda Verde that I was    permitted to consult, are directed against the cutting of trees in the rural    zone by subsistence agriculturists. These denunciations are generally backed    up by references to environmental laws, rhetorically placing the infringements    in the criminal sphere by the use of expressions such as "criminal acts" or    "criminal deforestation".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Various rural leaderships affirm that IBAMA has    succeeded in curtailing slash and burn practices within the APA through rigid    control and intervention. As these practices are crucial in the rural subsistence    economy, this has had profound consequences. "The land is weak and becomes exhausted    after a few years. When this happens, you have no other choice but to clear    new land. IBAMA prohibits this, so many people move to town because they can    not survive anymore on their own land", says Evanilson, president of the Association    of Rural Workers. He also mentions cases where IBAMA intervened after the felling    of only one tree. One subsistence agriculturist was fined over 10.000 Reais<a name="5n"></a><a href="#n5"><sup>5</sup></a>    after felling a tree on his land for the construction of a chicken fence. According    to Milton, the majority of Miranda residents consists of former subsistence    agriculturists that were not able to adjust their life strategies to the APA’s    regulations. This implies a mere relocation of environmental problems and the    creation of new social problems. The concentration of coastal land in external    hands has also curtailed local access to crucial resources. Artisan fishing    was a common practice among the rural population to complement their diet. However,    many new owners of coastal estates have prohibited access to their land in an    attempt to privatise beaches. Many rural families have remained without the    possibility to fish.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The struggle for control over natural resources    has also led to interest conflicts between federal institutions. In particular    IBAMA and the INCRA &#150; the national institute for agrarian reform &#150;    have clashed. There are three settlements of INCRA within the APA of Canoas.    The settlement of Samaipata, located near the road and consisting of 32 families,    has received 810 hectares from INCRA. Of the area expropriated by INCRA, 80%    was destined for cultivation. The remaining 20% was defined as a reserve. According    to Olivia &#150; spokeswoman of the settlement &#150; IBAMA consistently intervenes    when residents of Samaipata try to convert part of the cultivation area to agriculture.    As a result, the residents are at a deadlock.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Local people complain about the absence of viable    alternatives. Environmentalists promote the cultivation of a variety of fruits    as a suitable alternative to current agricultural practices. This alternative,    however, is reject by rural leaderships as not viable. It would require a starting    investment for which most subsistence agriculturists lack the means. Also, these    fruits would only start yielding sufficient returns after six years. No financial    means are available to bridge this period. The current crops &#150; manioc,    potato, means and rice &#150; have a much shorter production cycle, ranging    between two and twelve months. At the time of research, ecotourism was not an    alternative either for the rural populations, as their participation in tourism    was negligible.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Another recurring argument of the rural population    is that they are not responsible for most environmental degradation. They claim    that the lion’s share of deforestation has been perpetrated by the sawmill of    a company from the state of Espirito Santo, by middle- and large-scale landowners    converting their territory into pasture land, and because of the growing demand    for wood from part of the expanding tourism industry. According to Olivia, "it    is mostly small-scale deforestation close to the road that the IBAMA and Onda    Verde deal with, more extensive deforestation is neither punished nor discussed".    She claims that at night trucks loaded with wood pass the settlement, coming    from the interior of the APA. Such practices are also reported by informants    living in other parts of the APA. People of Samaipata have repeatedly denounced    these practices with IBAMA. However, IBAMA has not reacted once.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Part of the explanation for this bias is that    IBAMA of Rio Claro only operates during office hours and therefore has no capacity    to deal with infringements perpetrated at night. However, it also strongly illustrates    the strategic alliance between IBAMA and Canoas’ environmental movement. This    alliance is clearly perceived by the population of Canoas. According to Olivia,    "Onda Verde wants to impose its law upon us by denouncing us to IBAMA". The    bias also illustrates the prioritisation of environments that are located within    reach of the tourist’s gaze.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The data presented so far suggest that environmental    preservation is a selective process. Furthermore, environmental education concentrates    on the urban zone of Canoas, in spite that the project’s staff consider environmental    degradation much more serious in the rural zone. And though the local population    are defined as target group of the EEP, much of the project’s output seems directed    at tourists, for example folders, videos and audio tapes with Canoas’ attractions    and bumper stickers. According to its co-ordinator Roberto, the formal goal    of the ecotourism component of the EEP is "to convince inhabitants of the rural    zone that ecotourism is an economically more beneficial form of land use than    cutting trees or cultivating manioc". In practice, however, its focus is entirely    on existing tourism structures and large-scale entrepreneurs with investment    capacity. Efforts concentrate on the coast and the access road. It seems no    coincidence that these are also the most important spaces for the tourism industry.    Roberto even claims that "in truth, environmental education is only the means    to accomplish our objective: the development of ecotourism".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">What constitute critical natural resources at    a particular time and place is socially determined (Painter, 1995, p. 7). Environmental    preservation is embedded in specific practices, that suggest that some environments    are more deserving of being preserved than others. In the case of Canoas, these    privileged environments coincide with those that are of strategic interest to    the ecotourism industry. The most important stretches of rainforest within the    district of Canoas are located on its western borders, at a considerable distance    from town and coast. Significantly, they have been left <I>outside</I> of the    APA and therefore are not protected (SCT, 1996b, p. 16).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The migrant community claim that ecotourism is    the economic activity which offers most benefits to Canoas’ natural environment.    Simultaneously, they attribute the responsibility for environmental degradation    to the local population, in particular subsistence agriculturists. In the name    of environmental necessity, this dual argument enables the ecotourism industry    to claim access to natural resources and to curtail local competition in the    use of these resources. This is not uncommon. There is a tendency among environmental    organisations and policy makers to regard local populations as the main threat    to the natural environment (Monbiot apud Mowforth; Munt, 1998, p. 264; Troost,    1995). "As a consequence of their vulnerability and lack of power, smallholder    producers often have received a disproportionate share of the blame for environmental    decline" (Stonich, 1998, p. 29). Impoverishment is certainly an important cause    of environmental degradation. The urgency for survival leaves poor people with    no other option than over-exploiting natural resources (Painter, 1995, p. 8-9).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">However, political ecological research shows    that the bulk of environmental degradation is the result of practices by wealthy    individual or corporate interests, using natural resources for the purpose of    capital accumulation (Painter, 1995; Stonich, 1998, p. 29). Their easy and renewed    access to natural resources fails to provide an incentive for using them in    a sustainable manner. Both processes are interrelated. The same policies and    practices that increase the access of powerful players, contribute to the marginalisation    and resulting impoverishment of smallholders. Therefore, "the crucial issue    underlying environmental destruction in Latin America is gross inequity in access    to resources" (Painter, 1995, p. 9). In Latin America, the way in which social    inequities are institutionalised guarantees the unequal distribution of control    over natural resources (Durham, 1995, p. 252).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Not only environmentally degrading practices    are intimately related to questions of power, but also the attribution of responsibility    for them. Power grants stakeholders access to valuable resources and enables    them to divert responsibility for the deterioration of these resources to less    powerful stakeholders. The ways in which the attribution of responsibility for    environmental problems is used politically, becomes important in the definition    of solutions. In the case of Canoas it has generated policies and actions, that    partly result in a diminished competition from small stakeholders in the access    to natural resources.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The APA as a conservation model is intended to    reconcile local economic interests with environmental preservation. In practice,    however, the APA of Canoas has substantially restricted the opportunities of    local people to pursue their economic survival strategies, granting them little    more than a marginal role within the ecotourism framework. Ecotourism is presented    to the population of Canoas as a development strategy that will resolve all    economic problems. The question, however, is whether tourism can be a viable    livelihood alternative in a context in which the most fundamental social problems    continue unresolved. The unequal distribution of power not only restricts the    local population’s access to natural resources. It also reduces their opportunities    to substantially benefit from tourism.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="3">Concluding remarks</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The implementation of preservation policies and    the rapid pace of tourism development have resulted in the emergence of new,    external power groups in Canoas. Gradually, power is shifting away from local    to external hands. This results in conflicts over the access to valuable resources.    Ecotourism exploits environments while at the same time depending on their preservation.    This paradox leads to the restriction of competing forms of natural resource    use, in the case of Canoas through the implementation of environmental regulation.    A crucial question for understanding environmental policies and their consequences    is: what is being preserved, by whom and for whom (Mowforth; Munt, 1998, p.    12)? In the APA of Canoas, the environments receiving priority are those that    form part of ecotourism’s direct resource base: the town, the coast and the    access road. The driving force behind environmental preservation comes from    the environmental movement, the ecotourism industry and government agencies.    All these are external actors. Interventions have also mostly benefited external    groups, in particular the ecotourism industry and the environmental movement,    through an increase of control over natural resources. Local people, on the    contrary, have had their access to natural resources restricted. It is by no    means the intention to depict the local population as passive victims of events.    Though considerable, the power of Canoas´ environmental movement and ecotourism    sector has its limitations. For example, it has not been sufficient to have    the settlers of the Miranda evicted. Also, the migrant community does not have    the least influence upon the decisions of local political organs. The resistance    strategies of the local population and their leadership, however, are beyond    the scope of this paper.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Ecotourism has profound social impacts through    the transformation it generates in the distribution of access to and control    over natural resources. World wide, the ecotourism industry makes new and increasingly    powerful claims on local natural resources. Such claims are secured through    public environmental policies, the most visible of which are the creation of    protected areas. The establishment of such areas is legitimised by the necessity    for environmental preservation. However, as the case of Canoas shows, the logic    behind them is just as much to extract economic value from them through tourism    development. Such interventions regulate and redistribute access to natural    resources. The various social groups involved have unequal influence on the    political level where such interventions are decided upon. Some are favoured,    such as the ecotourism industry and environmental groups in the case of Canoas.    Others are disadvantaged, in particular local populations depending on natural    resources for their life strategies. This can lead to over-exploitation of remaining    resources or displacement of environmental degradation through migration. As    the establishment of protected areas increases inequalities in the access to    natural resources, an important question to be further explored, is whether    such policy does not indirectly contribute to a net increase or mere displacement    of environmental degradation.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana" size="3">References</font></b></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">BOO, E. <I>Ecotourism: the potentials and pitfalls,    v. 1</I>. Washington DC: World Wildlife Fund, 1990</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000076&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">CHEONG, S-M.; MILLER, M. L. Power and tourism:    a Foucauldian perspective. <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>, v. 27, p. 371-390,    2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000077&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">CODETUR. <I>Programa de desenvolvimento tur&iacute;stico    da Bahia</I>: oportunidades de investimento. Salvador: Governo do Estado da    Bahia, &#91;s.d.&#93;.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000078&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">DHARMARATNE, S. G.; SANG, F. Y.; WALLING, L.    J. Tourism potentials for financing protected areas. <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>,    v. 27, p. 590-610, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000079&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">DURHAM, W. Political ecology and environmental    destruction in Latin America. In: PAINTER, M.; DURHAM, W. (Ed.). <I>The social    causes of environmental destruction in Latin America</I>. Ann Arbor: University    of Michigan Press, 1995</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000080&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">EPPLER-WOOD, M. Global solutions: an ecotourism    society. In: WHELAN, T. (Ed.). <I>Nature tourism</I>. Washington DC: Island    Press, 1991.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000081&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">FUKS, M. <I>Conflitos ambientais no Rio de Janeiro:    </I>a&ccedil;&atilde;o e debate nas arenas p&uacute;blicas. Rio de Janeiro:    Editora UFRJ, 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000082&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">GALANI-MOUTAFI, V. A critical analysis of subjectivity.    <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>, v. 28, p. 808, 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000083&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">HONEY, M. <I>Ecotourism and sustainable development</I>:    who owns paradise? Washington DC: Island Press, 1999.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000084&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">KHAN, M. M. Tourism development and dependency    theory: mass tourism vs. ecotourism. <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>, v. 24,    p. 988-991, 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000085&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MENEZES, T. H. <I>Uso da den&uacute;ncia de crime    ambiental em assentamentos rurais na Mata Sul pernambucana</I> &#91;Conference    paper&#93;. In: REUNI&Atilde;O DA ASSOCIA&Ccedil;&Atilde;O BRASILEIRA DE ANTROPOLOGIA,    23., 2002, Gramado. 2002.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000086&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MOWFORTH, M.; MUNT, I. <I>Tourism and sustainability</I>:    new tourism in the third world. London: Routledge, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000087&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">PAINTER, M. Introduction: anthropological perspectives    on environmental destruction. In: PAINTER, M.; DURHAM, W. (Ed.). <I>The social    causes of environmental destruction in Latin America</I>. Ann Arbor: University    of Michigan Press, 1995.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000088&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">PLACE, S. E. Nature tourism and rural development    in Tortuguero. <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>, v. 18, p. 186-201, 1991.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000089&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">SCT (Secretaria de Cultura e Turismo &#150; Governo    do Estado da Bahia). <I>Plano de manejo</I>: &aacute;rea de prote&ccedil;&atilde;o    ambiental do litoral de XXX: volume I: diagn&oacute;stico do meio f&iacute;sico,    bi&oacute;tico e socio-econ&ocirc;mico. Salvador, 1996a.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000090&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">SCT. <I>Plano de manejo</I>: &aacute;rea de Prote&ccedil;&atilde;o    Ambiental do litoral de XXX: volume II: zoneamento e plano de gest&atilde;o.    Salvador, 1996b.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000091&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">SCT. <I>Plano de manejo</I>: &aacute;rea de prote&ccedil;&atilde;o    ambiental do litoral de XXX: zoneamento ecol&oacute;gico-econ&ocirc;mico e plano    de gest&atilde;o: S&iacute;ntese. Salvador, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000092&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">STONICH, S. C. Political ecology of tourism.    <I>Annals of Tourism Research</I>, v. 25, p. 25-54, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000093&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">STRONZA, A. Anthropology of tourism: forging    new ground for ecotourism and other alternatives. <I>Annual Review in Anthropology</I>,    v. 30, p. 261-283, 2001.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000094&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">TROOST, J. <I>Ecotoerisme: optie voor duurzame    exploitatie van beschermde gebieden?</I> (MA-thesis)&#150;Vrije Universiteit,    Amsterdam, 1995.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000095&pid=S0104-7183200300020001000020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Recebido em 03/08/2003    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana" size="2">Aprovado em 20/08/2003</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><a name="nota"></a><a href="#vnota">*</a> This    paper is a follow-up of the author's MA-thesis in Cultural Anthropology, at    the Vrije Universiteit of Amsterdam: The Hidden Stone Discovered. Tourism, <i>Environmental    Preservation and Social Conflicts</i>, 2000.    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="n1"></a><a href="#1n">1</a> Canoas is a pseudonym. As conflicts are    an important part of this paper, all names of local places, people and organisations    have been replaced by pseudonyms, in order not to cause damage to anyone. In    the bibliographic references, the original name of Canoas has been replaced    by XXX.    <br>   <a name="n2"></a><a href="#2n">2</a> Area of Environmental Protection.    <br>   <a name="n3"></a><a href="#3n">3</a><i> Favela</i> is the Brazilian term for    slum.    <br>   <a name="n4"></a><a href="#4n">4</a> Pousada is the Brazilian term for dormitory    facilities that range in quality from low budget to reasonably classy; the more    up scale accommodations are called hotels.    <br>   <a name="n5"></a><a href="#5n">5</a> At the time approximately 6 thousand US$.</font>  </p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BOO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecotourism: the potentials and pitfalls]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[World Wildlife Fund]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHEONG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S-M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MILLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Power and tourism: a Foucauldian perspective]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<page-range>371-390</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CODETUR]]></surname>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Programa de desenvolvimento turístico da Bahia: oportunidades de investimento]]></source>
<year></year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Salvador ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Governo do Estado da Bahia]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DHARMARATNE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SANG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F. Y.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WALLING]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[L. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Tourism potentials for financing protected areas]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<page-range>590-610</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DURHAM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Political ecology and environmental destruction in Latin America]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAINTER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DURHAM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The social causes of environmental destruction in Latin America]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Ann Arbor ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[EPPLER-WOOD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Global solutions: an ecotourism society]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WHELAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Nature tourism]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Island Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FUKS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Conflitos ambientais no Rio de Janeiro: ação e debate nas arenas públicas]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Editora UFRJ]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GALANI-MOUTAFI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A critical analysis of subjectivity]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<page-range>808</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HONEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecotourism and sustainable development: who owns paradise?]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eDC DC]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Island Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KHAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Tourism development and dependency theory: mass tourism vs. ecotourism]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<page-range>988-991</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MENEZES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T. H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Uso da denúncia de crime ambiental em assentamentos rurais na Mata Sul pernambucana]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[23 REUNIÃO DA ASSOCIAÇÃO BRASILEIRA DE ANTROPOLOGIA]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>2002</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Gramado </conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MOWFORTH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MUNT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Tourism and sustainability: new tourism in the third world]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAINTER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Introduction: anthropological perspectives on environmental destruction]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAINTER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DURHAM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The social causes of environmental destruction in Latin America]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Ann Arbor ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PLACE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Nature tourism and rural development in Tortuguero]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<page-range>186-201</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Governo do Estado da Bahia^dSecretaria de Cultura e Turismo</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Plano de manejo: área de proteção ambiental do litoral de XXX]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>I</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Salvador ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>SCT</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Plano de manejo: área de Proteção Ambiental do litoral de XXX]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>II</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Salvador ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>SCT</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Plano de manejo: área de proteção ambiental do litoral de XXX: zoneamento ecológico-econômico e plano de gestão: Síntese]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Salvador ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[STONICH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Political ecology of tourism]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annals of Tourism Research]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<page-range>25-54</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[STRONZA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Anthropology of tourism: forging new ground for ecotourism and other alternatives]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annual Review in Anthropology]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<page-range>261-283</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TROOST]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecotoerisme: optie voor duurzame exploitatie van beschermde gebieden?]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Amsterdam ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[(MA-thesis)-Vrije Universiteit]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
