<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>0104-7183</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Horizontes Antropológicos]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Horiz. antropol.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>0104-7183</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Programa de Pós-Graduação em Antropologia Social - IFCH-UFRGS]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S0104-71832000001400002</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0104-71832000001400002</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Plural identities among youth of immigrant backround in Montreal]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Meintel]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Deirdre]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Université de Montréal  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Canada</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2000</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2000</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<numero>14</numero>
<fpage>13</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0104-71832000001400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S0104-71832000001400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S0104-71832000001400002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Our research concerns the ethnic identity of youth (18-22yrs) of immigrant parentage (Greek, Portuguese, Chilean, Vietnamese and Salvadoran, with a comparison group of French-speaking Québécois youth) in Montreal. Despite the questioning of notions of ethnicity and ethnic identity that has been going on for several decades, this area of research is still marked by essentialist perspectives that do not coincide with the results of our research. The young people interviewed express fluid ethnic identities that have changed over time and that are characterised by multiple forms of ethnic belonging. They present their ethnic identity as a source of enrichment rather than of conflict or feelings of inferiority. The oral accounts of youth of immigrant origin in Montreal give much evidence of transnationality, that is, ties with the cultural group of origin whether in the country of origin or elsewhere; and of transethnicity, solidarities with other ethnic groups in Montreal that are seen as culturally or structurally similar. Though these two orientations would seem to be somewhat contradictory, they are, we argue, in fact compatible. Both offer numerous advantages to immigrant groups and their members, particularly in the present-day context. We examine our research results in light of contextual factors related to the Montreal milieu as well as to the age group of those interviewed. We propose that, without minimising these factors, one must question the conceptualisation of ethnic identity especially as it concerns youth of immigrant origins.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[RESUMO Nossa investigação refere-se a identidade étnica de jovens (18-22 anos) de ascendência imigrante (gregos, portugueses, chilenos, vietmamitas e salvadorenhos, em comparação com grupos de jovens de fala francesa quebecois) em Montreal. Apesar dos debates sobre noções de etnicidade e identidade étnica que tem sido feita por muitas décadas, esta área de pesquisa é ainda marcada por perspectivas essencialistas que não coincidem com os resultados de nossa investigação. Os jovens entrevistados expressam identidades étnicas fluidas que tem mudado extraordinariamente e que tem se caracterizado por múltiplas formas de pertencimento étnico. Eles apresentam sua identidade étnicas como uma fonte de enriquecimento ao invés de conflito ou sentimento de inferioridade. As considerações orais de jovens de origem migrante em Montreal oferecem muitas evidências de transnacionalidade, isto é, laços com o grupo cultural de origem, seja no país de origem ou outro lugar e a trans-etnicidade, solidariedade com outros grupos étnicos em Montreal que são vistos como culturalmente ou estruturalmente similares. Embora estas duas orientações possam ser vistas como algo contraditório, elas são, nós sustentamos, de fato compatíveis. Ambas oferecem numerosas vantagens para grupos imigrantes e seus membros, particularmente no contexto atual. Nós examinaremos os resultados desta pesquisa à luz de fatores contextuais relativos ao meio de Montreal tanto quanto aos grupos de idade de nossos entrevistados. Nós propomos que, sem minimizar estes fatores, devemos questionar a conceitualização de identidade étnica especialmente no que diz respeito a jovens de origem migrante.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[ethnic identity]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[transnationality]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[urban youth]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[identidade étnica]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[jovens urbanos]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[transnacionalidade]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ARTIGOS</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" font size="4"><b>Plural    identities among youth of immigrant backround in Montreal</b></font></p>       <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><B>Deirdre Meintel    </B></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Universit&eacute;    de Montr&eacute;al - Canada </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><B>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Our research concerns    the ethnic identity of youth (18-22yrs) of immigrant parentage (Greek, Portuguese,    Chilean, Vietnamese and Salvadoran, with a comparison group of French-speaking    Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois youth) in Montreal. Despite the questioning of notions    of ethnicity and ethnic identity that has been going on for several decades,    this area of research is still marked by essentialist perspectives that do not    coincide with the results of our research. The young people interviewed express    fluid ethnic identities that have changed over time and that are characterised    by multiple forms of ethnic belonging. They present their ethnic identity as    a source of enrichment rather than of conflict or feelings of inferiority. The    oral accounts of youth of immigrant origin in Montreal give much evidence of    transnationality, that is, ties with the cultural group of origin whether in    the country of origin or elsewhere; and of transethnicity, solidarities with    other ethnic groups in Montreal that are seen as culturally or structurally    similar. Though these two orientations would seem to be somewhat contradictory,    they are, we argue, in fact compatible. Both offer numerous advantages to immigrant    groups and their members, particularly in the present-day context. We examine    our research results in light of contextual factors related to the Montreal    milieu as well as to the age group of those interviewed. We propose that, without    minimising these factors, one must question the conceptualisation of ethnic    identity especially as it concerns youth of immigrant origins. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><B>Keywords: </B>ethnic    identity, transnationality, urban youth. </font></p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><B>RESUMO</B></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nossa investiga&ccedil;&atilde;o    refere-se a identidade &eacute;tnica de jovens (18-22 anos) de ascend&ecirc;ncia    imigrante (gregos, portugueses, chilenos, vietmamitas e salvadorenhos, em compara&ccedil;&atilde;o    com grupos de jovens de fala francesa quebecois) em Montreal. Apesar dos debates    sobre no&ccedil;&otilde;es de etnicidade e identidade &eacute;tnica que tem    sido feita por muitas d&eacute;cadas, esta &aacute;rea de pesquisa &eacute;    ainda marcada por perspectivas essencialistas que n&atilde;o coincidem com os    resultados de nossa investiga&ccedil;&atilde;o. Os jovens entrevistados expressam    identidades &eacute;tnicas fluidas que tem mudado extraordinariamente    e que tem se caracterizado por m&uacute;ltiplas formas de pertencimento &eacute;tnico.    Eles apresentam sua identidade &eacute;tnicas como uma fonte de enriquecimento    ao inv&eacute;s de conflito ou sentimento de inferioridade. As considera&ccedil;&otilde;es    orais de jovens de origem migrante em Montreal oferecem muitas evid&ecirc;ncias    de transnacionalidade, isto &eacute;, la&ccedil;os com o grupo cultural de origem,    seja no pa&iacute;s de origem ou outro lugar e a trans-etnicidade, solidariedade    com outros grupos &eacute;tnicos em Montreal que s&atilde;o vistos como culturalmente    ou estruturalmente similares. Embora estas duas orienta&ccedil;&otilde;es possam    ser vistas como algo contradit&oacute;rio, elas s&atilde;o, n&oacute;s sustentamos,    de fato compat&iacute;veis. Ambas oferecem numerosas vantagens para grupos imigrantes    e seus membros, particularmente no contexto atual. N&oacute;s examinaremos os    resultados desta pesquisa &agrave; luz de fatores contextuais relativos ao meio    de Montreal tanto quanto aos grupos de idade de nossos entrevistados. N&oacute;s    propomos que, sem minimizar estes fatores, devemos questionar a conceitualiza&ccedil;&atilde;o    de identidade &eacute;tnica especialmente no que diz respeito a jovens de origem    migrante. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><B>Palavras-chave:</B>    identidade &eacute;tnica, jovens urbanos, transnacionalidade. </font></p> <hr noshade size="1">     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>    <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Our research concerns    the ethnic identities of young adults (18-22years old) of immigrant parentage,    focussing on those of Greek, Portuguese, Chilean, Vietnamese and Salvadoran    background who were born in Montreal or at least spent most of their formative    years there. Despite the questioning of notions of ethnicity and ethnic identity    that has been going on for several decades, this area of research is still marked    by assimilationist perspectives that do not coincide with the results of our    research. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The young people    we interviewed express fluid ethnic identities that change over time and are    characterised by multiple forms of ethnic belonging which include strong identification    with the parents' country of origin. Their identities are composed of an accumulation    of affiliations; these are superimposed upon each other without one excluding    the other that are articulated into a personal syncretic identity somewhat differently    in each individual case. Plural identities are seen by our subjects as a source    of enrichment rather than a source of inner conflict or feelings of inferiority.    Indeed, for them, ethnic identity is not framed in a logic of closure, but rather    becomes the basis for wider solidarities both in the local setting and across    transnational space. Moreover, our subjects insist on the importance of their    several affiliations, rather than accepting one alone. Research on other themes    related to plural identities (i.e., international adoptions and mixed marriages)    gives further support for the conclusion that ethnocultural mixedness, be it    derived genealogically, via mixed marriage, or socially, via adoption, immigration    or other experiences, is widely valued in Montreal. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The data discussed    here originate primarily from semi-structured interviews with young people and    parents in various immigrant groups,<a name="nota11"></a><a href="#nota1"><SUP>1</SUP></a>    as well as with a comparison group of Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois youth of French    background. Our inter-pretations have been greatly enriched by participant-observation    field work carried out by graduate students in the immigrant groups included    in this study. We examine the research results in light of contextual factors    related to the Montreal milieu as well as to the age group of those interviewed.    </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><font size="3">The    Montreal multi-ethnic context</font></b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">To speak of immigration    to Quebec is inevitably to speak of Montreal, since almost 80% of new immigrants    to the province settle on the Island of Montreal, in the St. Lawrence River,    which includes the city proper and several other townships (Gouvernement du    Qu&eacute;bec, 2000a, p. 54). Still others settle in the greater Montreal metropolitan    region, about 10% of the rest, by informal estimates. This despite increased    efforts of late by the Quebec government to settle new arrivals in areas other    than Montreal. Moreover, in recent years Quebec has received a disproportionate    share of Canada's refugees, resulting in the presence of an ever larger, more    diversified and more "visible" immigrant population in Montreal (Laperri&egrave;re,    1989, p. 109).<a name="nota22"></a><a href="#nota2"><SUP>2</SUP></a> In the    1990's the main source countries for new arrivals to Qu&eacute;bec were, in    order of importance, Lebanon, France, China, Haiti, Hong Kong and Algeria (Gouvernement    du Qu&eacute;bec, 2000a, p. 39). Immigrants make up 17.8% of the total Montreal    metropolitan area population of nearly 3,393,700; on the Island of Montreal,    the proportion rises to over 25%. After Toronto, Montreal has the second highest    <I>number </I>(586,465) of immigrants living in her metropolitan area of all    cities in Canada, a fact that can    have important consequences for new arrivals. (Statistics Canada census data).    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The uniqueness    of the Montreal multi-ethnic context has attracted the attention of a number    of researchers. Anctil (1984), speaks of Montreal's "double majority" as it    contributes to greater retention of ethnic traits, such as language, religious    practice and endogamy by immigrant groups than in other North American cities    of comparable size. The &#171;double majority&#187; of which Anctil writes is,    of course, composed of the descendants of the two founding peoples, the French    and the British. Until the 1960's, interethnic relations in Montreal were generally    seen and constructed in religious terms, the "Catholic" category corresponding    approximately to the Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois,<a name="nota33"></a><a href="#nota3"><SUP>3</SUP></a>    and the "Protestant" to the Anglo-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois. Since the secularization    and liberalization of Quebec society during the so-called "Quiet Revolution"    of the 1960's, ethnic belonging has been expressed in linguistic terms, with    religion relegated to the background. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Today "French"    and "English" are commonly used as ethnic categories popular parlance, though    inaccurately. Just as the earlier religion-based bipolarity was inexact, so    is today's linguistic one. Jewish immigrants from Russia, the most numerous    group arriving at the turn of the twentieth century, were shunted to "Protestant"    schools and social services, and their English-speaking descendants are often    referred to as "English". Irish immigrants of the mid-ninetenth century, on    the other hand, generally shared religion and working-class status with Francophones    such today, many Francophones have Irish names such as Ryan, O'Neill and so    on.<a name="nota44"></a><a href="#nota4"><SUP>4</SUP></a> </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Also, it is important    to realize that the linguistic categories commonly used in as a gloss for ethnic    differences, namely "anglophone", "francophone" and "allophone" do not by any    means correspond to discrete groupings even on a linguistic level. This has    been officially recognized, at least implicitly, by the Office de la Langue    Fran&ccedil;aise (OLF), the public body charged with advancing the use of French    in Qu&eacute;bec. The most recent official defnition of "Franco-phone" by the    OLF is based the criterion of the language used on a regular basis in public,    rather than "mother tongue" or ancestry or even language used at home. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The unique quality    of the Montreal inter-ethnic context has also been shaped by lies in the fact    that neither majority's ethnic hegemony has been demographically or politically    stable over the last century-and-a-half. Though the French have predominated    since 1871, for a period in the 1830's and 40's the majority of the city's residents    were of British origins. The 20th century hs been marked by the growth of the    "othe" category; i.e., those of neither French nor British origins. As of 1986,    15.5 per cent of Montrealers were monolingual speakers of a language other than    French or English (Choini&egrave;re, 1990, p. 44), while 27 per cent claimed    an ethnic origin other than French or British (Choini&egrave;re, 1990, p. 74).    In certain neighborhoods, particularly in the younger age groups, being of &#171;minority&#187;    origin is to form part of a multi-ethnic majority of backgrounds other than    French nor British, such that certain of the city's institutions such as neighborhood    health care facilities, schools and day care centres have already been greatly    affected (Blanc; Chicoine; Germain, 1989). Indeed, immigrants and the children    of immigrants outnumber Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois in many local instituations    (schools, clinics, churches and so on.) </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The change in ethnic    and linguisitc political hegemony that have marked the last 15 years have, if    anything, further contributed to the maintenance of ethnic distinctiveness,    most clearly in the area of language. The most important changes of this period    were brought about by Bill 101, passed in 1977, under the first governement    of the sovereignist party, the Parti Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois. This bill made    French the sole official language of public life in Quebec and obliged children    whose parents' mother tongue was not English to go to French-language schools.    Schools are still divided by religion; most publicly supported schools are officially    Catholic (and French) or Protestant (and English), though efforts are underway    to abolish the religious identification. Before Bill 101, immigants were oriented    to English-language social services and their children to English-language schools.    In great part, this was the result of efforts by the Catholic clergy around    the turn of the century to limit contacts between French-speaking catholics    and immigrants, many of whom were Jewish. In consequence, the descendants of    immigrants came to identify as "Anglophones" in most cases; however, this has    changed since 1977. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Painchaud and Poulin    (1983) have noted that the changes in Quebec's language laws in the 1970's had    the effect of contributing to the maintenance of Italian    as the common language of the Italian community in Montreal ; we have noticed    the same among the Portuguese. Increasingly, the children of immigrants are    trilingual, learning, their parents' mother tongue at home, French at school,    and English via the mass media, social contacts and sometimes, special classes.    According to studies of the last few years, Montrealers who have grown up in    English are increasingly bilingual, especially in the younger age brackets,    while younger French-speakers are increasingly fluent in English as well (Jedwab,    1998; Meintel, 1999). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Besides the "double    majority", Montreal's special multi-ethnic character has also been shaped by    her historical role as a springboard to the rest of Canada and even to the United    States, such that new groups usually established their first ethnic institutions    (e.g., churches) in the city. This has also contributed to ethnic retention    by giving historical depth to immigrant groups that, in some cases, did not    immigrate in large numbers until long after the arrival of the founding members    of the community (Anctil, 1984, p. 447). And, as Breton (1964) long ago pointed    out, "institutional completeness" may be much more important than sheer numbers    in the maintenance of ethnic identity and distinctiveness over time. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In more suble and    profound ways, the Montreal context offers a hospitable environment for perpetuating    immigrant ethnic identities. For decades public discourse centered on the ethnic    specificity of the Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois terms of language, culture and identity    has dominated the mass media and political life in Quebec. The long struggle    of the francophone Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois for recognition of their group identity,    language and culture has served as something of a paradigm for other ethnic    groups. &#91;Cf. Coulon's discussion (1994) of "mimetisme" by ethnic communities    of the discourse and logic of the State&#93;. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Francophone Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    have been so long a political and cultural minority that their political hegemony    is still problematic and precarious even to themselves. Several of the young    Greeks, Portuguese and Chileans interviewed in the research presented in following    sections express an explicit sense of identification with the French-speaking    Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, not as members of minorities wishing to identify with    the majority, but rather as members of minorities relating to another minority    whose successful struggle they admire. Indeed the very word "minority" has a    peculiar resonance in Montreal at present, since virtually people of virtually    any ethnic category, not only immigrants, can lay claim to minority status:    the Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, because of French's linguistic isolation    in Canada and North America generally, Anglo-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois (those    of British ancestry), because of declining numbers and the official hegemony    of the French language in Quebec since 1977. Furthermore, individuals and groups    often <I>claim</I> ethnic minority status, in order to make or justify claims    to economic or political resources. (This is widely the case in Canada and the    United States.) In Montreal, stigmatizing minorisation of immigrants occurs    in particular contexts, notably in dealings with government agencies that control    scarce resources and where the personnel includes few of immigrant background;    <I>e.g.</I>, welfare and unemployment offices. In other contexts, interaction    takes place without ethnic hierarchy coming into play (Le Gall; Meintel, 1997).    Indeed, it is worth remembering that in Montreal, as elsewhere, "minority" and    "majority" refer to a relational dynamic, not to innate characteristics of individuals.    </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Methods of research    </b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The data on which    most of our discussion is based are taken from 80 interviews with young adults    between 18 and 22 years of age, including 20 Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    youth, and 20 immigrant parents. The 70 young adults of immigrant background    were of Portuguese, Greek, Salvadoran, Chilean. In addition we have used 10    interviews carried out in a parallel study using the same methods on youth of    Vietnamese parentage (M&eacute;thot, 1995). The Greek and Portuguese youth were    usually born in Montreal, whereas the others had arrived while still in primary    school, except for the Salvadorans, who had arrived in early adolescence. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">An intial period    of three months of participant observation allowed the research assistants to    construct an institutional topography of each group (churches, voluntary associations,    newspapers, etc.), to establish contacts with various social networks in the    gorup and to sketch out the social, demographic and economic characteristics    of the group, as well as the history of its migration to Qu&eacute;bec. At the    same time they sought to learn as much as possible about the social and cultural    life of the group, especially as related to the family. In some cases the assistants    were of the same origin as those they studied, in some cases of a different    origin, and in several cases, of Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois background.    In general, the interviews were held in the language of choice by the respondant,    be it their mother tongue, French or English. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The interviewees    were all bi- or tri-lingual, speaking their parents' mother tongue at home and    in ethnic community contexts, and English or French in other situations. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The initial round    of interviews were centered on issues related to how such youth participate    in Qu&eacute;bec society: employment, schooling, studies, social life and marriage    choices. Largely inspired by the Life Course Analysis pioneered by social historians    such as Elder (1977) et Hareven (1978), we sought to shed light on how decisions    related to work, family and social life were negotiated by the young adult and    the immediate family. Thus we decided to limit our study to youth between the    ages of 18 and 22 who were not yet cohabiting or married, as they were likely    to be engaged in making choices related to marriage, work and studies, yet still    be in frequent interaction with the family of origin. In fact, we found that    nearly all single young people of immigrant parentage were still living with    their parents, something that is considerably less frequent among their peers    of Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois background. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Interviews with    parents centered on the same themes as those with the youth, in order to verify    whether the young people's representations of the perspectives of the parental    generation corresponded in fact to how parents saw the same issues (Indeed,    there was close correspondance between the two). The twenty interviews with    young Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, evenly divided by sex, focussed on the    same th&egrave;mes as the others (schooling, work, social life and marriage).    The results of these last interveiws were unexpectedly revelatory and helped    us better the similarities of young people of immigrant origin across ethnic    lines. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Finally another    series of interviews were carried out with 10 Greek and 10 Portuguese youth,    on themes that had emerged from the preceding round of interviews, notably autonomy,    respect, family oblication, and the importance of the parent's country of origin    for the second generation, be it on the imaginary or concrete level. The master's    theses and publications of the student researchers who carried out the interviews,    some of which are cited here, have further enlarged our data base for each group.    </font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Ethnicity, ethnic    identity, plural identities </b></font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Though one often    hears the terms "ethnicity" and "ethnic identity" used interchangeably, it is    worth noting here that for our purposes, the latter term referes to subjective    dimension of ethnicity, to individuals' sense of belonging to a group that their    real or symbolic ancestors belonged to, as well as the sense of uniqueness,    unity, history and shared destiny shared with others in the same group (adapted    from Isajiw, 1990, p. 35). For us, ethnicity refers to a wieder phenomenon that    encompasses ethnic identity, but that includes as well the cultural models that    mark the group as distinctive; i.e., Barth's &#171;ethnic markers&#187; (1969),    as well as the social networks, institution, organisations, sharred activities,    economic and political interest that can mobilize an ethnic group. Ethnic identity    is often a focus of group ideology, and indeed, collective memory may be fashioned    so as to support a particular kind of ethnic identity. However, just as social    memory varies from one individual to another, unlike institutionalized collective    memory (Connerton, 1989), so ethnic identity is somewhat different for each    individual, even within the same ethnic group. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">When we discuss    plural, or composite, identities, we are referring to identities with several    referents. Grosser (1996) invokes his own status as male, father, Jewish, historian,    etc. to argue that individtual's identities are always plural. We would go even    further and suggest that even within the domain of ethnicity, identities are    probably more often plural than not, save for the influence of homogenizing    ideologies of identity promoted in many national contexts. At the same time,    following Devereux (1972), we hold that identity is by <I>definition </I>singular    ("unicit&eacute;") and unique. To imply that having a sense of belonging to    several societies or ethnic group means having several identities contributes    to an overly pathologizing view of those who identify with several ethnic categories.    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Children of immigrants    have often been described in schizophrenic terms, as being "torn" between different    cultures and identities, as having a "double identity" and suffering from social    pathology due to their plural origins and ethnic affiliations. Typically such    youth (especially North Africans in France) are described as "in crisis", torn    between opposing values (Khelil, 1991; Malewska, 1982; Yahyaoui, 1989). We have    argued elsewhere (Meintel, 1992) that the notion of a "double" identity is "oxymoronic",    to quote Giraud (1987). Though in rare cases, our subjects speak of themselves    in such terms we interpret such discourse more in terms of what the same author    terms a "strategic pluralism" (Giraud, 1987) rather than an a sign of crisis.    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The notion that    plural ethnic affiliations are by definition problematic is probably due in    part to the pervasive influence of Robert Park's theory of race relations, where    ghettoized immigrants eventually lose cultural particularities </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">and    ethnic specificity, to eventually assimilate, mixed marriage being one indicator    of that assimilation is nearly accomplished. Park's model was actually progressive    for its day: he was in fact arguing for what today would be called the "integratablility"    of immigrants from southern Europe arriving around the turn of the twentieth    century who were considered too different racially and culturally to ever become    fully American. Though clearly inadequate to describe the complexities of identity    and belonging in the present era, it nonetheless continues to inspire bipolar    models whereby &#171;traditional&#187; migrants are expected inevitably to give    up their culture and identities in the face of the "modernity" of the host society.    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Park's model is    not the only reason that plural identities, changes of identity and variations    of identity within the group concerned are generally taken to be problematic.    The fact that most academic social science has developped within powerful nation-states    (England, the United States, France) during the period when the State itself    was at its strongest has probably been a factor in leading researchers to think    in terms of exclusive identities. Indeed our title is somewhat misleading, in    that it presents plural identities as the "marked" case. Social scientists would    probably do well to problematize the exclusive "citizenship" model so often    applied to national, ethnic and even religious affiliations - i.e., unitary,    homogeneous, static identities and their construction as such. </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Immigrant youth:    a social portrait </b></font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Overall, the parents    of the Chilean and Vietnamese youth interviewed are better-educated and more    often urban in origin than those of the others, who tend to work in manual occupations    (often specialized ones in the case of the Greeks) or small family enterprises    and come from peasant or working-class background in the home country. Most    of the Greek and Portuguese youth were studying at the collegial level and working    part-time at jobs obtaine through ethnic networks, often via their parents.    Some hope to go on to university or have already begun universty studies. The    others in these two groups are working for minimum wage and would like to learn    a trade or specialized occupation in the service sector. The Vietnmese interviewed    by M&eacute;thot were all engaged in studies and oriented to or already at the    university, as was the case for most of the Chileans. The Salvadorans were mostly    studying at the collegial level, though some of the young men were apprentices    in semi-qualified occupations, such as garage mechanics. None of the Vietnamese    worked at a job, given their parents wish that they study full time so as to    excell academically. Most are oriented to liberal professions, especially in    the health field, such as medicine and dentistry. </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Young Greeks tend    to be English-speaking (though this is now changing), while the Portuguese,    some of whose parents have arrived in Canada more recently, speak English and/or    French; for the others we interviewed, French tended to be their second language    and sometimes English their third. Most socialize with peers from their own    group of origin or from other immigrant groups, and far less with other Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois.    Most Chileans and some Vietnamese young people have or have had close Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    friends. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Virtually all live    with their parents, and this for normative reasons rather than economic motivations,    a theme to which we return at a later point. Most of the Salvadoran households    included in the study are mother-headed, with the fathers often living in El    Salvador; in several cases Chilean fathers were absent due to death or divorce.    Most of the Portuguese youths contribute substantially to household income (Claudio,    1991), a pattern that is present in somewhat attenuated form among the Greeks.    In the latter case, the young people feel they <I>ought</I> to help their parents    either with money or by working in the family enterprise, but do so only irregularly,    with the tacit assent of their parents (Xenocostas, 1991). The young Latin Americans    help their parents financially on an informal, ad hoc basis, more substantially    in certain Salvadoran cases. Young women more often than their male peers help    with housework, but often do little because studying and holding a part-time    job. Greek and Portuguese sons are sometimes obliged to help in renovations    or in the family business, especially in the latter group. </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Family and identity    </b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As mentioned earlier    our project was initially focussed on immigrant family relationships and young    people's life choices that would have a long term effect on insertion in Quebec    society; ethnic identity emerged so strongly as a theme from the initial interviews    that it eventually became central to the analysis. It came as a surprise that    our respondants expressed emphatically supportive of the values they claimed    to share with their parents (and which were indeed those expressed by the parents    interviewed), and this, even in cases where there    seemed to be considerable disagreement in the day-to- day. Most proclaim their    adherance to the principle, transmitted by their parents, that family interests    should prevail over individual ones. As we have discussed elsewhere, it is in    the domain of family relationships and values that immigrants and their children    seem to find a major distinction between themselves and "les Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois",    and one that they value highly, the younger generation quite as vocally as the    older (Meintel, 1989). In general, both generations, in all the immigrant groups    included in the study, see their family lives as governed by notions of respect    for elders and family obligation to a far greater degree than Franco-Quebecois.    As a young Greek-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois puts it : </font></p>     <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Young Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois      are independent, they think abouve all of themselves (not their family)...      They are not like us, they don't have the same values, they are not as family-oriented      as the Greeks, they are not as respectful of their parents... (Marcos, 20      years old, student, born in Quebec). </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Among all the groups    but the Chileans, youth of both sexes usually lived in the parental home until    establishing a permanent couple relationship. While for the Salvadorans this    might take the form of longterm cohabitation, for the others, it meant marriage.    As for the Chileans, many of the parents are of leftist political orientations    and correspondingly, are quite permissive about sexual relations before marriage    - moreso than the parents of many of our young Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois subjects.    Many of the young people, especially among the describe marriage as the "real"    beginning of adult life. Cohabitation without marriage is often rejected by    the young women in these groups for moral or religious reasons, and also, some    say, it is "less romantic" than marriage. Even admitting that they might enjoy    the freedom of living elsewhere, youth of both sexes generally accept living    in their parents home, if only not to hurt their parents or embarrass them in    the ethnic community. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Young women often    brought up the importance of chastity and virginity at marriage as an ideal;    though this was less a focus than success in school work for the Vietnamese,    and for the chileans, notions of female chastity were a non-issue, given the    liberal attitudes of both youth and parents. For the Greeks, Portuguese and    Salvadorans, it was a question of morality and also of reputation for the girl    and her family. </font></p>      <blockquote>       ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">I have to watch      myself, I can't do just anything with guys that might give rise to gossip.      (Angela, 21 years old, student, born in Quebec of Greek parentage.) </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The words of a    young Salvadoran women make a clear connection between her identity and the    issue of virginity: </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">I was fourteen      when we came her, I know how my mother thinks and I know how Latino men think.      .And I'm Catholic. I have friends who have done it, but personally I prefer      not to... For me it's a culture, a way of thinking... (Eva, 21 years old,      student, born in El Salvador). </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nonetheless, like    her Salvadorean peers of both sexes, and most of the mothers interviewed, Eva    rejects machismo ; she abhores the idea of a man demanding virginity of a partner    ("Who does he take himself for?"). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Among Greeks and    Portuguese, the generations generally agree on the principle of ethnic endogamy.    Nonetheless, young people reason somewhat differently from their parents ; their    preference for marrying within the group (and its religion) is seen as contributing    to good relations between the two families, but they admit to a somewhat extended    notion of endogamy: ideally, someone of the same origin might be best, but failing    that, "at least" someone of a Mediterranean background. A few claim that ethnic    origin means nothing to them as regards the choice of a partner, but consider    it important for the sake of their parents. In other words, both youth and parents    see marriage as uniting two families, not just two individuals, and like their    parents, most see value in cultural proximity. However cultural proximity is    interpreted in more elastic fashion by the youth, and they put the emphasis    on its benefits for parents and family more than for themselves. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Young Latin Americans    seem to agree even more strongly with their parents than the others, at least    in principle. Chilean parents are characterized as "open" by their children,    as regards sexual mores, cohabitation, exogamy and so on Salvadoran parents    are much more conservative in regard to these questions, but the young people    (most of whom spent their primary school years in El Salvador) agree with them.    Moreover, in these two groups, respect for parents as parents is reinforced    by the respect for them as heroes of a political struggle. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Space does not    permit us to elaborate fully on how differences of opinion between the generations    regarding concrete issues (e.g. acceptable hours for girls to be out) are expressed;    however, it bears mentioning that each group is somewhat different in how conflict    is played out: the Vietnamese are unlikely to express any difference of opinion    with their parents, but note that their parents tend to be permissive on other    issues if their grades are high enough; Salvadoran youth are verbally open about    differences opinion with their parents but usually conform "out of respect";    Greek and Portuguese of the same age group are likely to disagree openly and    sometimes heatedly with parents, and often end up doing what they please, while    keeping an appearance of conformity, even if lying is necessary, once again,    "out of respect" (See Meintel; Le Gall, 1995 for further details). Among Salvadorans,    Portuguese and Greeks, parents have difficulty accepting their children, especially    the girls, dating more than one person before marriage. Typically, boyfriends    and girlfriends are not introduced to until marriage or (for the Salvadorans)    permanent cohabitation seemed likely, thus circumventing a potential problem.<a name="nota55"></a><a href="#nota5"><sup>5</sup></a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Generation/culture/immigration    </b> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">While the attitudes    our young subjects express may not correspond to their eventual choices in all    cases, the strong consensus they express in relation to their parents would    seem to contradict the numerous studies that emphasize generational conflict    in immigrant families, and consider it "far more serious" than in other families    (Malewska; Gachon, 1988). We do not seek to minimize the disagreements that    may exist between immigrant parents and their young adult offspring. However,    the supposition that conflict is a factor of cultural differences between parents    and offspring is often erroneous. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In Portuguese households,    for example, young men often are at odds with their fathers on the issue of    contributing their weekends to doing renovations on rental property (typically    the family lives on one floor of a duplex and pays the mortgage by renting the    other). However, the same type of conflict is found in rural Portugal. There    it used to be common for all to contribute their labor to the family agricultural    enterprise, but now young people are more often involved in wage work than in    the past and are loath to confide their earnings to their parents (Pina Cabral,    1986, p. 71). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Studies of immigrant    families usually do not include a "control group"; i.e. a selection of respondants    the native population; however we found this to be very useful for our analysis,    notably in regard to the issue of "conflict" between the generations. Most of    our interview subjects from immigrant backgrounds expressed a wish for "better    communication" with their parents in regard to contentious issues such as dating    patterns. However, the young Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois spoke even more    frequently of "lack of communication" with their parents. And for them, it was    not a matter of disgreement about specific problems, but rather a more general    lack of contact and affect that was at issue. Indeed, it seemed though there    was often minimal interaction and communication between parents and offspring,    even though living under the same roof (Meintel, 1989).<a name="nota66"></a><a href="#nota6"><SUP>6</SUP></a>    </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The supposition    that immigrant families are by definition more conflict-ridden than others is    based on a set of questionable notions about culture, migration and modernity    whereby "traditional" parents are thought to be at odds with "modern" children    influenced by the host society, a very dubious premisse. In the households concerned    by our own study, Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois parents were not, in general, as liberal-minded    as Chilean parents, because some of the Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois youth    came from conservative Catholic backgrounds. As we will see later one, such    notions as immigrants as "traditional" and "conservative" are less adequate    than ever in light of todays migratory currents. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">At this point,    though, it is important to note that the consensus young adults claim to hold    with their parents about fundamental family issues is so closely related to    identity that it may with some justification be construed as an identity strategy.    That is, family obligation, respect for elders and (in most of the immigrant    groups) more conservative behavior on the part of women are contrasted favorably    with the individualism, lack of respect and sexual looseness thought to characterize    the native-born Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois population (Meintel, 1989). And as we    have mentioned, some of the same subjects who emphasize their agreement with    parental values in the interviews are actually constantly at odds with their    parents regarding specific issues, such as financial contribution to the household    (as in the    case of some Portuguese). This said, we cannot speak of this consensus as "only"    a strategy, because where family ends and identity begins is impossible to discern:    for our young subjects and their parents, the two are inseparable. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">It should also    be noted that for many of our subjects, notions of Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois family    life are based on partial and often second-hand information, as well as media    images, since as they themselves report, they have few close friendships with    with majority Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois. Some mention being shocked by how other    students address teachers or how they talk about their parents. At the same    time, the fact is, Qu&eacute;bec society is markedly non-normative as compared    to the rest of Canada: divorce rates are high, and serial cohobitation without    marriage extremely common, such that 55% of all children are born out of wedlock    (as compared to 27% in the rest of Canada), according to a recent study.<a name="nota77"></a><a href="#nota7"><SUP>7</SUP></a>    </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Fluid affiliations    </b> </font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The importance    of age for our findings cannot be minimized. Nearly all the young people in    our immigrant-origin study group spoke of a change in their sense of identity    around the age of sixteen or so; that is, until that point, they had hoped to    simply to be like their peers. Somewhere between 15 and 17 years of age, they    develop an awareness of ethnic origins and pride in the cultural heritage associated    with them, a tendency that was particulary evident among young Chileans and    Vietnamese (cf. Grmela, 1991; M&eacute;thot, 1995). The shift in identification    was often associated with practical action: a change in patterns of sociability,    taking language classes so as to speak better Vietnamese,<a name="nota88"></a><a href="#nota8"><SUP>8</SUP></a>    plans to visit or continue studies in Chile: </font></p>      <blockquote>       ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">When I was younger,      I just wanted to be with the Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, I wasn't really friends      with young Chileans, but after you start hanging out more with Chileans, you      feel more Chilean, you say to yourself, `These are my roots', and you want      to go back there, you want to help. (Miguel, 18 years old, apprentice electrician.)      </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In a large-scale    study of various American ethnic groups, Mary Waters finds that such changes    are typical and appear regularly at certain moments of the life cycle (1990,    p. 36-46). In other research in Montreal we have found that older immigrant    women living alone (usually widowed) give more emphasis to ethnic identifications    and ethnic-centered activities than was the case earlier in their adult live    (Peressini; Meintel, 1993). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The young adults    in our study make it clear that they feel a sense of belonging to several cultures,    several national spaces, including Qu&eacute;b&eacute;c. They speak of their    plural affiliations not as a problem or a source of feelings of inferiority,    but if anything, as a source of enrichment. "Je suis Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    plus", several told us. While drawing contrasts between their own group of origin    and Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois in regard to family life they also see similarities;    the Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois are often described as "Latin" and thus, similar    to say, Portuguese, or Chileans. At the same time, several comment that their    identity is more secure than that of the Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois: as one woman    born of Portuguese parents puts it, "The French Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois are    not a people who are sure of themselves". </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Being "Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    plus" means being fully Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, but with yet other sources    of cultural richness and openness to the rest of the world: </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">I am Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois      but also Portuguese. </font></p>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois      culture and also the part of the Portuguese culture that we have, that makes      us people who are richer and more open. (Ida, born in Portugal, 23 years old).      </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Others talked of    how the experience of migration itself had enriched their lives. A young man    who is thinking of returning to Chile with his parents nonetheless has no regrets    about the migration experience: </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">When you come      from another country, you have different ideas, you are exposed to different      things... I think we are lucky to have come here, we have seen things that      we would not have, otherwise. (Daniel, 18 years old, student,arrived in Quebec      at 8 year of age). </font></p> </blockquote>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">These children    of immigrants believe that they possess all that is Qu&eacute;becois, more:    access to at least one, if not several other countries where they have close    family, knowledge of several languages, proximity to various other cultures.    Because of their multiple ways of situating themselves, they experience a critical    distance    toward all the cultural milieux they are a part of; can be quite as critical    of their own ethnic milieu and of the parents' milieu of origin as they are    of "les Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois". Young Latin Americans (and often, their mothers)    are highly critical of machismo: </font></p>     <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In El Salvador,      machismo is everywhere... The woman is supposed to do everything in the house,      and the macho, he hits the woman... I hate this stupidity. (Francisco, 18      years, student, arrived in Qu&eacute;bec at 12 years of age). </font></p> </blockquote>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">At the same time,    the ethnic milieu in Montreal is seen by the Greek and Portuguese especially    to be more conservative, less "modern" than the home country is today. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As we mentioned    earlier, the notion of "double identity" is not very helpful for characterising    the multiple affiliations of our subjects. The "we" in their narratives is an    elastic concept , revealing a wide range of identifications. "We Greeks in Qu&eacute;bec"    (as opposed to Greeks in Greece) gives place to "We Europeans" or "We Mediterraneans"    or, to mention a term one hears very often in Montreal, "We ethnics" (i.e.,    to refer to those of recent immigrant origin). What is more, some of the young    people evoke regional identifications, such as "Greeks from the Islands", "Azoreans",    "continental Portuguese", etc. Ethnic identity is far from the "turning inward"    or "ghetto mentality" in the way these young people relate themselves to others;    rather, it is often a basis for connectedness with others in the local environment    or across national boundaries. </font></p>      <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3">Ethnicity as    a base for connectedness </font></b></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Perhaps in part    because of the connection they make between family and ethnicity, most the young    people born in Canada as well as those born elsewhere feel a strong connection    with the parents' country of origin, something that we had not expected when    we began the study. While the place of the other national space may be important    primarily for imagining oneself in the world, there are many concrete connections    with it as well. Most have visited the country (some were themselves born there),    some would like to go there regularly; a few would like to actually live there.    Not, it should be added, in the rural villages where their parents came from    in many cases, but rather in Lisbon, Athens... Somewhat paradoxically, such    a project is sometimes seen as a means to have more personal freedom than in    the local ethnic community. </font></p>      <blockquote>       <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">I'd like to live      alone or with someone before I get married, but I wouldn't do it while living      here, with my familiy around... That is why I'd go to Greece. (Angela, 21      years, student, born in Qu&eacute;bec). </font></p> </blockquote>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Moreover, such    transnational solidarities are not always limited to the parents' country of    origin; a number the Vietnamese and the Salvadorans have spent long periods    in the United States and keep close contact with relatives there. The same is    true of Haitians in Montreal, who circulate between New York and Florida. Among    more e recently-arrived groups such as the Shiite Lebanese nuclear families    are commonly dispersed across several national spaces, including France, Quebec,    Lebanon and others (Le Gall, forthcoming). </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Transnational ties    do not exclude solidarities that cross ethnic lines on the local Montreal level    (Meintel, 1994); the young Vietnamese speak of the "Asiatic" category, including    themselves along with Laotians, Cambodians, Chinese and others. Even if such    a category is meaningless in outside the immigration context, they recognize    that it is operative in Montreal. On the one hand they are often confused with    Chinese (which some contest); on the other they remark on cultural convergences    between "les "Asiatiques", including family mores, especially the respect for    elders, religion, philosophy, while not disregarding the historically troubled    relations between China and Vietnam. The Chileans and Salvadorans for their    part feel part of a "community" that brings them together with other immigrant    groups from Latin America (Guatemalans, Colombians, Mexicans, Uruguayans, etc.).    Music, language, patterns of sociability, similar political concerns, and the    Catholic religion are all cited as points of convergence; at the same time,    voluntary associations, newspapers, churches, specialized grocery stores, bookstores    and other institutions help give structure to the community. It should be noted,    though, that class barriers seem to operate within this wider community, as    Lopes and Espiritu (1990) have noted regarding Latin Americans in the United    States; that is, Chileans, though taking prominent roles in some Latino associations,    tend to frequent members of their own group far more than the Salvadorans, whose    close friendships often include those from other Latin American countries. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Some of the identifications    mentioned earlier ("we Mediterraneans", "we Latins") give an idea of other,    less institutionalized transethnic solidiarities that are    nonetheless real for our subjects. The appelations "ethnics" is exceedingly    common in Montreal, and is used by others to refer to those descended from origins    other than British or French and is also used by those concerned to refer to    themselves. Indeed, while most of our respondants have close friendships outside    their group of origin, those ties concern mainly other children or grandchildren    of immigrants. Such solidarities are not without limits; some mention Blacks    or Pakistanis as "too different" to envision close relations with them. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Identity in    Montr&eacute;al today </b></font></p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Though the children    of immigrants we interviewed might be construed as "maintaining" ethnically    specific identities, one has to keep in minde that, while they may evoke one    or another identification in different discursive or social contexts, they insist    on being able to claim all of them. In short, they affirm cumulative,<a name="nota99"></a><a href="#nota9"><SUP>9</SUP></a>    plural identities (Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois, Greek, Greek-from-the Islands, Mediterranean,    "ethnic") that may be expressed selectively according to context, yet without    denying or negating any of the others. In fact our interlocutors are affirming    their mixedness, a theme that recurs in our work with Fran&ccedil;oise Romaine-Ouellette    on the Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois parents adopting internationally, who generally    project and try to support plural (Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois and Chinese, for    example) identities for their children. Research currently underway by Annie    LeBlanc on adult children of mixed marriages involving one Armenian parent as    well as that of Marie-Nathalie Le Blanc (1991) lends further support to the    conclusion that in ethnically mixed marriages, parteners embrace a mixed identity    for the family, leaning heavily toward that of the minority partner, and that    offspring of such marriages also feel themselves to be, as our informants put    it, "Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois plus". Mixedness that appears to be emerging as    a widespread value in Montreal, if not in Qu&eacute;bec generally, a theme that    we are studying in collaboration with colleagues.<a name="nota1010"></a><a href="#nota10"><SUP>10</SUP></a>    This is not a homogenizing mixedness destined to obscure real differences of    class or ethnicity,<a name="nota1111"></a><a href="#nota110"><SUP>11</SUP></a>    but rather a diversified mixedness whereby individuals can claim several identities    without denying any of them. In another publication we hope to elaborate further    on why Montreal is such a hospitable context for plural identities, not only    in the ethnic domain, but in those of kinship/family and religion as well. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In recent years,    since this study was carried out, trilingualism and international orientation    appear to have become even more valued among Montreal youth of all origins,    as the influences of globalisation make themselves felt. Those of French or    English mother tongue are more bilingual than ever before, and trilingualism    is extremely common among children of immigrants who are now in their early    twenties. Multilingualism and connections with other cultural contexts have    obvious value in the era of globalization. Moreover, present-day migration currents    are bringing migrants to Quebec who are better educated than ever before, moreso    than the general population (Gouvernement du Qu&eacute;bec, 2000b, p. 11); they    are educated, multilingual and often urban in bacground, such as to render obsolete    the stereotype of immigrants as peasants for whom migration has brought their    first direct contact with modern society. </font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">We have emphasized    the particular characteristics of the Montreal multi-ethnic setting in our approach    to plural identities partly because we believe that identities are very much    the product of cultural and political context. Indeed, as Levi-Strauss (1977)    shows us, the very notion of identity is very much a cultural one. In our view,    this emphasis on particularisms need not exclude comparison or even generalizations;    rather, we hope that this excursion into the particularities of ethnic identities    in Montreal may shed light on what might be less evident and more implicit in    other contexts. </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>References </b></font></p>      ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ANCTIL, P. Double    majorit&eacute; et multiplicit&eacute; ethnoculturelle &agrave; Montr&eacute;al.    <I>Recherches Sociographiques</I>, 25, 3, p. 441-450, 1984.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000113&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BARTH, F. <I>Ethnic    groups and boundaries</I>. Boston: Little Brown, 1969.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000115&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BLANC, Bernadette;    CHICOINE, N.; GERMAIN, A. Quartiers multiethniques et pratiques familiales:    la garde des jeunes enfants d'&acirc;ge scolaire. <I>Revue Internationale d'Action    Communautaire</I>, n. 21/61, p. 165-176, Spring 1989.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000117&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BRETON, R. Institutional    completeness of ethnic communities and the personal relations of emigrants.    <I>American Journal of Sociology</I>, 70, p. 193-205, 1964.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000119&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CHONI&Egrave;RE,    R. <I>La situation d&eacute;mographique et socio-economique de la population    du Montr&eacute;al metropolitain</I>: principaux r&eacute;sultats du r&eacute;censement    de 1986 par CLSC et DSC. Montr&eacute;al: R&eacute;groupement de D&eacute;partements    de Sant&eacute; Communautaire du Montr&eacute;al M&eacute;tropolitain, 1990.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000121&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref -->    </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CLAUDIO, F. <I>Culture    change and the redefinition of ethnicity</I>: the case of Portuguese youth in    Montreal. Master's thesis, D&eacute;partement d'anthropologie, Universit&eacute;    de Montr&eacute;al, 1991.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000123&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">COULON, C. Conclusion:    &eacute;tat et identites. In: MARTIN, Denis Constant (Dir.). <I>Cartes d'identit&eacute;s</I>:    comment dit-on `nous' en politique? Paris: Presses de la Fondation de Sciences    Politiques, 1994. p. 283-297.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000125&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">DERFEL, A. When    adults split, kids pay. <I>The Gazette</I>, p. 1 and 13, June 2000.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000127&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">DEVEREUX, G. L'identit&eacute;    ethnique: ses bases logiques et ses dysfunctions. <I>Ethnopsychiatrie Compl&eacute;mentariste</I>,    Paris: Flammarion, p.131-168, 1972.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000129&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ELDER, G. Family    history and the life course. <I>Journal of Family History</I>, v. 2, n. 4, p.    279-304, 1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000131&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">FONSECA, C. <I>Caminhos    da ado&ccedil;&atilde;o</I>. S&atilde;o Paulo, Cortez, 1995.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000133&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GIRAUD, M. Mythes    et strat&eacute;gies de la `double identit&eacute;'. <I>L'homme et la Soci&eacute;t&eacute;</I>,    v. 83, p. 59-67, 1987.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000135&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GOUVERNEMENT DU    QU&Eacute;BEC. <I>Caract&eacute;ristiques de l'immigration au Qu&eacute;bec</I>.    Produced by the Direction de la Planification Strat&eacute;gique du Minist&egrave;re    des Relations avec les Citoyens et de l'Immigration, Qu&eacute;bec, 2000a.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000137&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GOUVERNEMENT DU    QU&Eacute;BEC. 2000b. <I>L'immigration au Qu&eacute;bec</I>: un choix de d&eacute;veloppement.    Minist&egrave;re des Relations avec les Citoyens et de l'Immigration, Qu&eacute;bec,    2001-2003.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000139&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GRMELA, S. The    political and cultural identity of second generation Chilean exiles in: Quebec.    In: SHARMA, S. P.; ERVIN, A. M.; MEINTEL, D. Meintel (Ed.). <I>Immigrants and    refugees in Canada</I>: a national perspective on ethnicity, multiculturalism    and cross-cultural adjustment. Saskatoon: University of Saskatchewan, 1991.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000141&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref -->    </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GROSSER, A. <I>Les    identit&eacute;s difficiles</I>. Paris: Presses de Sciences Po, La Biblioth&egrave;que    du Citoyen, 1996.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000143&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">HAREVEN, T. Cycles,    courses and cohorts: reflections on theoretical and methodological approaches    to the historical study of family development. <I>Journal of Social History</I>,    v. 12, p. 97-109, 1978.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000145&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ISAJIW, W. W. Ethnic-identity    retention. In: BRETON, R.; ISAJIW, W. W.; KALBACH, E.; REITZ, J. G. <I>Ethnic    identity and equality</I>: vaireties of experience in a Canadian city. University    of Toronto Press, 1990. p. 34-91.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000147&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">JEDWAB, J. <I>Heritage    languages in Canada</I>: for the Centre de langues patrimoniales de l'Universit&eacute;    de Montr&eacute;al. 73 pages. In&eacute;dit, 1998.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000149&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">KHELIL, M. <I>L'int&eacute;gration    des Magrh&eacute;bins en France</I>. Paris: Presses Universitaires de France,    1991.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000151&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LAPERRI&Egrave;RRE,    A. (Dir.). <I>La construction sociale des relations interethniques et interraciales    chez des jeunes de deux quariters montr&eacute;alais</I>. Montr&eacute;al: Universit&eacute;    de Montr&eacute;al et l'Institut Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois de Recherche sur la    Culture, 1989.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000153&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LE BLANC, M.-N.    <I>La construction du sujet ethnique dans les mariages mixtes chez les canadiens    fran&ccedil;ais et les juifs s&eacute;pharades &agrave; Montr&eacute;al</I>.    Master's thesis, D&eacute;partement d'Anthropologie, Universit&eacute; de Montr&eacute;al,    1991.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000155&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LE GALL, J. <I>Les    relations familiales pour les femmes chiites libanaises &agrave; Montr&eacute;al</I>.    Forthcoming.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000157&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LE GALL, J.; MEINTEL,    D. <I>Espaces observ&eacute;s</I>: ethnicit&eacute; et appropriation territoriale.    In: MEINTEL, D.; PICH&Eacute;, V.; JUTEAU, D.; FORTIN, S. <I>C&ocirc;te-des-Neiges</I>:    un quartier pluriethnique &agrave; Montr&eacute;al. Paris: Harmattan, 1997.    p. 211-228.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000159&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">L&Eacute;VI-STRAUSS,    C. (Dir.). <I>L'identit&eacute;</I>. Paris: Grasset, 1977.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000161&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LINTEAU, P.-A.    La mont&eacute;e du cosmopolitisme montr&eacute;alais. <I>Questions de Culture</I>,    n. 2, p. 23-54, 1982.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000163&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200026&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">LOPES, D.; ESPIRITU,    Y. Panethnicity in the United States: a theoretical framework. <I>Ethnic and    Racial Studies</I>, v. 13, n. 2, p. 198-224, avril 1990.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000165&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200027&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MALEWSKA, H. (Dir.).    <I>Crise d'identit&eacute; et d&eacute;viance des jeunes immigr&eacute;s</I>.    Paris: Minist&egrave;re de la Justice, 1982.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000167&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200028&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MALEWSKA, H.; GACHON,    C. <I>Le travail social et les enfants de migrants</I>: racisme et identit&eacute;,    recherche-action. Paris: CIEMI: Harmattan, 1988.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000169&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200029&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MEINTEL, D. Les    Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois vus par les jeunes d'origine immigr&eacute;e. <I>Revue    Internationale de l'Action Communautaire</I>, n. 21/61, p. 81-94, printemps    1989.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000171&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200030&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">______. Identit&eacute;    ethnique chez de jeunes montr&eacute;alais d'origine immigr&eacute;e. <I>Sociologie    et Soci&eacute;t&eacute;s</I>, v. 24, n.<SUP> </SUP>2, p. 73-89, 1992.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000173&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200031&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">______. Transethnicit&eacute;    et transnationalit&eacute; chez des jeunes issus de milieux immigr&eacute;s.    <I>Revue Europ&eacute;enne des Migrations Internationales</I>, v. 9, n. 3, p.    63-79, 1994.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000175&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200032&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MEINTEL. Les politiques    linguistiques et la nouvelle pluriethnicit&eacute; montr&eacute;alaise. Publi&eacute;    Etudes Canadiennes. <I>Canadian Studies</I>, n. 45, 1999.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000177&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200033&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MEINTEL, D.; LE    GALL, J. <I>Les jeunes d'origine immigr&eacute;e</I>: rapports familiaux et    les transitions de vie - le cas des jeunes chiliens, grecs, portugais, salvadoriens    et vietnamiens. Qu&eacute;bec: Minist&egrave;re des Affaires Internationales,    de l'Immigration et des Communaut&eacute;s Culturelles, 1995. (Collection &Eacute;tudes    et recherches, n. 10).    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000179&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200034&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">M&Eacute;THOT,    C. <I>Du Vi&ecirc;t-Nam au Qu&eacute;bec</I>: la valse des identit&eacute;s.    Qu&eacute;bec: Institut Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois de Recherche sur la Culture,    1995.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000181&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200035&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">ORIOL, M. L'ordre    des identit&eacute;s. <I>Revue Europeenne des Migrations Internationales</I>,    v. 1, n. 2, p. 171-185.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000183&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200036&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">PAINCHAUD; POULIN,    R. 1983 Conflit linguistique et structure de pouvoir dans la communaut&eacute;    Italo-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;coise. <I>Sociologie et Societ&eacute;s</I>, v. 15,    n.<SUP> </SUP>2, p. 89-104, 1985.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000185&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200037&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">PERESSINI, M.;    MEINTEL, D. Identit&eacute; familiale et identit&eacute; individuelle chez des    immigrantes italiennes: r&eacute;flexions &agrave; partir de deux recherches.    <I>Culture</I>, v. 13, n.<SUP> </SUP>2, p. 17-36, 1993.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000187&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200038&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">PINA-CABRAL, J.    de. <I>Sons of Adam, daughters of Eve</I>: the peasant world view of the Alto    Minho. Oxford, Clarendon Press, 1986.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000189&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200039&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">WATERS, M. <I>Ethnic    options</I>: choosing identities in America. Berkeley, Los Angeles: University    of California, 1990.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000191&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200040&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">XENOCOSTAS, S.    Familial obligation: ideal models of behaviour for second generation Greek youth    in Montreal. In: SHARMA, S. P.; ERVIN, A. M.; MEINTEL, D. Meintel (Ed.). <I>Immigrants    and refugees in Canada</I>: a national perspective on ethnicity, multiculturalism    and cross-cultural adjustment. Saskatoon: University of Saskatchewan, 1991.    p. 294-316.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000193&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200041&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">YAHYAOUI, A. (Dir.).    <I>Identit&eacute;, culture et situation de crise</I>. Grenoble: La Pens&eacute;e    Sauvage, 1989.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000195&pid=S0104-7183200000140000200042&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>      <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="nota1"></a><a href="#nota11">1</a>    The research and analysis were made possible by funds from the FCAR (Province    of Qu&eacute;bec), the Secretariat of State (Canada), the Minist&egrave;re des    communaut&eacute;s culturelles et de l'immigration (Qu&eacute;bec) and from    the Universit&eacute; de Montr&eacute;al.</font>     <br>   <a name="nota2"></a><a href="#nota22">2</a> In the 1990's the main    source countries for new arrivals to Qu&eacute;bec were, in order of importance,    Lebanon, France, China, Haiti, Hong Kong and Algeria (Gouvernement du Qu&eacute;bec,    2000, p. 39).     <br>   <a name="nota3"></a><a href="#nota33">3</a> By "Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois"    we mean Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois of French background whose roots are long-established    in Quebec, since Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois is meant to refer to <u>all</u> citizens    of Canada who permanently reside in Qu&eacute;bec.    <br>   <font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="nota4"></a><a href="#nota44">4</a>    The Irish accounted for 7.1% of British immigrants in 1844 (Linteau, 1982, p.    26, Table 1) and by 1871 made up nearly a fourth (23.7%) of the city's population    (Linteau, 1982, p. 29).     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   <a name="nota5"></a><a href="#nota55">5</a> We should mention that we did not    ask questions about gay and lesbian relationships, nor was the subject was ever    brought up by any of our subjects.     <br>   <a name="nota6"></a><a href="#nota66">6</a> We chose to interview Franco-Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois    who were currently living with their parents, for greater comparability to the    youth of other groups. Their reasons for living with parents were economic rather    than normative and in many cases, the young person had lived elsewhere for a    time.    <br>   <a name="nota7"></a><a href="#nota77">7</a> This information comes from a newspaper    article (Derfel 2000) concerning ongoing research by Richard Tremblay, Nicole    Marcil-Gratton and other researchers at the Universit&eacute; de Montr&eacute;al.    The study was commissioned by the Quebec Health Departement.    <br>   <a name="nota8"></a><a href="#nota88">8</a> Young Vietnamese sometimes find    that they are embarrassed to speak Vietnamese with their grandparents, as they    don't know all the all the appropriate polite forms.    <br>   <a name="nota9"></a><a href="#nota99">9</a> The notion of cumulative identities    owes much to Fonseca (1995).     <br>   <a name="nota10"></a><a href="#nota1010">10</a> This is one of the themes of    research presently being carried out by the Groupe de recherche Ethnicit&eacute;    et soci&eacute;t&eacute;, an interdisciplinary research group, at the Universit&eacute;    de Montr&eacute;al.     <br>   <a name="nota110"></a><a href="#nota1111">11</a>    Other research that we have carried out on Cape Verdeans in the U.S. and in    Cabo Verde, supplemented by the more recent field work of Isabel Rodrigues,    indicates that "mixedness" is often invoked in political discourse (<i>Somos    todos mistos</i>) in such a way as to level or negate class and colour differences.    We leave it to the reader to decide whether such is the case in Brazil. </font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ANCTIL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Double majorité et multiplicité ethnoculturelle à Montréal]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Recherches Sociographiques]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>441-450</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BARTH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ethnic groups and boundaries]]></source>
<year>1969</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Boston ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Little Brown]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BLANC]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Bernadette]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHICOINE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[N.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GERMAIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Quartiers multiethniques et pratiques familiales: la garde des jeunes enfants d'âge scolaire]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revue Internationale d'Action Communautaire]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>61</numero>
<issue>61</issue>
<page-range>165-176</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BRETON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Institutional completeness of ethnic communities and the personal relations of emigrants]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[American Journal of Sociology]]></source>
<year>1964</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<page-range>193-205</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHONIÈRE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[La situation démographique et socio-economique de la population du Montréal metropolitain: principaux résultats du récensement de 1986 par CLSC et DSC]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Montréal ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Régroupement de Départements de Santé Communautaire du Montréal Métropolitain]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CLAUDIO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Culture change and the redefinition of ethnicity: the case of Portuguese youth in Montreal]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COULON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Conclusion: état et identites]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MARTIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Denis Constant]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Cartes d'identités: comment dit-on `nous' en politique?]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<page-range>283-297</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Presses de la Fondation de Sciences Politiques]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DERFEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[When adults split, kids pay]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Gazette]]></source>
<year>June</year>
<month> 2</month>
<day>00</day>
<volume>1</volume><volume>13</volume>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DEVEREUX]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[L'identité ethnique: ses bases logiques et ses dysfunctions]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ethnopsychiatrie Complémentariste]]></source>
<year>1972</year>
<page-range>131-168</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Flammarion]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ELDER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Family history and the life course]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Family History]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<issue>4</issue>
<page-range>279-304</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FONSECA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Caminhos da adoção]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São Paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cortez]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GIRAUD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Mythes et stratégies de la `double identité']]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[L'homme et la Société]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<volume>83</volume>
<page-range>59-67</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>GOUVERNEMENT DU QUÉBEC</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Caractéristiques de l'immigration au Québec]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Direction de la Planification Stratégique du Ministère des Relations avec les Citoyens et de l'Immigration]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>GOUVERNEMENT DU QUÉBEC</collab>
<source><![CDATA[L'immigration au Québec: un choix de développement]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<month>-2</month>
<day>00</day>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministère des Relations avec les Citoyens et de l'Immigration]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GRMELA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The political and cultural identity of second generation Chilean exiles in: Quebec]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SHARMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ERVIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Immigrants and refugees in Canada: a national perspective on ethnicity, multiculturalism and cross-cultural adjustment]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Saskatoon ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Saskatchewan]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GROSSER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Les identités difficiles]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Presses de Sciences PoLa Bibliothèque du Citoyen]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HAREVEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Cycles, courses and cohorts: reflections on theoretical and methodological approaches to the historical study of family development]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Journal of Social History]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>12</volume>
<numero>1978</numero>
<issue>1978</issue>
<page-range>97-109</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ISAJIW]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W. W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Ethnic-identity retention]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BRETON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ISAJIW]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W. W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KALBACH]]></surname>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[REITZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ethnic identity and equality: vaireties of experience in a Canadian city]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<page-range>34-91</page-range><publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Toronto Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JEDWAB]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Heritage languages in Canada: for the Centre de langues patrimoniales de l'Université de Montréal]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Inédit]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KHELIL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[L'intégration des Magrhébins en France]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Presses Universitaires de France]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LAPERRIÈRRE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[La construction sociale des relations interethniques et interraciales chez des jeunes de deux quariters montréalais]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Montréal ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Université de Montréall'Institut Québécois de Recherche sur la Culture]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LE BLANC]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.-N.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[La construction du sujet ethnique dans les mariages mixtes chez les canadiens français et les juifs sépharades à Montréal]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LE GALL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Les relations familiales pour les femmes chiites libanaises à Montréal]]></source>
<year></year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Forthcoming]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LE GALL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Espaces observés: ethnicité et appropriation territoriale]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PICHÉ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JUTEAU]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FORTIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Côte-des-Neiges: un quartier pluriethnique à Montréal]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<page-range>211-228</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Harmattan]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LÉVI-STRAUSS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[L'identité]]></source>
<year>1977</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Grasset]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LINTEAU]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.-A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[La montée du cosmopolitisme montréalais]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Questions de Culture]]></source>
<year>1982</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<page-range>23-54</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LOPES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ESPIRITU]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Y.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Panethnicity in the United States: a theoretical framework]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ethnic and Racial Studies]]></source>
<year>avri</year>
<month>l </month>
<day>19</day>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>198-224,</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MALEWSKA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Crise d'identité et déviance des jeunes immigrés]]></source>
<year>1982</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministère de la Justice]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MALEWSKA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GACHON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Le travail social et les enfants de migrants: racisme et identité, recherche-action]]></source>
<year>1988</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[CIEMIHarmattan]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Les Québécois vus par les jeunes d'origine immigrée]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revue Internationale de l'Action Communautaire]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>61</numero>
<issue>61</issue>
<page-range>81-94</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B31">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Identité ethnique chez de jeunes montréalais d'origine immigrée]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Sociologie et Sociétés]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>73-89</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B32">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Transethnicité et transnationalité chez des jeunes issus de milieux immigrés]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revue Européenne des Migrations Internationales]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>63-79</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B33">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Les politiques linguistiques et la nouvelle pluriethnicité montréalaise]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Canadian Studies]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>45</volume>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B34">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LE GALL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Les jeunes d'origine immigrée: rapports familiaux et les transitions de vie - le cas des jeunes chiliens, grecs, portugais, salvadoriens et vietnamiens]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Québec ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministère des Affaires Internationales, de l'Immigration et des Communautés Culturelles]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B35">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MÉTHOT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Du Viêt-Nam au Québec: la valse des identités]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Québec ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Institut Québécois de Recherche sur la Culture]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B36">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ORIOL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[L'ordre des identités]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revue Europeenne des Migrations Internationales]]></source>
<year></year>
<volume>1</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>171-185</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B37">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAINCHAUD]]></surname>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[POULIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[1983 Conflit linguistique et structure de pouvoir dans la communauté Italo-Québécoise]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Sociologie et Societés]]></source>
<year>1985</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>89-104</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B38">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PERESSINI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="fr"><![CDATA[Identité familiale et identité individuelle chez des immigrantes italiennes: réflexions à partir de deux recherches]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Culture]]></source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>17-36</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B39">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PINA-CABRAL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J. de]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Sons of Adam, daughters of Eve: the peasant world view of the Alto Minho]]></source>
<year>1986</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Oxford ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Clarendon Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B40">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WATERS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ethnic options: choosing identities in America]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Berkeley^eLos Angeles Los Angeles]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of California]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B41">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[XENOCOSTAS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Familial obligation: ideal models of behaviour for second generation Greek youth in Montreal]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SHARMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ERVIN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MEINTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Immigrants and refugees in Canada: a national perspective on ethnicity, multiculturalism and cross-cultural adjustment]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Saskatoon ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[University of Saskatchewan294-316]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B42">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[YAHYAOUI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Identité, culture et situation de crise]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Grenoble ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[La Pensée Sauvage]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
