<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1414-753X</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Ambiente & Sociedade]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Ambient. soc.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1414-753X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ANPPAS - Revista Ambiente e Sociedade]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1414-753X2012000100013</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1414-753X2012000100013</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Climate Change and "historical responsibilities"]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Goldemberg]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[José]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Guardabassi]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Patricia Maria]]></given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Universidade de São Paulo Instituto de Eletrotécnica e Energia ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ SP]]></addr-line>
<country>Brasil</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>04</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<fpage>201</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000100013&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000100013&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000100013&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[The historical responsibility of countries listed in the Annex I of the Convention on Climate Change has been used extensively as a justification for the lack of action of countries not included in Annex I to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions. We analyzed the contribution of non-Annex I countries to the CO2 emissions in the period 1850 - 2006 to assess their relative contribution to total CO2 emissions. In the period 1980 - 2006 non-Annex I countries represented 44% of the total but this contribution increased in the period 1990 - 2006 to 48%. If we extrapolate present trends to 2020 they will represent 56% in the period 1990 - 2020. The "historical responsibility" of Annex I countries is therefore decreasing. If we take 1990 as the starting year in which the Climate Convention recognized clearly that greenhouse gases are interfering dangerously with the climate system, it becomes very difficult to attribute "blame" and "guilt" to Annex I for their historical contributions. It becomes also quite clear the need of non-Annex I countries to engage with Annex I countries in the effort to reduce emissions. The Copenhagen Accord has no mention of "historical responsibilities".]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[As responsabilidades históricas dos países do Anexo I da Convenção do Clima têm sido utilizadas extensivamente pelos países que não fazem parte deste Anexo como justificativa para sua falta de ação a respeito da redução das emissões de gases de efeito estufa. Analisou-se aqui a contribuição de tais países nas emissões totais de CO2, no período 1850-2006, visando mensurar sua contribuição relativa. No período 1980-2006, os países que não são parte do Anexo I representaram 44% do total, mas esta contribuição aumentou, no período 1990-2006, para 48%. Extrapolando as tendências atuais para o ano 2020, tais emissões representarão 56% no período 1990-2020. Portanto, a "responsabilidade histórica" dos países do Anexo I está diminuindo. Ao considerarmos 1990 como o ano em que a Convenção do Clima reconheceu claramente que os gases de efeito estufa estão interferindo perigosamente com o sistema climático, se torna muito difícil atribuir "responsabilidade" e "culpa" aos países do Anexo I por sua contribuição histórica. Torna-se clara também a necessidade de engajamento dos países que não fazem parte do Anexo I, conjuntamente aos países do Anexo I, nos esforços de redução das emissões. O Acordo de Copenhague não faz menção a "responsabilidades históricas".]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[historical responsibilities]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Copenhagen Accord]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[non-Annex I CO2 emissions]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[responsabilidades históricas]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Acordo de Copenhague]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[emissões CO2]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[países não-Anexo I]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font size="2" face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif"><b>CONTRIBUI&Ccedil;&Atilde;O    AO DEBATE</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><a name="top"></a><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><b>Climate    Change and "historical responsibilities"</b> </font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Jos&eacute;    Goldemberg<sup>I</sup>; Patricia Maria Guardabassi<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>I</sup>Professor    do Instituto de Eletrot&eacute;cnica e Energia da Universidade de S&atilde;o    Paulo. Av. Prof. Luciano Gualberto, 1289 Butant&atilde; CEP 05508-010 - S&atilde;o    Paulo, SP - Brasil. (Instituto de Eletrot&eacute;cnica e Energia da Universidade    de S&atilde;o Paulo, SP - Brasil)    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Pesquisadora do Centro Nacional de Refer&ecirc;ncia em Biomassa.    Av. Prof. Luciano Gualberto, 1289 - Cidade Universit&aacute;ria Butant&atilde;    CEP 05508-900 - S&atilde;o Paulo, SP - Brasil. E-mail: <a href="mailto:guardabassi@iee.usp.br">guardabassi@iee.usp.br</a>    (Centro Nacional de Refer&ecirc;ncia em Biomassa. Instituto de Eletrot&eacute;cnica    e Energia da Universidade de S&atilde;o Paulo, SP - Brasil)</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The historical    responsibility of countries listed in the Annex I of the Convention on Climate    Change has been used extensively as a justification for the lack of action of    countries not included in Annex I to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions.    We analyzed the contribution of non-Annex I countries to the CO<sub>2</sub>    emissions in the period 1850 - 2006 to assess their relative contribution to    total CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. In the period 1980 - 2006 non-Annex I countries    represented 44% of the total but this contribution increased in the period 1990    - 2006 to 48%. If we extrapolate present trends to 2020 they will represent    56% in the period 1990 - 2020. The "historical responsibility" of Annex I countries    is therefore decreasing. If we take 1990 as the starting year in which the Climate    Convention recognized clearly that greenhouse gases are interfering dangerously    with the climate system, it becomes very difficult to attribute "blame" and    "guilt" to Annex I for their historical contributions. It becomes also quite    clear the need of non-Annex I countries to engage with Annex I countries in    the effort to reduce emissions. The Copenhagen Accord has no mention of "historical    responsibilities".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Keywords:</b>    historical responsibilities, Copenhagen Accord, non-Annex I CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As responsabilidades    hist&oacute;ricas dos pa&iacute;ses do Anexo I da Conven&ccedil;&atilde;o do    Clima t&ecirc;m sido utilizadas extensivamente pelos pa&iacute;ses que n&atilde;o    fazem parte deste Anexo como justificativa para sua falta de a&ccedil;&atilde;o    a respeito da redu&ccedil;&atilde;o das emiss&otilde;es de gases de efeito estufa.    Analisou-se aqui a contribui&ccedil;&atilde;o de tais pa&iacute;ses nas emiss&otilde;es    totais de CO<sub>2</sub>, no per&iacute;odo 1850-2006, visando mensurar sua    contribui&ccedil;&atilde;o relativa. No per&iacute;odo 1980-2006, os pa&iacute;ses    que n&atilde;o s&atilde;o parte do Anexo I representaram 44% do total, mas esta    contribui&ccedil;&atilde;o aumentou, no per&iacute;odo 1990-2006, para 48%.    Extrapolando as tend&ecirc;ncias atuais para o ano 2020, tais emiss&otilde;es    representar&atilde;o 56% no per&iacute;odo 1990-2020. Portanto, a "responsabilidade    hist&oacute;rica" dos pa&iacute;ses do Anexo I est&aacute; diminuindo. Ao considerarmos    1990 como o ano em que a Conven&ccedil;&atilde;o do Clima reconheceu claramente    que os gases de efeito estufa est&atilde;o interferindo perigosamente com o    sistema clim&aacute;tico, se torna muito dif&iacute;cil atribuir "responsabilidade"    e "culpa" aos pa&iacute;ses do Anexo I por sua contribui&ccedil;&atilde;o hist&oacute;rica.    Torna-se clara tamb&eacute;m a necessidade de engajamento dos pa&iacute;ses    que n&atilde;o fazem parte do Anexo I, conjuntamente aos pa&iacute;ses do Anexo    I, nos esfor&ccedil;os de redu&ccedil;&atilde;o das emiss&otilde;es. O Acordo    de Copenhague n&atilde;o faz men&ccedil;&atilde;o a "responsabilidades hist&oacute;ricas".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Palavras-chave:    </b> responsabilidades hist&oacute;ricas, Acordo de Copenhague, emiss&otilde;es    CO<sub>2</sub>, pa&iacute;ses n&atilde;o-Anexo I.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Introduction</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The United Nations    Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) commonly referred as Convention    on Climate Change was adopted on May 9<sup>th</sup> 1992, at the United Nations    Headquarters, in New York, by the Intergovernmental Negotiating Committee (INC)    and was opened for signature in June 1992 at the Rio de Janeiro Earth Summit.    It was signed by Heads of State and other senior representatives from 154 countries    (and the European Community) and entered into force on March 21<sup>st</sup>    1994.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">One could then    consider 1992 as the year at which a decision was taken by the signatories to    achieve "stabilization of greenhouse gas concentrations at a level that would    prevent dangerous anthropogenic interference with the climate system" (article    2 of the Convention).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">A number of commitments    were adopted in the Convention binding "all Parties, taking into account their    common but differentiated responsibilities and their specific national and regional    development priorities, objectives and circumstances" (article 4 of the Convention).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The developed countries    (listed in the Annex I of the Convention) where committed to take actions "with    the aim of returning individually or jointly to their 1990 levels these anthropogenic    emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gas" (article 4 of the Convention)    which, as is well known, didn't occur.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Convention    determined also that the burden of the actions and assistance to developing    country Parties should fall in the countries listed in Annex II (developed countries).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Convention    strengthened these commitments in 1997 through the Kyoto Protocol which established    quantitative levels of reduction of at least 5% below the 1990 level, between    2008 and 2012, for the countries listed in Annex I of the Convention (developed    countries and economies in transaction). Non-Annex I countries (developing countries    were exempted from any mandatory reductions).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The year 1990 is    the reference year in the Convention after which no country could argue ignorance    of the adverse effects of the increased concentration of greenhouse gases in    the atmosphere.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The rational for    these decisions is stated in the preamble of the Convention which took note    "that the largest share of <u>historical</u> and current global emissions of    greenhouse gases has originated in the developed countries, that per capita    emissions in developing countries are still relatively low and that the share    of global emissions originating in developing countries will grow to meet their    social and development needs".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This is the only    place in the Convention where mention is made of "historical emissions" which    was largely used by developing countries, particularly China, to avoid taking    actions to reduce their emissions or to reduce the rate of growth of such emissions.    As a consequence, emissions from Annex I countries have grown at an approximate    rate of 4.7% per year while emissions from Annex I remained relatively stable    (<a href="/img/revistas/asoc/v15n1/13f01.jpg">Figure 1</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">It is therefore    the ultimate objectives of the Convention would not be achieved unless the developing    countries (particularly the large emitters) would also take proactive steps    to reduce their emissions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">What we will do    here is to analyze the significance of "historical emissions" in the last few    decades as they relate to the objectives of the Climate Convention.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>The evolution    of the emissions of developing countries</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">We analyzed the    total contribution of the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions of Annex I and Non-Annex    I (CO<sub>2</sub> emissions represent approximately 70% of all greenhouse gases    emissions).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a href="#f2">Figure    2</a> indicates such contribution in different intervals of time.</font></p>     <p><a name="f2"></a></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/v15n1/13f02.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As can be seen    the amount of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from 1750 up to 1980 doubled in the period    1980-2007.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">If we extrapolate    present CO<sub>2</sub> emissions to 2020 one notices that emissions will double    in the period 1990-2020 compared to emissions from 1750-1990.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">What this means    is that what happened in the past, until 1990, has not contributed overwhelmingly    to total emissions since 1750.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">If one goes a step    further and ask how the "historical emissions" are split among Annex I and non-Annex    I countries one gets the following picture.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/v15n1/13f03.jpg"></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Conclusions</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">It is evident the    growing importance of the share of the contribution of non-Annex I countries    to CO<sub>2</sub> emissions; therefore any "blame" such countries could put    in Annex I countries as the main polluters of the past is very rapidly turning    against them.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The "guilt" attributed    to Annex I countries before 1990 anyway has a very shaky legal foundation because    since ancient antiquity one cannot punish anyone before the nature of the violation    is clearly established (Muller et al, 2007). As far as climate change is concerned,    the year 1990 is the reference before which one really didn't have a clear idea    of the problems related to climate change and the role of anthropogenic activities.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The "historical    responsibilities" argument has been used - somewhat perversely - to justify    the lack of effort of non-Annex I Countries to follow a low carbon trajectory.    The argument is that Annex I countries based their development on the unrestricted    use of fossil fuels and that restrictions imposed now on their use by non- Annex    I countries would hurt their efforts to develop. This is a distorted view of    the reality. With new technologies in existence now - which were not available    many decades ago - non-Annex I countries can develop "leapfrogging" many steps    followed in the past by Annex I countries when they industrialized, incorporating    clean low carbon technologies early in their process of development.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Finally, to be    consistent, "historical responsibilities" should be looked upon as concerning    not only the past but also the future. "Guilt" for past deeds, before 1990,    although not as important as one could think, might be real but there is not    much one can do about them except compensating the people and countries affected,    (such as the low-lying island in the Pacific). In contrast "guilt" resulting    in increasing greenhouse gas emissions - and one knows now quite well their    consequences due to the work of IPCC - can still be reduced by serious mitigation    actions in both Annex I and non-Annex I countries.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The Copenhagen    Accord adopted in December 2009 has no mention of historical responsibilities.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CAIT (Climate Analysis    Indicators Tools) 2010. Available at: <a href="http://cait.wri.org/" target="_blank">http://cait.wri.org/</a>.    Access on February 22<sup>nd</sup> 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000056&pid=S1414-753X201200010001300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CDIAC (Carbon Dioxide    Information Analysis Center) 2010. Available at: <a href="http://cdiac.ornl.gov/trends/emis/meth_reg.html" target="_blank">http://cdiac.ornl.gov/trends/emis/meth_reg.html</a>.    Access on February 23<sup>rd</sup> 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000058&pid=S1414-753X201200010001300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">MULLER, B.; HOHNE,    N.; ELLERMANN, C. "Differentiating (Historic) Responsibilities for Climate Change"    - Summary report. Oxford Institute for Energy Studies. 2007. Available at: <a href="http://www.oxfordclimatepolicy.org/publications/DifferentiatingResponsibility.pdf" target="_blank">http://www.oxfordclimatepolicy.org/publications/DifferentiatingResponsibility.pdf</a></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000060&pid=S1414-753X201200010001300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Copenhagen Accord    (Decision-/CP.15), 2009. Available at: <a href="http://unfccc.int/files/meetings/cop_15/application/pdf/cop15_cph_auv.pdf" target="_blank">http://unfccc.int/files/meetings/cop_15/application/pdf/cop15_cph_auv.pdf</a></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000061&pid=S1414-753X201200010001300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">United Nations    Framework Convention on Climate Change, 1992. Available at: <a href="http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/convkp/conveng.pdf" target="_blank">http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/convkp/conveng.pdf</a></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000062&pid=S1414-753X201200010001300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Submetido em 20/04/2012    <br>   Aprovado em 04/05/2012</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Climate Analysis Indicators Tools</collab>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center</collab>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MULLER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOHNE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[N.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ELLERMANN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA["Differentiating (Historic) Responsibilities for Climate Change": Summary report]]></source>
<year>2007</year>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Oxford Institute for Energy Studies]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>Copenhagen Accord</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Decision-/CP.15]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<edition>http://unfccc.int/files/meetings/cop_15/application/pdf/cop15_cph_auv.pdf</edition>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<source><![CDATA[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
