<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1414-753X</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Ambiente & Sociedade]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Ambient. soc.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1414-753X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ANPPAS - Revista Ambiente e Sociedade]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1414-753X2002000100003</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1414-753X2002000100003</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Brazilian environmental sociology: a provisional review]]></article-title>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Sociologia ambiental brasileira: um levantamento provisório]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ferreira]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Leila da Costa]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Campinas State University Department of Sociology ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2002</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2002</year>
</pub-date>
<numero>10</numero>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>43</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100003&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[The article aims firstly at the reconstitution and analysis of history within the scope of international environmental sociology situated in the context of contemporary sociology. It also discusses - from the standpoint of literature (Buttel, Dunlap, Hanning, among others) - its theoretical-methodological and institutional aspects as well in order to understand the obstacles encountered to legitimate and consolidate a set of problems which, until recently, were not dealt with by social sciences. Secondly, it analyses the Brazilian case. Environmental sociology in Brazil is strongly influenced by American empirical sociology, the precursor of the institutionalization process for the themes. On the other hand, further analysis of this case is relevant to understand the relationship between the scientific sphere, and the creation of environmental policies and social movements.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[Primeiramente o artigo busca a reconstituição e análise histórica inerente ao escopo da sociologia ambiental internacional no contexto da sociologia contemporânea. Ele também discute - a partir da literatura (Buttel, Dunlap, Hanning, entre outros) - seus aspectos teórico-metodológicos e institucionais de modo a compreender os obstáculos encontrados para se legitimar e consolidar um conjunto de problemas os quais, até recentemente, não eram trabalhados pelas Ciências Sociais. No segundo momento o artigo analisa o caso brasileiro. A sociologia ambiental no Brasil é fortemente influenciada pela sociologia empírica americana, a precursora no processo de institucionalização desses temas. Por outro lado, uma análise posterior sobre esse caso é relevante para se compreender a relação entre a esfera científica, a implementação de políticas ambientais e os movimentos sociais.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Environmental Sociology]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[intellectual production]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Brazil]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Sociologia ambiental]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[produção intelectual]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Brasil]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ARTIGOS    / ARTICLES</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="4"><b><a name="top50"></a>Brazilian    environmental sociology: a provisional review<font size="3"><a href="#back50"><sup>*</sup></a></font></b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>Sociologia    ambiental brasileira: um levantamento provis&oacute;rio</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Leila    da Costa Ferreira</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Department    of Sociology, Campinas State University. <a href="mailto:leilacferreira@uol.com.br">leilacferreira@uol.com.br</a></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ABSTRACT</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The article    aims firstly at the reconstitution and analysis of history within the scope    of international environmental sociology situated in the context of contemporary    sociology. It also discusses &#151; from the standpoint of literature (Buttel,    Dunlap, Hanning, among others) &#151; its theoretical-methodological and institutional    aspects as well in order to understand the obstacles encountered to legitimate    and consolidate a set of problems which, until recently, were not dealt with    by social sciences.    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Secondly,    it analyses the Brazilian case. Environmental sociology in Brazil is strongly    influenced by American empirical sociology, the precursor of the institutionalization    process for the themes. On the other hand, further analysis of this case is    relevant to understand the relationship between the scientific sphere, and the    creation of environmental policies and social movements.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Key words:</b>    Environmental Sociology, intellectual production, Brazil</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">RESUMO</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Primeiramente    o artigo busca a reconstitui&ccedil;&atilde;o e an&aacute;lise hist&oacute;rica    inerente ao escopo da sociologia ambiental internacional no contexto da sociologia    contempor&acirc;nea. Ele tamb&eacute;m discute - a partir da literatura (Buttel,    Dunlap, Hanning, entre outros) - seus aspectos te&oacute;rico-metodol&oacute;gicos    e institucionais de modo a compreender os obst&aacute;culos encontrados para    se legitimar e consolidar um conjunto de problemas os quais, at&eacute; recentemente,    n&atilde;o eram trabalhados pelas Ci&ecirc;ncias Sociais.    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">No    segundo momento o artigo analisa o caso brasileiro. A sociologia ambiental no    Brasil &eacute; fortemente influenciada pela sociologia emp&iacute;rica americana,    a precursora no processo de institucionaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o desses temas.    Por outro lado, uma an&aacute;lise posterior sobre esse caso &eacute; relevante    para se compreender a rela&ccedil;&atilde;o entre a esfera cient&iacute;fica,    a implementa&ccedil;&atilde;o de pol&iacute;ticas ambientais e os movimentos    sociais.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Palavras-chave:</b>    Sociologia ambiental, produ&ccedil;&atilde;o intelectual, Brasil.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Scientific    research concerning the interrelationship between society and environment is    rapidly evolving all over the world. The growing proliferation of contributions    from the most diverse areas of specialization seems to confirm this impression.    What is usually called "environmental problems" became important concerns, although    restricted to certain groups.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The social    sciences, for example, attribute to society the dominant paradigm of faith in    progress and human rationality. Marx (1980) as well as Durkheim (1995) see the    modern era as turbulent, but both believe that the possible benefits provided    by the modern era overcome its negative aspects. Weber (1982) was the most pessimistic    of the three, seeing the modern world as a paradox where material progress was    obtained only at the cost of bureaucratic expansion that crushed creativity    and individual autonomy. However, not even he completely anticipated how extensive    the dark side of modernity would become.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Both natural    and social scientists built their theories on two basic premises: the Newtonian    model and Cartesian dualism (GULBENKIAN COMISSION, 1996). The intellectual history    of the XIXth. century is, above all, characterized by the process of diversification    and professionalization of knowledge, that is, the creation of permanent institutional    structures destined both to produce a new knowledge and to reproduce the producers    of this knowledge.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">According    to the Gulbenkian Commission (1996), the creation of multiple disciplines in    the social sciences was part of a global effort undertaken in the XIXth. century    to guarantee and advance "objective" knowledge about "reality" based on empirical    discoveries (understood as in opposition to the work of "speculation"). The    idea was to apprehend the truth instead of inventing or intuiting it. The process    of institutionalizing this type of intellectual activity was neither simple    nor linear. However, we can affirm that this whole process was, to a large extent,    a "success" story. The establishment of disciplinary structures generated investigation    structures of analysis and training that were not only productive and viable,    but also generated a significant bibliography today regarded as the legacy of    contemporary social sciences.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Yet, at    the precise moment in which, for the first time, the institutional structures    of social sciences seemed finally in place and clearly defined, the practice    of social scientists began to change after the Second World War. Sociologists    paved the way for others transforming "political sociology" and "economic sociology",    as early as in the 1950's, in important sub-groups within the discipline.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Political    scientists followed and everyone broadened their concerns beyond the more traditional    themes.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The post    war years saw a redefinition of the objective in a manner that integrated all    the social processes with political implication or intentions: pressure groups,    protest movements, community organizations, among others.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">It was in    this context that research emerged - studies that today we call environmental    sociology. This initiative to introduce environmental debate and the environmental    dimension within sociology may have happened not only as a consequence of this    process, but also as a response to the intensification of negative socio-environmental    impacts due to economic expansion or to the explosive social reaction against    the evidence of degradation. However, it is noteworthy that this environmental    approach was developed late in sociology, well after the pioneering treatment    in biology, ecology, economics, demography and geography, among others.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">At the same    time, it is also surprising that in a short time during the last decade, the    concept of risk –intrinsically linked to environmental concerns – came to occupy    a central place in social theory (GUIVANT, 1998). According to the author, two    important contemporary social theorists, Ulrich Beck (1992 and 1999) and Anthony    Giddens (1991), contributed to this by considering risks, especially environmental    and technological risks of serious consequences, as the key to understanding    the characteristics, limits and transformations of the historical project of    modernity.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Nevertheless,    environmental sociology already is in some places , particularly in the United    States, a reasonably productive area that certainly influenced the questions    posed by contemporary sociology, which, in turn, influenced the area.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Given this,    some serious questions arise: Why did sociology delay in taking a position in    relation to the environmental problem? Why had this theme gained such strength    at the end of the XXth. century? Finally, other dilemmas arise along with this    new area of the Social Sciences: From what viewpoint must we consider it? What    are the paradigms that influence it? What are its theoretical and methodological    limits?</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Keeping    these dilemmas in mind, the present work intends to be a preliminary review    of the international literature and a specific commentary on Brazilian environmental    sociology.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>ENVIRONMENTAL    SOCIOLOGY: RISE AND INSTITUTIONALIZATION</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Environmental    sociology, as scientific and academic production, emerged along with the social    protest movements that arose in the early 1960's and the evidence of the emergency    situation caused by the degradation of natural resources and industrial development.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The birth    of the environmental movement in the 1960's surprised sociologists, who, at    that time, did not have a theoretical model or tradition of empirical research    to guide their understanding of the relation between society and nature (VIOLA    &amp; LEIS, 1992).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The pioneers    of classical sociology, Durkheim, Marx and Weber had tangentially touched upon    the question; beyond this, only isolated works appeared occasionally in the    area of rural sociology, without promoting a substantial accumulation of knowledge    that would have permitted the creation of a theoretical field.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Hannigan    (1997) believes there are two explanations for the fact that sociologists marginalized    the environmental question in their theoretical work. One of these refers to    the weaknesses inherent in geographical and biological determinism and its conservative    vision in understanding change and social conflict; the other alludes to the    prevalent thinking that, in the middle of the XXth. century, emphasized the    literature of the sociology of modernization. The belief in progress and in    human ability to discover the causes and solutions for all problems would be    responsible for the entrance of countries to modernity.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">What is    now identified as "environmental concern" was seen as backward and an obstacle    to development, to progress. Certainly, there were critics of the development    paradigm, the Marxist sociologists; but, even so, they tended to see the environmental    problem as a detour from the more crucial questions of humanism.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Giuliani    (1998) points out that sociology was born marked by the thinking that makes    society independent from nature, a concept seen as a conquest of modernity.    Buttel (1992) points out the ambiguous relationship of sociology, in its developmental    stage, with the natural sciences. If, on one side, sociological thinking was    influenced by concepts coming from the natural sciences, on the other, the real    need to legitimate the social sciences demanded a reaction against the simplicity    of explanations surrounding biological and geographic determinism, as was seen    earlier.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In this    context, although in a differentiated form and principally since the 1960's,    groups of sociologists began to give importance to the environmental problem    and perceive its relevance and range, which contributed to its inclusion in    the agenda of governments, international organizations, social movements and    business sectors around the world. It became evident that the environmental    question was not just one more passing fad, nor a dramatization by militants    or radical scientists, such as the so-called radical ecologists or political    ecologists who initiated work in the area in the 1960's (FERREIRA, 1992).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Environmental    sociology assumes a significant position in studying the divergence and conflict    about nature (understood here, in its broadest sense, as both the natural and    constructed) and the causes and extent of environmental problems among the diverse    actors involved (BUTTEL, 1987; REDCLIFT &amp; WOODGATE, 1996; HANNINGAN, 1997;    CATTON &amp; DUNLAP, 1998).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">This type    of orientation developed especially in the mid 1980's contributing to theoretical    revitalization and to a greater projection within the discipline process motivated,    in part, by the growth of environmental movements and the increasing concern    for the global effects of environmental risks (MOL, 1993; VIOLA, 1997). The    previous period, between the 1970's and the beginning of the 1980's, was characterized    by scattered works, but of no less importance.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">According    to Buttel (2000), the American environmental sociology, for example, that dominated    the international field until the end of the 1980's and the beginning of the    1990's, has various deficiencies. The American environmental sociological theory    originally developed as a reaction to the lack of attention sociology paid to    biophysical phenomena; thus, it emphasized the strong, if not intrinsic, tendencies    of modern societies to degrade the environment and tended to minimize the theorization    of the processes to improve the environment. But, in a somewhat incoherent manner,    the dominant environmental sociology was also inclined to see that these tendencies    of environmental degradation could be reversed if the environmental movement    joined forces adequately. The environmental movement is also seen as essentially    the only significant mechanism to achieve solutions for environmental problems,    being, moreover, a progressive force sui generis.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The culture    of American environmental sociology tended, therefore, to simplify the processes    of environmental mobilization and to exaggerate the coherence of environmentalism.    Finally, the author points out, the principal works of American sociology tended    to a reductive vision of environmental policies, whether seeing the formation    of state environmental policies in relatively benign terms or emphasizing the    inexorable forces that compel state policy to exacerbate environmental degradation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">On the other    hand Buttel (2000) comments on some recent tendencies in the environmental sociological    culture – particularly pointing to theories on post-modernity in the center    of general sociology and the application of a particular post-modernity ("reflexive    modernization") to the problems of the relationship between society and environment.    For the author, the theory of Beck (1992) about a "risk society" and the works    of Spaargaren (1996) and Mol (1995) are the most visible contributions to environmental    sociology anchored in the notion of reflexive modernization. Also, social constructivists    and discourse analysts, such as Hannigan (1997) and Yearley (1996), have presented    interpretative sociologies of environmental risks and of environmental policy    that are largely consistent with the frame of reference of reflexive modernization.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The notion    of reflexivity – that citizen-actors are not just passive recipients of the    overarching forces of modernity and that modernization can "turn backward",    as a way of facing the problems it created – has contributed to sociology in    general and to environmental sociology in particular.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>THE INTELLECTUAL    CLIMATE AND THE POLITICAL-INSTITUTIONAL TRAJECTORY</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">It is clear    that the process of institutionalizing environmental sociology, within sociology,    was not homogeneous. It can be subdivided in terms of the political and cultural    happenings of the time, as well as of the actual intellectual development of    the "state of the art". In this way, on one hand, we can distinguish "schools",    or dynamic centers of teaching, research and debate in different parts of the    world. Occasionally, the dynamic center consists of a few professors, or only    one sociologist, who deal with the environmental question; other times, it is    a complex that includes departments, national and international professors,    scientific debate, the teaching of theories, techniques and research.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">It is worth    noting that the period spanning from the 1960's to the mid 1980's, in which    intellectual production was more systematic and institutionalized, was profoundly    influenced by the cultural climate of the 1960's New social movements, a counter    culture and a radical criticism of industrialism and the military industrial    complex by the new social movements marked a drastic change in the cultural    and university climate in various parts of the planet, including the United    States, accentuating the need to investigate the environmental problem.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The political-institutional    trajectory of the discipline in the United States, a pioneer in institutionalizing    environmental sociology, began in the 1970's. It is worth noting again that    there was, already in the 1960's in the United States and Europe, a non-systematic    but interesting production that approached the problems from a more radical    perspective. The so-called "radical ecologists" or "political ecologists" certainly    influenced future work<b>.</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The initial    concern focused on more preservationist aspects of the environmental question,    that gradually gained new profiles with the energy crisis that began in 1973    and the accompanying increase in oil prices. This energy crisis coincided with    the release, by the Club of Rome, of the report "Limits to Growth" that alerted    in an alarming tone to the possibility of the depletion of natural resources    and of planetary environmental catastrophe, if the expectations of economic    growth remained constant (FERREIRA, 1992). The publication of the report generated    intense debates about the question of scarcity and the prevalent model of growth.    In spite of the innumerable criticisms it received during this period, there    was a proliferation of research initiatives concerning environmental movements,    energy and natural resources, analyses of environmental policies, alternate    proposals to growth and a heated and polemical debate about the population question    (HOGAN, 2000).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">On the other    hand, the section of environmental sociology of the American Sociological Association    grew from 290 members in 1976 to 321 in 1979, attracting researchers with different    interests. According to Dunlap (1997), in the mid 1970's, the three national    sociological associations in the United States (the Rural Sociological Association,    the Society for the Study of Social Problems, and the American Sociological    Association) started groups and sessions of environmental sociology, as well    as treating the theme in a number of other sessions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">According    to the author, the question of the scarcity of natural resources, in spite of    being widely divulged and debated, was not duly assimilated by the American    political culture oriented by the myth of unlimited growth. In this sense, the    Reagan era represented an explicit rejection of the idea of limits, and the    climate of the American dream of growth and prosperity interrupted the nightmare    of scarcity (VIG &amp; KRAFT, 1998). Obviously this process interfered in the    work done in this field that, according to Dunlap (1997), suffered a decline    in the decade of 1980. According to the author, the section of environmental    sociology was reduced to less than 300 members in 1980; few new articles were    written and none were published in the principal sociological journals.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">However,    accidents involving nuclear power plants and toxic contamination of great proportions,    as the cases of Three Mile Island (1979), Love Canal, Bhopal (1984) and Chernobyl    (1986), ignited public and scientific debate about the question of risks in    contemporary societies. Consequently, the question of citizenship and quality    of life gained new impulse at that moment (DUNLAP, 1997; HOGAN, 1992). A change    in the scale of environmental problems, which shifted from a local to a global    level, began during this period, transforming the frequency of environmental    problems and accidents. The actual nature of the problems made them more difficult    to predict and understand (DUNLAP, 1993; FERREIRA &amp; VIOLA, 1996).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In fact,    the end of the 1980's saw a favorable climate in the process of consolidation    of the area at an international level. Various data confirm this; once again    there was an increase in the members of the ASA section at the turn of the decade,    reaching 400 members in 1993. The volume of published texts and increased student    interest in courses addressing this problem also confirms this. Another significant    sign was the growing international attention dedicated to the area, and the    formation of a work group on environment and society in 1990 in the International    Association of Sociology, ISA, not to mention the impact of Rio-92 (DUNLAP,    1997).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In respect    to theoretical-methodological aspects, Buttel (1996) writes that the trajectory    of environmental sociology could be synthesized in three distinct periods: its    formation from the combination and contributions of other specific sociologies;    the phase of constituting its own theoretical nucleus with a more consensual    profile, and the diversification and greater incorporation in the theoretical    body of general sociology.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In relation    to the formation period, the author notes that Rural Sociology was the pioneer    in contributing to the area. He points out, however, that other specific sociologies    also participated in this process, such as the sociology of communities, development    sociology, urban sociology and the theory of social movements. In a certain    degree, environmental sociology did not emerge as a new discipline, but within    already existing disciplines, trying, on one hand, to fill the theoretical lacuna    of the classical tradition in relation to environmental questions, and, on the    other, to create an institutional locus for the development of a new theme.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">With respect    to the theoretical lacuna, Buttel (1996) considers that the tendency of classical    sociology created theories that implicitly assume societies and human groups    as being independent or isolated from the biophysical processes. For him, sociology,    seeking to liberate itself from the social thinking of reductionism, prejudices    and conservative vision of the beginnings of human ecology, exaggerated in promoting    the separation between the social process and the natural world. Catton &amp;    Dunlap (1998) are more emphatic in criticizing the resistance of sociology to    environmental questions, highlighting the socio-cultural context of the formation    of sociology, as well as its analytical paradigms. They argue that sociology    was profoundly influenced by a Western anthropocentric culture. This vision    of the world, in turn, was historically accentuated by convergent processes    of technical-scientific development and accumulation of wealth, favored by colonial    expansion that resulted in the industrial revolution, the strengthening of the    idea of progress and the process of westernizing the rest of the world.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The following    phase, that of the constitution of a theoretical core, was unified around the    works of environmental sociologists, such as Catton, Dunlap, Schnaiberg, Buttel,    Redclift, Harteley, Chapman, Yearley, Hannigan, among others, who stood out    in theoretical work after the 1970's. These authors, despite the differences    of their analytical perspectives, emphasized the materialist and realist character    of the environmental crisis, offering explicit criticisms of the tendencies    of modern industrial societies, without disregarding the importance of the cultural    dimension of this process. They strongly criticized the unsustainabilityof modern    societies which depended on a model of producing, consuming, and discarding    that depleted natural resources more rapidly than the capacity for regeneration.    They believed, therefore, that the present crisis should favor a change in the    paradigm, as much in society as in sociology.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The third    phase in the intellectual trajectory of environmental sociology, which is clearly    explicit at the turn of the 1980's, is characterized by greater theoretical    diversity and by a certain incorporation of classical sociological theory.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Particularly    important are the influences from contemporary sociology, in the sense of a    shift that occurs from explanations based on materialism and structuralism to    cultural and subjective perspectives as well as to astrong influence of daily    life sociology. This theoretical shift strongly contributed to the increased    receptivity of the question as a socially relevant phenomenon. It is possible    to see, from this moment, the contributions of outstanding sociologists who    emphasize the importance of the question within the context of societies with    high modernity, as is the case of Beck (1992), Giddens (1991), Touraine (1989)    Castells (1999), among others.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">For Hannigan    (1997), the new analytical perspective began to emphasize social, political    and cultural processes in which environmental conditions are defined as being    acceptable or not. In this sense, an "environmental problem" is a socially constructed    aspect seen as more relevant than the actual work of evaluating whether the    complaints are valid or not. Environmental problems would be similar to other    social problems and the action of the different actors would be the object of    the principal analysis.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>ENVIRONMENTAL    SOCIOLOGY IN BRAZIL</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In Brazil,    the process of institutionalizing environmental sociology finds itself at an    intermediate phase compared to international experiences. The best example of    organization in the area can be analyzed through the Work Group "Ecology, Politics    and Society" (Grupo de Trabalho "Ecologia, Politica e Sociedade") of the National    Association of Graduate Work and Research in Social Sciences (ANPOCS) (VIEIRA,    1992; FERREIRA &amp; VIOLA, 1996; DRUMMOND &amp; SCHROEDER, 1998).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">This group    met for the first time at ANPOCS in 1986, when the environmental question was    still treated in an incipient way in Brazilian social sciences and brought together    a small group of intellectuals. Since then, the environmental question acquired    relevance in the international scientific community, as we saw earlier, and    this was reflected in the local scientific community, as we will see in this    paper.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In 1992,    with the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development in Rio de    Janeiro, the working group opted to give priority to the discussion so as to    deepen a critical vision in relation to the Brazilian context. This discussion    culminated in the publication of the book <i>Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento    Sustent&aacute;vel</i>, organized by Daniel Hogan &amp; Paulo Vieira, which    certainly reflected the "moment" experienced by the group that already represented    a certain regional diversity.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Since then,    various intellectuals connected with the group completed doctoral and post-doctoral    studies overseas, preferentially, but not exclusively, in the United States,    France and England. These international contacts are reflected in the production    in the area.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the mid    1990's, the thematic concern of the ANPOCS Work Group was the question of globalization,    obviously influenced by the "climate of the social sciences" in the new century    (FERREIRA, 1997), once again with an emphasis on the Brazilian context. That    same year the book <i>Incerteza de Sustentabilidade na Globaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o</i>,    organized by Leila Ferreira &amp; Eduardo Viola was published.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Today, environmental    sociology, political science of environment, anthropological and demographic    studies about the theme have been consolidated in various Brazilian universities,    as we will see. The number of dissertations, theses, books and works published    reflects the degree of interest that this question has acquired. Along with    this, there are other indicators of the degree of institutionalization of the    theme within Brazilian social sciences, such as the publication of the journal    Revista Ambiente e Sociedade, financed by FAPESP and CNPq; as well as the fact    that the environmental question was a predominant theme in various national    congresses, such as the Brazilian Anthropological Association (ABA) in the year    2000 and the International Congress of Rural Sociology that was held in Rio    de Janeiro in the same year.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">However,    similar to what happened to the ASA group in the United States, after 1998,    the National Association of Post Graduation did not accept the new proposal    of the environmental group that has not participated in ANPOCS since then. Yet    some members continue their connection with the association through forums and    round table discussions. This does not imply a decline of interest in the area    since intellectuals and students connected with the Work Group have met in other    academic forums, such as the Brazilian Sociological Society (SBS), the Latin    American Studies Association (LASA), and the International Sociological Association    (ISA). Moreover, it is worth mentioning that a National Association of Graduate    Study and Research in Environment and Society (ANPPAS) was formed in September    2000.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">A work that    tries to reflect on the "state of the art" of Brazilian environmental sociology    faces a series of dilemmas. They are not questions of the type "how did Brazilian    environmental sociology institutionalize itself purely and simply". They are    rather situated on two levels: in the first place, the concern for the world    of ideas - how has this area developed in the last decades?, what are the main    concerns?, what are the principal themes treated and how are they included in    the debate of contemporary Brazilian social science? That is, there is an explicit    theoretical concern: if the recent changes led to the affirmation of the existence    of a global and complex society, for instance: what stance has environmental    sociology taken in regard to this theme?</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The discussion    here is only exploratory. The themes are complex and controversial. For these    reasons, it should not be considered more than a provisional exploration.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the second    place, it is worth making a final observation to explain a basic aspect of the    sociology of sociological production on the environmental theme. It is undeniable    that there exists a certain correspondence between a given theory and the empirical    question which better fits its concepts. That is, the "world vision" inherent    in a sociological theory favors the selection of certain configurations of reality.    Thus, on one hand, it is certain that an area finds itself strongly influenced    by American empirical sociology, precursor in the process of institutionalizing    the theme. On the other hand, it is necessary to take into consideration the    specificities of the process in the case of Latin America, more specifically,    those of Brazil and, consequently, we believe that the detailed analysis of    the Brazilian case is relevant to understand the relationship between the scientific    field, the environmental policy-making and the social movements.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>THE INTERNALIZATION    OF THE ENVIRONMENTAL QUESTION IN GRADUATE PROGRAMS IN BRAZIL</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The following    analysis of the principal graduate programs in the areas of sociology, social    sciences and new interdisciplinary programs tries to map the production of dissertations    and theses in the area of environmental sociology in Brazil.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Four master's    dissertations and eight doctoral theses have been completed under the Sociology    Program of the University of S&atilde;o Paulo (USP) related to the themes of    environment and society. The program has a total of 284 master's theses and    316 doctoral theses defended. These data correspond to the period 1958 - 2000.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Concerning    work on the master's level, it can be noted that the years vary from 1972 (DIEGUES),    1980 (TEIXEIRA), 1996 (SILVA) to 1997 (SEKIGUCHI). When we compare the theses    from the Graduate Program of the Philosophy and Human Science Institute of the    State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), we find a greater incidence of works    in the area beginning in the 1980's (1983 and 1986), but especially in the 1990's    ( most of the dissertations were presented between 1991 and 1998).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Considering    these data, we can risk a first conclusion: the consolidation of this area as    an academic career opportunity, at least in the above-mentioned universities    - USP and UNICAMP- occurred mainly in the 90's. The theses produced prior to    these years can be considered as "the vanguard". Actually, it is these avant-garde    intellectuals who inaugurated this research area in the mentioned universities.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the case    of Unicamp, the Master's Program in Sociology has a research field called "Environment,    technology and development". Of the 160 dissertations defended in the program,    20 are in the area of environment and technology, and we may say that other    23 treated the theme in a crosscutting manner focusing in the areas of rural    sociology, urban sociology and theoretical sociology.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the master's    program in Sociology at USP, we must point out that there is no research field    that is strictly linked to the environmental question, as is the case at Unicamp.    However, accompanying the trajectory of some of these intellectuals, here called    the vanguard, who received their degrees at USP, we see that they are, in spite    of not being now members of the Philosophy, Literature and Human Sciences Department,    responsible for the creation of research centers and even an Interdisciplinary    Graduate Program in the area of environment and society.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Although    USP, in its Graduate Program in Sociology, has a relatively low production in    respect to the environmental theme (1.4% for master's and 2.5% for doctoral),    it has an Interdisciplinary Graduate Program in Environmental Science (Procam)    in rapid development and whose work in environmental sociology is wide-ranging.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In relation    to the doctorate, we find a fundamental difference between the two universities:    Unicamp's program is integrated, that is, concerned with the three social science    disciplines – anthropology, political science and sociology; while the doctoral    program at USP is exclusively sociology.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the case    of the program at Unicamp, an area dedicated to the theme entitled "Social Change:    Questions in Environment and Technology" has existed since 1985. Of the 123    theses defended in the program, 16 are directly connected to the area.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Interestingly,    the themes treated at Unicamp, at both the master's and the doctoral level,    are considered "classical" in sociological theory, such as the question of modernity,    the State, democracy, social conflict, development, social movements, and risk,    as well as knowledge, perception and social representation concerning the environment    and globalization. Worthy of note is that the dissertations and doctoral theses    cover a diversity of theoretical approaches, from the more classical perspectives,    the Marxist, the Durkeimian or the Weberian, as well as more contemporary social    theories. More recently, we have seen theses approaching the questions of complexity    and inter-disciplinary studies .</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Regarding    the sociology program at USP, the themes treated were the following: environmental    policy, public policy, conservation of natural resources, development, mining,    cooperatives and environmental awareness. The theoretical-methodological approach    is also, like Unicamp's, diversified.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the case    of Procam (interdisciplinary program), 70 master's theses have been defended,    of which 53 are directly related to the question of environment and society.    The themes are also quite diversified, dealing with questions of conservation,    risk, quality of life, sustainable development, management, environmental education,    environmental law, public policy and social movements. We consider important    to mention here that the theoretical-methodological approaches have sought a    more interdisciplinary perspective that has, in some cases, prejudiced the theoretical    treatment itself; yet these are no less interesting for their thematic diversity,    as well as for their innovative perspective.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The program    of the Federal University of Santa Catarina in Florianopolis has, like that    of UNICAMP, "more tradition" in the area, as much due to the years of dissertation    and theses developments as to the number of professors and researchers who are    dedicated to the theme.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Of the 54    doctoral theses defended in the program, 24 are directly linked to the theme.    The thematic diversity is also very broad, ranging from the question of agriculture,    the urban question, the question of work, of decentralization, of globalization,    risk, sustainability, public policy and social theory. It should be noted here    the theoretical-methodological differentiation of the dissertations and theses,    some of which present an approach more related to systems theory.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the case    of the University of Brasilia, since 1970, 174 dissertations have been defended    in sociology, 11 of these directly linked to the theme and, of 81 doctoral theses    only 4 connected to the area. It is notable that these theses are very recent.    The themes treated on the master's level were social movements, State action,    conservation of natural resources, development, as well as analyses concerning    the Cerrado and Amazonia.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">On the doctoral    level, the themes included non-governmental organizations, Agenda 21, Amazonia    and environmental policy. In respect to the theoretical approach, these also    are of a more classical and contemporary perspective of social science.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">There also    exists in Brasilia a Graduate Program in Sustainable Development, where 24 dissertations    have been defended, all related to the perspective of environment and society.    The themes included environmental management, perception, administration, family    agriculture, environmental impact, environmental policy, residues and sustainability.    Here, too, the perspective strives to be interdisciplinary in the dissertations    and theses.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">At the Federal    University of Para, we visited both the Sociology Department and the Graduate    Program in Sustainable Development in the Humid Tropics, connected to the Center    of Amazonian Studies (NAEA). Of a total of 130 dissertations defended, 32 were    directly related to the theme as well as the 8 doctoral theses. The themes are    particularly related to the question of regional development (Amazonia), discussing    social movements, migration, gender, poverty, the State, national frontiers    and urbanization. The approach of the dissertations and theses to the environmental    question was based on an interdisciplinary perspective.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The theme    was best treated at the Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), in their    Program of Social Ecology, where there are 24 master's theses defended, of which    8 approach the question from the environmental social sciences. The research    topics were business, environmental education, consumption, residues, sustainable    development and culture and environment.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the case    of the Sociology Program at the Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, we    found 5 dissertations connected with the theme, treating agrarian colonization,    social movements and the agrarian question.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The Joaquim    Nabuco Foundation in Recife and the National Institute on Amazonian Research    (INPA) are important centers in this area. At the Joaquim Nabuco Foundation    the research projects are linked principally to ecological economics. At INPA,    the majority of studies are focused on socio-economics and the environment.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The Doctoral    Program in Environment at the Federal University of Parana in Curitba has a    strong articulation between the theses and dissertations on the doctoral level    and the research developed by the university professors. Once again the approach    is interdisciplinary.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">We can conclude,    through the analysis of the data collected that there has been a real internalization    of the environmental question from the point of view of sociology in the Graduate    programs in Brazilian universities. Obviously, this internalization differed    from university to university, and demonstrated that the State University of    Campinas and the Federal University of Santa Catarina are the two that stand    out with the greatest production in the area in both quantitative terms and    thematic diversity.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Moreover,    it is important to note that the question was internalized in different ways    in Brazilian universities as regards methodology, and was included in sociology    and social sciences programs, as well as in the so-called interdisciplinary    programs.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>INTELLECTUAL    PRODUCTION</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">As mentioned    previously, we opted to prioritize, in this paper, the production of the ANPOCS    Work Group, through its principal collections, since we believe this group congregates    the principal Brazilian intellectuals connected to the theme.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The book    <i>Ecologia e Politica no Brasil</i> (1987), organized by Jos&eacute; P&aacute;dua,    was one of the first in Brazil to discuss the relationship between ecology and    politics. It compiles the texts that were presented during a seminar in Rio    de Janeiro in 1985, at the time when the discussion of the Green party was beginning    in the country. Since then, we can see that the environmental question penetrated    Brazilian political debate and the local environmental movement began a phase    of growth. Several of its representatives went beyond the frontier of the movement    and entered the political arena, seeking new ways of action. Fernando Gabeira,    Carlos Minc and Liszt Viera are some of the more expressive names in this wave    and appear in the book not only as militants, but also as intellectuals reflecting    on their own work. Together with Jos&eacute; Augusto P&aacute;dua, Eduardo Viola    and Paulo Gonzaga de Carvalho, this reflection gives historical context to the    debate proposed in the book. As academics, the authors trace the origins of    political ecology in Brazil, analyze the trajectory from the beginning of the    ecological movement until the eco-political option in 1986, according to Viola    or, even examine the actions of public agencies related to the control of industrial    pollution. The book, in fact, discusses the ecology question from multiple angles    and emphasizes not only its environmental but also its political and social    aspects.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><i>Ecologia    e Politica Mundial</i> (1991), organized by H&eacute;ctor Leis, was a product    of the Environmental Area of the International Relations Institute of the Pontifical    University of Rio de Janeiro, together with the area of publications of the    Federation of Social Assistance and Education Organs (FASE). It was part of    an ambitious editorial program that intended to link and engage forces of academic    institutions, non-governmental organizations and publishers, with the purpose    of producing a critical reflection on the question that the authors called "the    emerging transnational public space of ecology". Contribution that consciously    desired to serve as a bridge as much in the sense of "South-South" as "North-South",    according to the authors of the time, broadening and extending the network of    cooperation among individuals, organizations and countries.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">As participants    in the book, H&eacute;ctor Leis and Eduardo Viola reflect on global disorder    of the biosphere and the new international order, emphasizing the organizing    role of ecology. H&eacute;ctor Leis also presents a second chapter in which    he analyzes the role of the environmental question as a transforming agent of    the international order. Cl&oacute;vis Brigad&atilde;o's chapter about the Amazonia    and the Antarctic - diagnostics of ecological security, Roberto Guimar&atilde;es    on Latin America and the global agenda on environment, and Jos&eacute; Augusto    P&aacute;dua on the birth of green politics in Brazil complete the collection.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">As the United    Nations Conference on Environment and Development was being held in Rio de Janeiro    in June 1992, the old Work Group "Ecologia, Pol&iacute;tica e Sociedade" of    ANPOCS decided to open priority space for the discussions, seeking to deepen    the criticism of this theme, referent to the Brazilian context, as we saw earlier.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">To the extent    that the official agenda of discussions and resolutions of UNCED fundamentally    contemplated environmental problems of a global nature – greenhouse effect,    changes in the ozone layer, pollution of the oceans, loss of bio-diversity –    the concerns of the members were double. On one side, it was seen that such    problems tend to be connected with public opinion as challenges that are beyond    the specific socio-cultural, economic or political-institutional aspects of    each nation. On the other side, in giving a privileged position to the Amazonian    question, the promoters of the Meeting seem to underestimate the obvious fact    that 90% of the Brazilian population is concentrated in other areas of the country,    undergoing a devastating process of accelerated urbanization. The mobilization    of public opinion in the months preceding the meeting ran the risk of camouflaging    the seriousness of those socio-environmental problems more directly related    to guaranteeing the right to quality of life for Brazilians. In a contradictory    way, the conference could turn into a political regression in the process of    the struggles to create an environmental policy better fitted to Brazilian characteristics.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In this    sense in 1990, the ANPOCS Work Group approved the publishing of a collection    of works that reflected the academic profile of the community of Brazilian Environmental    social sciences and ways to approach some of our socio-environmental challenges,    recovering in the best possible way the ample regional and thematic diversity    involved.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In spite    of the plurality of the theoretical references and methodological focuses within    the set of contributions to the book <i>"Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento    Sustent&aacute;vel"</i> (1992), we can observe a common concern in relating    environment to the social setting and also to explain the specificity of the    socio-environmental problems in developing countries.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the field    of State-society relations analysis, Leila Ferreira and L&uacute;cia Ferreira    start from the assumption that the process of public policy formation cannot    be reduced to a merely structural or functional picture, and they analyze the    universe of the construction of citizenship in a third-world country through    the interactions of different social actors. Eduardo Viola and H&eacute;ctor    Leis offer a synthetic panorama of the dynamics of the Brazilian environmental    movement, exploring the more interesting implications of its multi-sectorial    expansion, as well as identifying new opportunities that arise with the progressive    incorporation of a sustainable development focus.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Paulo Freire    Vieira's text proffers a first look at the repercussions of the environmental    problem in the field of social sciences in Brazil up to 1992. In the group of    texts related to the treatment of empirical analysis, the work by Daniel Hogan    contributed to the demystification of traditional stereotypes in demographic    theory about the role of population pressure as the determinant factor in the    process of environmental degradation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Haroldo    Torres and Donald Sawyer also focus on demographic analysis. The first isolates    the environmental problems generated by accelerated and disordered urbanization    with an emphasis on basic sanitation. Donald Sawyer proposes an evaluation of    the present role and development chances of family-based agricultural, forestry    and pastoral production and extraction – the ecological peasantry – in the Amazon    region in light of socio-environmental pressures of conventional agricultural    practices.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Ricardo    Neder and S&oacute;nia Barbosa return to a discussion about urban-industrial    transformation during the last decade. Based on an evaluation of the negative    socio-environmental impacts in some experiments of industrial deconcentration    in S&atilde;o Paulo State, Neder adopts a socio-political perspective. Barbosa,    in turn, opts for an approach to the concept of quality of life in extremely    degraded areas, based on epidemiological indicators and a discussion of citizenship.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The book    <i>Incertezas de Sustentabilidade na Globaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o"</i> (1996),    organized by Leila Ferreira and Eduardo Viola, begins with the premise: the    existence of global processes that transcend the categories of State, social    class and nation. It has as its hypothesis the emergence of a global society.    According to the organizers, for the Work Group "Ecologia e Sociedade"of ANPOCS,    whose research objective leans toward the biosphere, it necessarily goes beyond    national frontiers; a concern with ecology has no country, its roots are planetary.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">A reflection    about globalization and environment is interesting, because of its breadth and    seems at first sight to distance itself from particularities. In the case of    this book, exactly the opposite happens. The reflection about globalization    and environment is revealed exactly through the quotidian. This is one of the    central threads of the book. We find in its pages, along with more general discussions    about globalization, a set of problems with which we are very familiar – the    question of democratic consolidation in the country, the question of local power,    the problem of water and of different types of pollution, the question of the    quality of life, the question of public space, a discussion about development    and protected areas – the very areas that the ANPOCS Work Group has studied    for more than a decade.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In 1996,    the thematic concern with the process of globalization referred also to the    Brazilian context. However, it went beyond the thematic context and reflected    the consolidation of a national production problem.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the book,    Eduardo Viola analyzes the multi-dimensional aspect of globalization and its    impact on Brazilian environmental policy from 1989 to 1995. H&eacute;ctor Leis    discusses Globalization and democracy post Rio-92 and Octavio Ianni offers a    theoretical reflection about globalization and diversity.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Franz Br&uuml;seke    discusses the question of development from a reflection about "destructuralization".    Leila Ferreira discusses alternatives of sustainability in local Brazilian power,    while Daniel Hogan discusses sustainability in the river basin networks in S&atilde;o    Paulo State.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Pedro Jacobi    approaches the question of environmental perception in urban centers; Mario    Fuks analyzes the legal protection of environment in Rio de Janeiro and Ricardo    Neder the public regulations in Brazil.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the field    of discussions about the protection of natural resources, we have the text by    L&uacute;cia Ferreira about citizenship, social and environmental rights, and    that of Ant&ocirc;nio Carlos Diegues concerning protected natural areas in Brazil.    And finally, Clovis Cavalcanti discusses ecological economics.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">At the moment,    it merits clarifying why these programs and these books were chosen for analysis.    In respect to the graduate programs, we have mapped out the principal centers    where environmental social sciences are focused. As for the books, we opted    to analyze these collections as they reflect the work produced by the old ANPOCS    Work Group, which brought together the largest number of social scientists concerned    with the theme.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In spite    of the plurality of theoretical-methodological references underlying the graduate    programs, as well as the collections analyzed, we can confirm the importance    that the environmental question has acquired for Brazilian social sciences.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>BIBLIOGRAPHY</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">BECK, U.    <b>Risk Society. Towards a New Modernity.</b> Sage Publications. London, 1992<b>.</b></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000131&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    <b>The Reinvention of Politics. Rethinking Modernity in the Global</b> <b>Social    Order</b>. Polity Press.Cambrigde, 1999.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000132&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">BUTTEL,    F. "New directions in environmental sociology<b>".</b> <i>Annual review Sociology</i>    13:465-488, 1987<b>.</b></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000133&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "A sociologia e o meio ambiente: um caminho tortuoso rumo &agrave; ecologia    humana"<b><i>.</i></b> <i>Perspectiva. Revista de Ci&ecirc;ncias Sociais</i><b>.</b>    Vol.15. pp. 69-94, 1992<b>.</b></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000134&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "Environmental and resource sociology: theoretical issues and opportunities    for synthesis". <i>Rural Sociology Society</i>. Volume 61, n.1, 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000135&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "Sociologia ambiental, qualidade ambiental e qualidade de vida: algumas observa&ccedil;&otilde;es    te&oacute;ricas". In: Herculano, S; Porto M. &amp; Freitas, C. (org.). <b>Qualidade    de Vida e Riscos Ambientais</b>. EDUFF. Niter&oacute;i, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000136&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CATTON,    W. &amp; DUNLAP, R. "Environmental sociology: a new paradigm". <i>The American    Sociologist.</i> Vol.13.n.1. february, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000137&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">DUNLAP,    R. "From Environmental to Ecological Problems", In: CALHOUN, C. &amp; RITZER,    G. (org.). <b>Social Problems</b>. MacGraw-Hill. New York, 1993.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000138&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "The evolution of environmental sociology: a brief history and assessment of    American experience". In: REDCLIFT, M. &amp; WOODGATE, G. (eds). <b>The International    Handbook of the environmental sociology</b>. Northampton. Madison, 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000139&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">DURKHEIM,    E. <b>Select Writings</b>. Cambridge University Press. Cambridge, 1995.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000140&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">FERREIRA,    Leila C. <b>A quest&atilde;o ambiental. Sustentabilidade e Pol&iacute;ticas    P&uacute;blicas no Brasil.</b> S&atilde;o paulo, Boitempo, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000141&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    <b>Estado e Ecologia: Novos Dilemas e Desafios ( A pol&iacute;tica ambiental    no Estado de S&atilde;o Paulo)</b>.Tese de Doutoramento. IFCH. Unicamp. Campinas,1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000142&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    (org). <b>A sociologia no Horizonte do S&eacute;culo XXI</b>. S&atilde;o Paulo,    Boitempo, 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000143&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.&amp;    VIOLA, E. (orgs.) <b>Incertezas de Sustentabilidade na</b> <b>Globaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o.</b>    Campinas: Editora da UNICAMP, 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000144&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GIDDENS,    A. <b>As Conseq&uuml;&ecirc;ncias da Modernidade</b>. S&atilde;o Paulo: Unesp,    1991.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000145&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GIULIANI,    G. M. (1998). "Sociologia e ecologia: um di&aacute;logo reconstru&iacute;do".    <i>Revista Dados</i>. vol.41(1), 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000146&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GUIVANT,    J. "Trajet&oacute;rias das an&aacute;lises de risco: da periferia ao centro    da teoria social". In: <i>BIB/ ANPOCS</i>. N.46.2* semester, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000147&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">HANNIGAN,    J. <b>Environmental Sociology- a social constructionist</b> <b>perspective</b>.    Routledge. London and New York, 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000148&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">HOGAN, D.    &amp; VIEIRA, P. <b>Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento</b> <b>Sustent&aacute;vel</b>.    Ed. Unicamp. Campinas, 1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000149&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">HOGAN, D.    <b>S&oacute;cio-demographic dimensions of sustainability. Brazilian perspectives.</b>    Rio de Janeiro, ISA, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000150&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">LEIS, H.    <b>Ecologia e Pol&iacute;tica Mundial.</b> Rio de Janeiro, Vozes, 1991.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000151&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">MARX, K.    <b>O Capital. Cr&iacute;tica da Economia Pol&iacute;tica</b>. Vol.II. Rio de    Janeiro, Civiliza&ccedil;&atilde;o Brasileira, 1980.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000152&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">MOL, A &amp;    SPARGAREN, G. (1993). "Environment, Modernity and Risk society"<b>.</b> <i>International    Sociology</i>. V.8.n.4/431-459, 1993.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000153&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">PAEHLKE,    R. <b>Environmentalism and the Future of Progressive Politics</b>. New Haven:    Yale Ed, 1989.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000154&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">P&Aacute;DUA,    J, A. <b>Ecologia e Pol&iacute;tica no Brasil.</b> Rio de Janeiro<b>,</b> Espa&ccedil;o    e Tempo, 1987.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000155&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">REDCLIFT,    M &amp; WOODGATE, G. (eds) <b>The International Handbook of</b> <b>Environmental    Sociology</b>. Edwaed Elgar. Cheltenham, Uk. Northampton, MA, USA., 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000156&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300026&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">YEARLEY,    S. <b>Sociology, Environmentalism and Globalization</b>. London, Sage, 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000157&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300027&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">VIEIRA,    P. "A problem&aacute;tica ambiental e as ci&ecirc;ncias sociais no Brasil".    In: HOGAN, D. &amp; VIEIRA, P. <b>Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento</b>    <b>Sustent&aacute;vel</b>. Ed. Unicamp. Campinas, 1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000158&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300028&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">VIG, N.    &amp; KRAFT, M. (eds). <b>Environmental Policy in the 1990s.</b> Washington,    D.C., Congressional Quartely Inc. 1990.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000159&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300029&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">VIOLA, E.    &amp; Leis, H "A evolu&ccedil;&atilde;o das pol&iacute;ticas ambientais no Brasil    (1971-1991)". In: HOGAN, D. &amp; VIEIRA, P. <b>Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento</b>    <b>Sustent&aacute;vel</b>. Ed. Unicamp. Campinas, 1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000160&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300030&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "Globaliza&ccedil;&atilde;o, sustentabilidade e governabilidade democr&aacute;tica    no Brasil". In: TRINDADE, A. A. &amp; CASTRO, M. F. (0rg.). <b>A sociedade democr&aacute;tica</b>    <b>no final do s&eacute;culo</b>. Bras&iacute;lia, Paralelo 15, 1997.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000161&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300031&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">WEBER, M<b>.    Ensaios de Sociologia.</b> Rio de Janeiro, Zahar, 1982.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000162&pid=S1414-753X200200010000300032&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>NOTES</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="back50"></a><a href="#top50">*</a>    My appreciation to L&uacute;cia da Costa Ferreira, Eduardo Viola, Roberto Guimar&atilde;es    and Renato Ortiz for reading the first version of this text.</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BECK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[U.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Risk Society: Towards a New Modernity]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sage Publications]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BECK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[U.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The Reinvention of Politics: Rethinking Modernity in the Global Social Order]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambrigde ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Polity Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BUTTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[New directions in environmental sociology]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Annual review Sociology]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<page-range>465-488</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BUTTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[A sociologia e o meio ambiente: um caminho tortuoso rumo à ecologia humana]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Perspectiva. Revista de Ciências Sociais]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<page-range>69-94</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BUTTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Environmental and resource sociology: theoretical issues and opportunities for synthesis]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Rural Sociology Society]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BUTTEL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Sociologia ambiental, qualidade ambiental e qualidade de vida: algumas observações teóricas]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Herculano]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Porto]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Freitas]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Qualidade de Vida e Riscos Ambientais]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Niterói ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[EDUFF]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CATTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DUNLAP]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Environmental sociology: a new paradigm]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The American Sociologist]]></source>
<year>febr</year>
<month>ua</month>
<day>ry</day>
<volume>13</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DUNLAP]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[From Environmental to Ecological Problems]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CALHOUN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RITZER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Social Problems]]></source>
<year>1993</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[MacGraw-Hill]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DUNLAP]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The evolution of environmental sociology: a brief history and assessment of American experience]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[REDCLIFT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WOODGATE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The International Handbook of the environmental sociology]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Northampton ]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DURKHEIM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Select Writings]]></source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FERREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Leila C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[A questão ambiental: Sustentabilidade e Políticas Públicas no Brasil]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Boitempo]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FERREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Leila C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Estado e Ecologia: Novos Dilemas e Desafios: A política ambiental no Estado de São Paulo]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FERREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Leila C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[A sociologia no Horizonte do Século XXI]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São Paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Boitempo]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FERREIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Leila C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIOLA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Incertezas de Sustentabilidade na Globalização]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Campinas ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Editora da UNICAMP]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GIDDENS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[As Conseqüências da Modernidade]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[São Paulo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Unesp]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GIULIANI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Sociologia e ecologia: um diálogo reconstruído]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Revista Dados]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<month>19</month>
<day>98</day>
<volume>41</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GUIVANT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Trajetórias das análises de risco: da periferia ao centro da teoria social]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[BIB/ ANPOCS]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>46</volume>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HANNIGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Environmental Sociology: a social constructionist perspective]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[LondonNew York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Routledge]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento Sustentável]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Campinas ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Unicamp]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Sócio-demographic dimensions of sustainability: Brazilian perspectives]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ISA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LEIS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecologia e Política Mundial]]></source>
<year>1991</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Vozes]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MARX]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[O Capital: Crítica da Economia Política]]></source>
<year>1980</year>
<volume>II</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Civilização Brasileira]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MOL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SPARGAREN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Environment, Modernity and Risk society]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Sociology]]></source>
<year>1993</year>
<month>19</month>
<day>93</day>
<volume>8</volume>
<numero>4</numero>
<issue>4</issue>
<page-range>431-459</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PAEHLKE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Environmentalism and the Future of Progressive Politics]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New Haven ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Yale Ed]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PÁDUA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J, A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecologia e Política no Brasil]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Espaço e Tempo,]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[REDCLIFT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WOODGATE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The International Handbook of Environmental Sociology]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cheltenham^eMANorthampton MA]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Edwaed Elgar]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[YEARLEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Sociology, Environmentalism and Globalization]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sage]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[A problemática ambiental e as ciências sociais no Brasil]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento Sustentável]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Campinas ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Unicamp]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[N.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KRAFT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Environmental Policy in the 1990s]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eD.C. D.C.]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Congressional Quartely Inc.]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIOLA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Leis]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[A evolução das políticas ambientais no Brasil (1971-1991)]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HOGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Dilemas Socioambientais e Desenvolvimento Sustentável]]></source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Campinas ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Unicamp]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B31">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIOLA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Globalização, sustentabilidade e governabilidade democrática no Brasil]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TRINDADE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CASTRO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[A sociedade democrática no final do século]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Brasília ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Paralelo 15]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B32">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WEBER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ensaios de Sociologia]]></source>
<year>1982</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Zahar]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
