<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1414-753X</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Ambiente & Sociedade]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Ambient. soc.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1414-753X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ANPPAS - Revista Ambiente e Sociedade]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1414-753X2002000100007</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1414-753X2002000100007</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The emergence and outcomes of collective action: an institutional and ecosystem approach]]></article-title>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[A emergência e os resultados da ação coletiva: uma abordagem institucional e ecossistêmica]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Futtema]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Célia]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Castro]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Fábio de]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Silva-Forsberg]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Maria Clara]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A03"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Ostrom]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Elinor]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A04"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of São Paulo  ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,State University of Campinas Núcleo de Estudos e Pesquisas Ambientais ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
<aff id="A03">
<institution><![CDATA[,Center for Sustainable Development Studies School for Field Studies ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[Atenas Alajuela]]></addr-line>
<country>Costa Rica</country>
</aff>
<aff id="A04">
<institution><![CDATA[,Indiana University Center for the Study of Institutions, Population, and Environmental Change ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>USA</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2002</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>06</month>
<year>2002</year>
</pub-date>
<numero>10</numero>
<fpage>107</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100007&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100007&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1414-753X2002000100007&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[Participation in collective action is frequently studied through a community-based analysis, with focus on the social features of the participants and on the ecological features of the managed system. This study addresses the importance of scaling down to household level to understand different individual incentives to collaborate (or not) as well as scaling up to the landscape level to evaluate the ecological outcome of the local forms of collective action. A study of a riparian community of 33 households in the Lower Amazon located between two distinct ecosystems -a privately owned upland forest and a communally owned floodplain- reveals that household-based analysis uncovers how heterogeneity within the community leads to different incentives for participation in the communal floodplain, while systemic analysis reveals that interconnection between the managed ecosystem and adjacent ecosystem influences the decisions to participate as well as the ecological outcomes of the collective actions.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[A participação numa ação coletiva é estudada com freqüência por meio de uma análise baseada nas comunidades e enfocada nas características sociais dos participantes e nas características ecológicas do sistema manejado. Este estudo refere-se à importância de se limitar a análise ao nível das famílias para compreender os diferentes incentivos individuais que colaboram (ou não), assim como de se ampliar a análise ao nível da esfera territorial a fim de se avaliar o resultado ecológico das formas locais de ação coletiva. Um estudo feito numa comunidade costeira de 33 famílias na Baixa Amazonia situada entre dois ecosistemas diferentes -uma mata/floresta de propriedade privada situada em terras altas e uma planície pluvial pertencente a uma comunidade- revela que a análise baseada nas famílias mostra que a heterogeneidade dentro da comunidade conduz a diferentes incentivos para participar das atividades na planície pluvial. A análise sistêmica, no entanto, mostra que a interconexão entre o ecosistema manejado e o ecosistema adjacente influi nas decisões para participar assim como nos resultados das ações coletivas.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[collective action]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[common-pool resource]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[ecosystem]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[floodplain]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[forest use]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[heterogeneity]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Lower Amazon]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[property rights]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[social capital]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[upland]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[ação coletiva]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[recursos naturais compartilhados]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[ecosistema]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[planície pluvial]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[uso florestal]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[heterogeneidade]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Baixa Amazônia]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[direitos de propriedade]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[capital social]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[terras altas]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ARTIGOS    / ARTICLES</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="4">The emergence    and outcomes of collective action: an institutional and ecosystem approach</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>A emerg&ecirc;ncia    e os resultados da a&ccedil;&atilde;o coletiva: uma abordagem institucional    e ecossist&ecirc;mica</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">C&eacute;lia    Futtema<SUP>I</sup>; F&aacute;bio de Castro<SUP>II</sup>; Maria Clara Silva-Forsberg<SUP>III</sup>;    Elinor Ostrom<SUP>IV</sup></font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><SUP>I</sup>Programa    de P&oacute;s-Gradua&ccedil;&atilde;o em Ci&ecirc;ncia Ambiental. University    of S&atilde;o Paulo, Brazil    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>II</sup>N&uacute;cleo    de Estudos e Pesquisas Ambientais. State University of Campinas, Brazil    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>III</sup>School    for Field Studies - Center for Sustainable Development Studies, Atenas, Alajuela,    Costa Rica    <br>   </font><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><sup>IV</sup>Center    for the Study of Institutions, Population, and Environmental Change, and the    Workshop in Political Theory and Policy Analysis. Indiana University, USA</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ABSTRACT</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Participation    in collective action is frequently studied through a community-based analysis,    with focus on the social features of the participants and on the ecological    features of the managed system. This study addresses the importance of scaling    down to household level to understand different individual incentives to collaborate    (or not) as well as scaling up to the landscape level to evaluate the ecological    outcome of the local forms of collective action. A study of a riparian community    of 33 households in the Lower Amazon located between two distinct ecosystems    &#151;a privately owned upland forest and a communally owned floodplain&#151;    reveals that household-based analysis uncovers how heterogeneity within the    community leads to different incentives for participation in the communal floodplain,    while systemic analysis reveals that interconnection between the managed ecosystem    and adjacent ecosystem influences the decisions to participate as well as the    ecological outcomes of the collective actions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Key words:</b>    collective action, common-pool resource, ecosystem, floodplain, forest use,    heterogeneity, Lower Amazon, property rights, social capital, upland</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">RESUMO</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">A participa&ccedil;&atilde;o    numa a&ccedil;&atilde;o coletiva &eacute; estudada com freq&uuml;&ecirc;ncia    por meio de uma an&aacute;lise baseada nas comunidades e enfocada nas caracter&iacute;sticas    sociais dos participantes e nas caracter&iacute;sticas ecol&oacute;gicas do    sistema manejado. Este estudo refere-se &agrave; import&acirc;ncia de se limitar    a an&aacute;lise ao n&iacute;vel das fam&iacute;lias para compreender os diferentes    incentivos individuais que colaboram (ou n&atilde;o), assim como de se ampliar    a an&aacute;lise ao n&iacute;vel da esfera territorial a fim de se avaliar o    resultado ecol&oacute;gico das formas locais de a&ccedil;&atilde;o coletiva.    Um estudo feito numa comunidade costeira de 33 fam&iacute;lias na Baixa Amazonia    situada entre dois ecosistemas diferentes &#151;uma mata/floresta de propriedade    privada situada em terras altas e uma plan&iacute;cie pluvial pertencente a    uma comunidade&#151; revela que a an&aacute;lise baseada nas fam&iacute;lias    mostra que a heterogeneidade dentro da comunidade conduz a diferentes incentivos    para participar das atividades na plan&iacute;cie pluvial. A an&aacute;lise    sist&ecirc;mica, no entanto, mostra que a interconex&atilde;o entre o ecosistema    manejado e o ecosistema adjacente influi nas decis&otilde;es para participar    assim como nos resultados das a&ccedil;&otilde;es coletivas.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Palavras    chave:</b> a&ccedil;&atilde;o coletiva, recursos naturais compartilhados , ecosistema,    plan&iacute;cie pluvial, uso florestal, heterogeneidade, Baixa Amaz&ocirc;nia,    direitos de propriedade, capital social, terras altas</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Studies    of collective action often focus on features of the participants and the managed    ecosystem. The social analysis of the participants helps to uncover the factors    driving participation in those local enterprises such as individual interest    to participate (Ostrom, 1998) and ability of the group to organize (McCAY &amp;    JENTOFT, 1998). An ecological analysis of the managed ecosystem helps to unveil    how characteristics of a resource influence the type of appropriation system    that is designed (SCHLAGER et al., 1994) and how the local institutional arrangement    influences the sustainability of common-pool resources (BERKES, 1989; GIBSON    et al., 2000).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In this    paper, we broaden the social and ecological context of the analysis of common-pool    resources by investigating the features of non-participants, in addition to    participants, to explore the factors that cause individuals to refrain from    contributing in collective action. We also analyze the features of the managed    ecosystem and investigate ecological and economic attributes of other closely    related ecological ecosystems to explore their interrelationships. This analysis    aims at addressing the importance of examining the emergence and outcomes of    collective action to common-pool resources by scaling down to household level    and scaling up to landscape level to understand individual incentives to participate    (or refrain) and the ecological outcomes of these local enterprises.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The emergence    of collective action depends, among other factors, on individual incentives    to participate in group-based decisions. Group-based activities demand several    collective tasks. These include coordination of actions, mechanisms of conflict    resolution, and information sharing (OSTROM, 1990). Given these needs, a minimum    organizational skill is fundamental to enable initiation and maintenance of    collective action. Experiencing collaboration in a group is a learning process    of acquiring and exchanging information through a social network that contributes    to enhance coordination skills in that individuals learn or develop commitment,    responsibility, and the importance of task fulfillment (COLEMAN, 1987). In addition,    the development of trust and reciprocity contributes to an enhanced social structure    that strengthens relations among individuals, and thus helps to build social    capital (OSTROM, 1999). The process of building social capital takes time and    energy, and historical events can facilitate or retard this process (DURSTON,    1998; WHITE &amp; RUNGE, 1994). For example, previous participation in organizations    and the experience of beneficial collective outputs are likely to motivate individuals    to join collective action (WHITE, 1996).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In addition    to well-structured social groups and previous individual experience in political    action, particular assets and perceptions directly influence individual choices    toward collaborative behavior. Since those features vary in the group, social    heterogeneity has been a major focus of debate involving collective action.    Despite evidence that socially homogeneous groups can more easily achieve collaboration    (BLAIR, 1996; CARDENAS, 2000; CERNEA, 1989), some authors suggest that heterogeneous    groups, in regard to political power or economic assets, may help to achieve    collective actions but may not ensure equal distribution of benefits (OLSON,    1965; DAVIS &amp; BAILEY, 1996).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Schlager    and Blomquist (1998) point out that problems arising from internal social heterogeneity    can be solved by defining a solid institutional arrangement, separating different    groups of users, or excluding different groups from having rights to a resource.    Recent studies have shown that institutional arrangements may help overcome    structural problems stemming from social differences among collaborators (VARUGHESE    &amp; OSTROM, 2001; GIBSON &amp; KOONTZ, 1997). Likewise, co-management models    have revealed the importance of defining different sets of rules for stakeholders    sharing different assets and interests (PINKERTON, 1994). Exclusion of groups    from having rights to a resource is the most studied situation in regard to    common-pool resources in explaining differences between participants and non-participants(McCAY    &amp; ACHESON, 1987). Cases in which village residents split into different    groups are, however, perhaps the most understudied situations.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Heterogeneity    is also an important component in the outcome of collective action as far as    it is related to ecological features of the landscape, such as the spatial distribution    of a resource and its value. In many cases, participants use multiple ecosystems,    and the collective appropriation from one ecosystem may be related to ecological    and economic features of other ecosystems. Such problems become more pronounced    in areas where local populations are located in highly patchy landscapes such    as between mountains and valleys (NETTING, 1976; GUILLET, 1981), and between    floodplains and uplands (CASTRO, 2000; FUTEMMA, 2000). In those cases, analysis    of the ecological outcomes of collective action should be conducted at the landscape    level to account for the relationship between different ecosystems.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The present    study addresses the issue of emergence and outcomes of collective action in    light of social and ecological heterogeneities. It is focused on a community    located between distinct ecosystems&#151;upland and floodplain&#151;in the Lower    Amazon. Two major collective actions took place at different times within a    20-year period. In the 1970s, all the local residents mobilized in a series    of demonstration petitions and other activities to gain private property rights    to the upland system. Twenty years later, one third of this group self-organized    to gain collective property rights to the adjacent floodplain area. We analyze    the two events&#151;upland privatization and floodplain collectivization&#151;in    an integrative fashion and reveal temporal, social, and spatial relationships    between the two events. The main goal of the paper is to understand: (1) why    only one-third of the households initiated collective action toward the floodplain    ecosystem, and (2) how the collective action in the floodplain related to the    upland forest.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>STUDY    AREA</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The Patos    community is located along the Amazon River and encompasses 33 households with    approximately 200 inhabitants. The community is situated 55 km east of Santar&eacute;m    city, the most important urban center in the Lower Amazon. Transportation to    the city can be achieved by bus (six hours on a dirt road) or by boat (three    hours upstream). Patos residents are non-Indian Amazonian natives who have been    living in the region since the early 1900s. Patos is part of a government-sponsored    settlement project (Gleba Ituqui), along with six other communities. This project    was established in 1987 and covers 16,589 ha (<a href="#figura1">Figure 1</a>).</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="figura1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888f1.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The region    is characterized by an average temperature of 26&deg;C and a high annual precipitation    that is concentrated in March and April (approximately 360 mm each month) but    varies from 1,000 to 3,000 mm (JUNK, 1984; RADAMBRASIL, 1976). The river level    fluctuates within a range of 5 m between the peaks of the dry season (July to    December) and the flood season (January to June). The Patos community is located    on the riverbank, between the upland and the floodplain ecosystems (see <a href="#figura1">Figure    1</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Upland    Ecosystem</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The Patos    upland ecosystem, characterized by moist tropical forest, encompasses 2,300    ha and can be divided into two ecological zones according to land-use: <i>bottomland</i>    zone and <i>plateau</i> zone. The bottomland zone is a 600-hectare strip of    land 1,200 m wide and is located along the river adjacent to the floodplain    ecosystem. The houses are located in this zone. Due to its older land-use history,    it is mostly covered by secondary vegetation, pasture, and cropland. The plateau    zone is separated from the bottomland by a height variation of 200 m, at a 50-degree    slope. The plateau covers 1,700 ha and is dominated by mature forest with numerous    valuable wood species (RADAMBRASIL, 1976). Highly acidic, nutrient-poor soils    (yellow latosol) predominate, interspersed with high-fertility patches of anthropogenic    black soil. Timber has been carried out in a few areas, but cropping and grazing    are the main land-use activity in this zone.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The private    property regime in the upland ecosystem can be traced back through a series    of four landowners to the nineteenth century when private land titles were issued    by the Portuguese Crown to local elite. Patos residents have lived in the area    since the early 1920s. Until 1987, they had informal access to land but no legal    rights. In the mid-1960s, a large ranching company bought land that included    the Patos community. The company planned to clear the area to sell the timber    and cultivate pasture for cattle ranching. To do so, the company tried to expel    the local residents from their land. Patos residents, together with residents    from neighboring communities and support from grassroots organizations and local    NGOs, reacted against them and claimed their legal rights to the land.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">After two    decades of land disputes, the government office in charge of agrarian reform,    the National Institute for Colonization and Agrarian Reform (INCRA), expropriated    the land in 1987 and established a large settlement project in the region. The    upland ecosystem was divided into 28 parcels of approximately 50 ha. Family    units and single males older than 18 years of age were given rights-of-use.    According to INCRA policy, a landholder will gain the right to sell the land    only when a definite land title is issued. Although landholders are currently    only allowed to occupy and use the land, informal land sales have taken place.    Today, one third of the community households have no land titles (see Land Tenure    and Household).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Floodplain    Ecosystem</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The floodplain    ecosystem covers 200 ha and includes two different zones: <i>flooded forest</i>    and <i>natural grassland</i>. The flooded_forest zone is dominated by <i>a&ccedil;ai</i>    palm trees (<i>Euterpe oleracea</i>), which yield a high-calorie fruit used    for consumption and commercialization. This zone is primarily used for extraction    of <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> fruit, and secondarily for extraction of some medicinal    products and timber trees. The natural grassland zone has no woody vegetation    and is dominated by grass species used in grazing areas during the dry season.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The floodplain    ecosystem has undergone changes in ownership as well. Although the floodplain    has been state property since 1934, land transactions still occur in the region    (de Castro, 2000). In Patos, the floodplain area was "owned" privately until    1993 by a series of landholders who allowed local residents free access to its    products. During the early 1990s, the last landholder decided to sell the floodplain    area, and the prospective buyer was a rancher who had just moved to Patos (the    33rd household, see Land Tenure and Household). Local residents believed that    the new rancher would prohibit them from using the floodplain resources.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Their perception    of the threat of losing access to the floodplain drove a few residents to organize    a group to buy the land. All local residents were invited, but only one-third    of the households decided to participate. Each of the 11 households paid US$250    for a share. As a result, access to the floodplain was ensured, but to only    one-third of the community.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Land    Tenure and Household</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">With the    exception of one household, the changes in land tenure have led to the formation    of three household groups since 1993 (see <a href="#tabela1">Table 1</a>): (1)    11 households hold a collective share of the floodplain as well as private parcels    on the upland, Collective-Private Landholders (CP); (2) 11 households hold only    private parcels on the upland, Private-Landholder (PL); and (3) 10 households    own no land, Landless (LL).</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="tabela1"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888t1.gif"></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The CP group    has access to both upland and floodplain, the PL group has access to upland    parcels only, and the LL group has access to upland parcels only with an owner's    permission. The LL households are mostly married children of PL and CP members    who either did not have families or were under age 18 at the time of parcel    distribution. They have their own houses located in areas that average 30 m    by 50 m. Landless households cultivate on relatives' land as sharecroppers or    by favor, or rotate their gardens among different borrowed lots. They are usually    involved in agricultural production, mainly for subsistence, and secondarily    for cash income, and are an important source of labor. The 33rd household refers    to a rancher who is considered an outsider by the community. Despite holding    a private parcel in the Patos upland ecosystem, this household is not categorized    as a PL, because the collective action was in many ways a reaction against this    household (discussed later). Thus, this household will be treated as a separate    actor given its particular position in the present local political-ecological    arena.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Data    Collection</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">We carried    out the household survey during two visits in 1997 and 1998 to evaluate whether    there was a relationship between household attributes and collaborative behavior.    We obtained information on demography, land use, socioeconomy, and land tenure    through structured interviews with 33 households. We focused our analysis on    PL and CP households because they share similar conditions in terms of land    tenure to the upland ecosystem, as well as similar economic opportunities.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In addition,    a vegetation inventory in the upland ecosystem was conducted to examine the    ecological conditions of the upland vegetation vis-&agrave;-vis the collective    action in the floodplain. Based on INCRA's grid map that displays a total of    28 private parcels across the upland forest, ten parcels (50 ha each) were randomly    chosen across PL and CP groups (five parcels each). In each parcel, a 200-meter    baseline along 100 meters on each side was measured in the mature forest and    10 plots of 300 m<sup>2</sup> (15 m x 20 m) lying to either side of the baseline    were randomly selected. We sampled a total of 3 ha distributed in 100 plots.    All trees above 2.5 cm dbh (diameter at breast height) were measured. For this    paper, we considered commercially valuable trees to be only those above 45 cm    dbh, based on Uhl and Vieira (1989).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Finally,    interviews on land use were carried out with the landholders in each of the    surveyed upland parcels to map the distribution of land-cover classes (pasture,    cropfield, and secondary vegetation), and to learn about the land-use history    and the fallow ages.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>FACTORS    AFFECTING THE SECOND COLLECTIVE ACTION</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>The Emergence    of Collective Action</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Because    the collective action in the floodplain was based on the land purchase, we assume    that a household takes into account the expected costs and benefits of obtaining    and investing cash to cooperate with the group. In <a href="#figura2">Figure    2</a>, we represent a decision tree that we hypothesize captures the essence    of a household's reasoning about whether to join others in the purchase of the    floodplain land. In the first-level decision, income may explain why individuals    from the LL group did not participate (see "a" in <a href="#figura2">Figure    2</a>). Because the LL group held no parcels in the upland ecosystem, they did    not have access to farm credit (bank loans) or to timber for selling.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a name="figura2"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888f2.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Assuming    the same level of income for CP and PL groups, we expect that the way each household    measures the economic importance of the floodplain would determine the second-level    decision regarding their interest in joining the collective action (see "b"    in <a href="#figura2">Figure 2</a>).In this regard, those PL households that    did not value the floodplain resources (e.g., natural grassland for grazing)    have little incentive to collaborate.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The importance    of a resource is related to ecological and social features of the household.    These features may influence the third-level decision by constraining households    from exploiting the potential resources from the floodplain ecosystem. In other    words, households that face more favorable ecological and social conditions    for using the floodplain resources are the ones predisposed to collective action    (see "c" in <a href="#figura2">Figure 2</a>). Each decision-making level is    discussed in more detail below.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Sources    of Income</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CP and PL    groups have three main sources of income available to them: farm credit, retirement    income, and timber sales. Since 1989, the State Bank of Amaz&ocirc;nia has provided    farm credit for agropastoral activities. We expect that a larger number of CP    households than PL have borrowed money to invest in cattle and/or to buy a floodplain    share. A moderately strong relationship exists between access to credit and    participation in collective action (tau = 0.64), as 82 percent of CP households    used farm credit compared to only 18 percent among PL households (<a href="#tabela2">Table    2</a>).</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="tabela2"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888t2.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">With regard    to retirement income, women older than 60 and men older than 65 receive a monthly    stipend of about US$120. This contributes a great deal to the household economy    in comparison to a salary of US$60/month for an elementary school teacher, which    is a highly valued profession in the region. Results show that a larger percentage    of CP (64 percent) than PL households (27 percent) have at least one member    who is retired and thus receives a regular income,which indicates that availability    of retirement salary is moderately associated with participation in buying the    floodplain land collectively (tau = 0.37; <a href="#tabela2">Table 2</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Finally,    both PL and CP households have access to woody trees in the upland forest, and    the interviews revealed that almost everyone had sold wood in the past (<a href="#tabela2">Table    2</a>). The price paid per tree is about the same among all households (mean    of US$10 per tree), giving them a similar profit from trading. Taking into account    only data on trading wood, income from timber sales is weakly associated with    the decision to cooperate in a group (tau = 0.19; <a href="#tabela2">Table 2</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In general,    in regard to sources of income, farm credit and retirement income are positively    associated with participation in the floodplain purchase. Given their inability    to gain access to farm credit or retirement income, it is now clear why the    LL households could not afford to join a collective action and chose not to    participate.But these variables do not fully explain why PL households did not    cooperate while the CP group did. PL households could have obtained credit based    on their land, and some of these households had retirement income. The fact    that some PL households did not participate may be related to the way they value    floodplain resources. In order to address this question, two main floodplain    products are analyzed in the next section: natural grassland and a<i>&ccedil;ai</i>    fruit.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Value    of Floodplain Resources</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">We suggest    that local residents take into consideration the economic value of products    such as natural grassland and <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> fruit in the household economy    (subsistence or cash income) when deciding whether or not to participate in    a collective effort.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The first    product, natural grassland, is directly related to cattle raising. Cattle are    used as draft animals or monetary investments and are raised in the upland during    the flood season and in the floodplain during the dry season. A household that    has one or two cows to pull carts will cultivate a small area of grass (usually    in the garden) to feed them. For monetary goals, a larger number of cattle are    raised (between 10 and 15), and a larger area for pasture is necessary. Thus,    we expect that CP households would (1) be more involved in cattle than PL households    because they would value grassland as a grazing area, and (2) have more impact    on plateau forest due to the opening of the pasture. Results show that raising    cattle is moderately related to decisions on collaborating with collective action    (tau = 0.54), since 45 percent of CP households raise cattle for monetary investment,    with a combined total of 61, whereas only one PL household (8 percent) raised    a herd of six (<a href="#tabela2">Table 2</a>). The impact on the plateau forest    is addressed in detail in the next section.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><i>A&ccedil;ai</i>    is an important subsistence and cash product from the floodplain in Santar&eacute;m    county and other parts of the Amazon region (Anderson, 1990; Brond&iacute;zio    and Siqueira, 1997). The fruit can be promptly sold in the local market and    harvesting <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> is a low-cost extractive activity, thus increasing    the interest among all households in collecting it. The establishment of the    collective property in the floodplain generated considerable conflict over the    <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> harvest. In the first year of the collective ownership only    CP members were allowed to harvest <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> for commercial use, which    created strong resentment among PL and LL residents. By the second year, after    harsh conflict, CP members allowed everyone to harvest <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> for    both subsistence and commercial purposes. We cannot reconstruct the differences    in harvesting of <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> fruit prior to the collective action, but    the present data show that there is a moderate strength of association between    <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> harvesting and participation (tau = 0.64). At the time of    the survey, 64 percent of CP households harvested <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> for commercial    purposes, while no household among the PL group did (<a href="#tabela2">Table    2</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Thus, we    find that the value assigned to floodplain resources by Patos residents is positively    associated with participation. The economic importance of floodplain products    helps to explain why Patos residents were attracted toward participation in    a collective action, but it does not fully explain why PL households refrained    from collaborating, since they were potential cattle raisers and <i>a&ccedil;ai</i>    collectors. In the next section, we analyze another set of variables affecting    the decision to participate or not.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>Conditions    for Use of Floodplain Resources</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The exploitation    of consumptive products in the floodplain may depend upon the opportunities    and constraints that are related to conditions for using them. While harvesting    palm fruit is a low-cost extractive activity, engaging in commercial cattle    ranching may depend upon a set of ecological and social conditions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The bottomland    zone presents a favorable environment for cattle raising, because it is close    to the river (good water access) and is dominated by secondary forest (lower    time and labor cost for pasture opening compared to mature forest). In contrast,    the plateau zone is dominated by mature forest and is located further from the    river. Therefore, households whose parcels are solely in the plateau zone face    limitations in raising herds of cattle and would thus have less interest in    obtaining access to the floodplain. We expect that CP households holding parcels    in the bottomland area would be more likely to have participated than those    in the plateau zone. Results confirm that 36 percent of CP households hold parcels    in the bottomland zone in contrast to none among PL households.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In addition    to ecological conditions, commercial cattle raising depends on the household's    ability to carry out ranch-related activities. Cattle raising is typically a    male activity in the Amazon region (Hecht, 1993), and the availability of an    active male labor force plays a key role in a household's decision to engage    in cattle ranching. Because of the CP group's investment in cattle, we expect    that CP households would have more male labor than PL households. Although availability    of labor is moderately related to collaboration with such a collective effort    (tau = 0.41), results show that a larger portion of the CP group (45 percent)    has more than one male in comparison to the PL group (9 percent) (<a href="#tabela2">Table    2</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In sum,    conditions for harvesting <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> in terms of labor force, access    to water, and access to bottomland are positively and moderately associated    with cooperative behavior (<a href="#tabela2">Table 2</a>). Therefore, less    favorable conditions for exploiting the natural grassland faced by the PL households    help to explain why they did not participate in the collective effort.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><i>Prior    Leadership Experience</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Finally,    due to the history of threats to land access, the interest in maintaining access    to the land prompted local leaders to initiate collective action. Leader is    defined as an individual or group of individuals who assume leading roles within    the community in the decision-making process of the group's political agenda.    Currently, the leaders in Patos are four residents who have a history of political    participation and leadership roles in the upland movement. They are in their    60s, Catholic, and belong to traditional families with strong kinship ties.    They have contributed to and are still fulfilling functions within the Patos    political structure, such as coordinator, promoter, and representative of the    community association and of regional unions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Thus, the    CP group is expected to have more leaders than the PL group. The results show    that 45 percent of CP households have a leader, as opposed to none among the    PL group (<a href="#tabela2">Table 2</a>), indicating a moderate relationship    between the presence of a leader and participative behavior (tau = 0.54). The    four households who were leaders in both collective actions are the only CP    members who have no cattle. Their participation is partially explained by their    interest in investing in cattle in the near future. Having participated actively    in the prior collective action made them particularly sensitive to the risk    of losing access to the floodplain resource to an outsider.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><i>Summary    of Empirical Results</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><a href="#tabela3">Table    3</a> presents all the attributes discussed above in one table. This array enables    one to examine the distribution of households that engaged in collectively purchasing    the floodplain land as contrasted with the households that did not. Each variable    is given a score of zero if it is not present. For all variables, except male    labor and cattle, a "1" means that the variable is present. For male labor,    a "1" connotes that up to two male laborers live in the household and a "2"    connotes that three or more are present. For cattle, one or two are coded "1,"    and more than two are coded "2." The coded values were then summed to provide    a rough indication of the overall presence in a household of attributes that    are potentially conducive to economic use of the floodplain land. As one can    see, the households who jointly purchased the floodplain land have higher scores    than those who did not, with few exceptions. The sum of attributes ranged from    9 to 4 for the households who jointly purchased land and from 3 to 1 for those    who did not, with the exception of households 12 and 23. Household 12 joined    the CP group initially but dropped its membership months later due to disagreements    with other members of the CP group. This household has a total of 10 active    individuals who produce manioc flour on a commercial basis, and owns two cows,    adding up to a higher score than the remaining PL households.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><a name="tabela3"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888t3.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The LL group    has been discussed in this paper in terms of how the lack of private rights    to the upland affected their participation in the collective property rights    to the floodplain (<a href="#figura2">Figure 2</a>). Lack of private rights    affects them in terms of financial sources, which reflects in the lowest scores,    from 0 to 2, with the exception of household 23. In that household, the head    individual "betrayed" the upland land movement by working for the large-scale    rancher. As a result of his non-cooperative behavior, the household received    no private parcel when they were allocated. This household now has a work force    of seven, and the head receives a monthly retirement stipend that provides the    household with a stable source of income. All these positive attributes give    the household 23 case a higher score than the rest of the LL group, while its    bad reputation has kept it isolated. In general, households that participated    in the collective action have more of the assumed important variables than PL    and LL households, which means higher material assets among the CP group. In    sum, the higher the score, the higher the chances are for cooperating.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>The Outcome    of Collective Action</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The main    value of the floodplain for the participants is related to <i>a&ccedil;ai</i>    fruit and natural grassland. The low degree of use of those products suggests    that currently no negative impact of human action has taken place in this ecosystem.    The total number of cattle is still small (approximately 60) for the available    grazing area of approximately 200 hectares. By the same token, extraction of    <i>a&ccedil;ai</i> fruit does not involve tree removal, so the flooded forest    has remained relatively unchanged. Thus, the floodplain collective action seems    to have been able to maintain that ecosystem's integrity.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">While collective    action has taken place specifically in the floodplain ecosystem, it has also    affected the upland ecosystem in many ways related to cattle ranching. Extraction    of timber to raise money to buy cattle and increased demand for pastureland    during the early 1990s represent the two major driving factors regarding change    in the forest cover on the upland ecosystem. The logging activity affects the    composition, structure, and regeneration of forest, while the opening of pasture    affects the landscape change. When all species (including trees, saplings, and    seedlings) are considered, the forest parcels of both PL and CP groups have    similar diversity indexes of 4.8 and 4.9, respectively. Yet, when only trees    above 10 cm dbh are considered, the forest areas held by PL households present    a lower richness value in species than CP parcels (<a href="#tabela4">Table    4</a>). It is important to note that higher diversity in land cover is not necessarily    related to ecosystem health. Some studies show that increased numbers of species    and individuals may be related to logging activity, especially among light-demanding    and pioneer species(Carvalho, 1992).</font></p>     <p align="center"><a name="tabela4"></a></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p align="center"><img src="/img/revistas/asoc/n10/16888t4.gif"></p>     <p align="center">&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The high    number of secondary vegetation species in the CP parcels suggests that trees    were probably removed in those parcels, creating more forest gaps than in PL    parcels. Considering only trees above 45 cm dbh, the parcels of CP households    have, on average, a smaller number of commercially valuable species compared    to those of PL households. Logging activity has also affected the vegetation    structure related to the reduction of basal area after logging (see Futemma,    2000) as observed in other Amazonian regions (Lopes et al., 1984; Uhl and Vieira,    1989). While the PL forest parcels display a basal area similar to unlogged    areas, CP forest parcels present traits more similar to logged ones (<a href="#tabela4">Table    4</a>). Additionally, PL parcels present a smaller number of young trees between    10 and 26 cm dbh than CP parcels (<a href="#tabela4">Table 4</a>). This pattern    changes above 26 cm dbh, in that PL parcels have more trees than CP parcels.    These results suggest that there is a larger number of young trees among CP    parcels due to regeneration processes than in PL parcels, as also observed by    Lopes et al. (1984).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Besides    forest structure, landscape changes related to cattle ranching are expected    to be more pronounced in parcels among the CP group, because they have opened    a larger area for pasture in the bottomland. The results of an analysis of remotely    sensed images (reported in Futemma 2000) show that the CP group has not only    opened larger areas of pasture (1 percent of the lot area on average) but also    larger farming areas (4.6 percent of the lot area on average) than the PL group    (0.4 percent for pasture and 2.9 percent for farming). Consequently, CP households    have smaller areas of mature forest and secondary vegetation due to their logging    and cattle ranching activities.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>DISCUSSION</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>The Emergence    of Collective Action</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Patos has    experienced two collective actions in less than 20 years. Both were similar    in some aspects but had different outcomes. Each case involved a group of people    who perceived a threat to their access to and use of resources. The conflict    over the upland ecosystem ended with the privatization of this area, while the    floodplain conflict led local residents to purchase the area and convert it    into a collective property. The entire community cooperated as a group in the    upland conflict (with one exception of an excluded household). The group had    support from external agents, and their access was maintained due to considerable    time and effort of local leaders. In the floodplain ecosystem, only part of    the community participated and the political process was mostly internal. Group    access was maintained by a purchase of the relevant land. Therefore, the cooperation    that occurred in the upland ecosystem demanded mainly political participation,    whereas, in the floodplain, it demanded direct economic investment and political    involvement.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Although    the processes that took place in the upland and floodplain were different events,    they are closely related due to ecological and social connections between the    two ecosystems. The location of Patos between the floodplain and upland ecosystems    provides an ecological opportunity to develop cattle ranching. The provision    of year-round access to pasture&#151;cultivated pasture on the upland during    the flood season and natural pasture on the floodplain during the dry season&#151;lowers    the cost of pasture maintenance. However, the proximity to floodplains and uplands    is not enough for the local population to use the resources unless institutional    arrangements ensure their access to both ecosystems. In Patos, residents were    able to achieve institutional access to the upland ecosystem and, in turn, to    improve access to sources of money. Since the floodplain's collective action    was based on a financial investment derived from use of the upland, the floodplain    collectivization is ecologically and socially related to the upland privatization.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In the past,    the local population enjoyed access to both the upland and the floodplain, but    held no legal rights to either location. The development of legal private rights    was not necessary until access to use and residence in the area was threatened    by the actions of an external rancher. The 15-year period of engagement in the    social movement provided the residents with two major assets. First, their legal    property rights to the upland provided new sources of capital (timber and farm    credit) and land tenure security. These created incentives for local residents    to engage in long-term investments on their lands. Second, the experience of    participating in this political process generated an unintended outcome: formation    of social capital based on local leadership and integration with external supporting    actors such as religious, civil, and grassroots organizations.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The first    group of assets&#151;the private rights to the upland parcels&#151;is related    to the floodplain ecosystem through cattle activity. Cattle ranching is an attractive    economic activity among smallholders because it demands less labor and involves    lower production costs (HECHT, 1993). A source of money from natural (timber)    and institutional-based (credit lines) capital explains why almost all cattle    raisers decided to cooperate in a group when access to the floodplain was threatened.    Cattle ranching is carried out primarily by male members of the household and    relies upon a water source. The differential household structure among CP, PL,    and LL groups reveals that household assets, such as available labor, are key    variables influencing participation in collective action whenever the capability    to exploit the resource strongly affects their decisions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In addition    to the individual interest in and the financial capability of purchasing the    floodplain area, the CP group enjoyed organizational abilities to develop an    institutional arrangement and encourage other residents to convert the land    into a collective property. The leaders, who played a key role in the origin    of the floodplain collective action, are the same leaders who participated extensively    in claiming the land rights to the upland, revealing the political relationship    between the process of land tenure change in the upland and floodplain ecosystems.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The formation    of a leadership is an important asset in most collective action groups, particularly    in areas with poor institutional support (SINGH &amp; BALLABH, 1994; DURSTON,    1998). In Patos, as in other Amazonian floodplain areas, peasants regularly    exchange labor, food, and other products and even share land among kin households    (LIMA-AYRES, 1992; FUTEMMA, 1995). Social capital is an asset that may be built    from a history of past cooperation (DURSTON, 1998; WHITE &amp; RUNGE, 1994).    Previous experience in group cooperation and their success in a previous collective    action contributed to the Patos residents' willingness to initiate the collective    action that occurred in the floodplain ecosystem.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In sum,    the ecological, social, institutional, and economic connections between floodplain    and upland ecosystems are key to understanding the emergence of the collective    action. By the same token, the analysis of the ecological outcomes of the collective    action indicates a similar interaction between floodplain and upland forest.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2"><b>The Outcome    of Collective Action</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Cattle raising    has been one of the main activities from small- to large-scale rural producers,    and changes in land-use patterns can be observed throughout the Amazon region    (Fearnside, 1989). The integrated use of floodplain and upland ecosystems for    cattle ranching has steadily increased during the past two decades in the Lower    Amazon and has altered both ecosystems, in some places at higher degrees of    disturbance than others (ARIMA &amp; UHL, 1997).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In Patos,    the connection between upland and floodplain ecosystems is not only related    to the influence of upland private rights, but to the emergence of collective    property rights on the floodplain. The upland and the floodplain are also related    in terms of ecological outcome in forest cover. The floodplain ecosystem has    not shown signs of change in vegetation cover since the collective property    regime was established, but that does not mean collectivization has led to resource    conservation. The change in property rights may be too recent to be reflected    in the land cover. While the group still holds a small herd, there is a trend    toward increasing the number of cattle. Therefore, an impact similar to what    would take place faster by the rancher and his large herd is still possible    in the long run by the joint owners. A second reason the collectivization of    the floodplain should not be related directly to forest conservation is its    connection with changes in upland forest cover. The decision of the participants    to purchase the floodplain area was based on sources of money provided from    the upland system (such as timber and credit lines), and value of the land related    to the cattle investment was backed up by conversion of upland forest to pasture.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">Thus, although    collective action in the floodplain has not directly affected the ecosystem    where it took place, it has indirectly affected the land-cover change on the    adjacent ecosystem due to the integrated production system of the households    involved in the process. The role of cattle ranching in changing land-use patterns    of both the upland and the floodplain ecosystems simultaneously reveals the    importance of an ecosystemic approach in studying the impact of human action    on natural systems. The ecosystemic approach enables one to understand how human    actions that take place in a given ecosystem can affect (and be affected by)    another ecosystem (ELLEN, 1982; MORAN, 1979). This approach stresses dynamic    processes. At the present time, the incentives at stake seem to lead CP households    to use the upland forest more intensively than PL households. We cannot yet    firmly conclude that in the long run CP households will continue to impact the    forest more than PL households. The "side-effect" of the floodplain collectivization    on the upland forest does not represent a prompt threat to that ecosystem. The    impact is still small and represents a tradeoff between the social responsibility    of local users to maintain their access to an area they have long relied upon    for their livelihood and the chance to ensure maintenance of ecological integrity    in both ecosystems.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In this    case, the questions related to the outcomes of collective action must be closely    attached to both ecosystems. The ability of the joint owners to develop a robust    institutional arrangement that accounts for the interconnection of floodplain    and upland ecosystems, the external economic and political changes that affect    the production systems and the local dynamics that influence the balance between    collaboration and conflict are fundamental to achieving a positive performance    of this local enterprise in the long run. Future studies will reveal how this    dynamic system evolves over time.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>CONCLUSION</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The Patos    case shows that the analysis of emergence and outcomes of collective action    should consider other scales of analysis besides a single community. At the    household level, differences in household assets may influence the motivation    to participate in collective action. Although all community members were invited    to be part of a floodplain collective property, a low investment capability    explained why the Landless group did not participate. The potential value of    the floodplain resource explains why the Collective-Private group participated,    and restrictions on credit and income and lack of other economic incentives    explain why Private-Landholder households refrained from participating. Landscape-level    analysis reveals that connection between the managed ecosystem and adjacent    ecosystems influences the decisions to participate as well as the ecological    outcomes of the collective actions. Finally, floodplain collectivization was    not only influenced by the upland privatization but influenced the ecological    outcomes on the upland ecosystem.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">The two    ecosystems are not only spatially connected. They also have a temporal connection    regarding the creation of social capital. The first collective action that took    place in the upland ecosystem helped to build the social capital that was used    in carrying out the collective action that took place in the floodplain ecosystem    twenty years later. The social capital from external actors in the upland collective    action enabled local residents to initiate the floodplain collective action    drawing almost entirely on internal resources. Local leaders were able to organize    the group, seek external assistance in obtaining information, and gain bargaining    power with local government agencies.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">In sum,    the analysis of collective actions in systems with pronounced social and ecological    heterogeneities requires analysis at different scales&#151;combining household,    community, and region&#151;to tease out factors influencing the emergence and    outcomes of those local efforts.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">We appreciate    the support provided by the National Science Foundation grant SBR9521918 to    the Center for the Study of Institutions, Population, and Environmental Change    and the support provided by the World Wildlife Fund grant CSR-107-98 to the    first author for doctoral field research. We are grateful to Projeto V&aacute;rzea    (IPAMInstituto de Pesquisa da Amaz&ocirc;nia) for their logistic support. We    owe our gratitude to Manoel Cordeiro for plant identification and Antonio Jer&ocirc;nimo    and Joanna Tucker for field assistance. We would also like to thank Emilio Moran    for his helpful comments on an earlier draft of this paper. We thank Joanna    Broderick and Patty Zielinski for careful editing of this paper. Finally, we    are deeply grateful to all Patos residents for making the collection of data    possible. The authors assume full responsibility for the content presented in    this paper. This article was originally published in <i>Society and Natural    Resources</i>, 15: 503-522, 2002.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="3"><b>BIBLIOGRAPHY</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ANDERSON,    A.B. "Use and management of native palm forest dominated by <i>a&ccedil;ai</i>    palm (<i>Euterpe oleraceae</i>) in the Amazon estuary". <i>Advances in Economic    Botany</i> 6, 1990:144154.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000132&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ARIMA, E.    &amp; CHRISTOPHER, U. "Ranching in the Brazilian Amazon in a national context:    Economics, policy, and practice" <i>Society and Natural Resources</i> 10(5),    1997: 451433.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000133&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">BERKES,    F. <b>Common property: Ecology and community-based sustainable development.</b>    London: Behaven Press, 1989.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000134&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">BLAIR, H.W.    "Democracy, equity, and common property resources management in the Indian subcontinent".    <i>Development and Change</i> 27, 1996: 475499.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000135&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">BRONDIZIO,    E.S. &amp; SIQUEIRA, A. "From extractivists to forest farmers: Changing concepts    of <i>caboclo</i> agroforestry in the Amazon estuary". <i>Research in Economic    Anthropology</i> 8, 1997: 233279.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000136&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CARDENAS,    J.C. "Real wealth and experimental cooperation: Evidence from field experiments".    <i>Paper presented at the Eighth Conference of the International Association    for the Study of Common Property</i>, Bloomington, Indiana, May 31June 4, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000137&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CARVALHO,    J.O. P. <b>Structure and dynamics of a logged-over Brazilian Amazonian rain    forest.</b> Ph.D. diss. University of Oxford, Oxford, U.K, 1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000138&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CASTRO,    F. <b>Fishing accords: The political ecology of fishing intensification in the    Amazon</b><i>.</i> Ph.D. diss. Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000139&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">CERNEA,    M. <b>User groups as producers in participatory afforestation strategies</b>.    World Bank Discussion Paper No. 7. Washington, D.C.: World Bank, 1989.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000140&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">COLEMAN,    J. "Norms as social capital". In: RADNITZKY, G. &amp; BERNHOLZ, P. (eds.) <b>Economic    imperialism: The economic approach applied outside the field of economics</b>,    New York: Paragon House, 1987: 133-155.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000141&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">DAVIS, A.    &amp; BAILEY.C. "Common in custom, uncommon in advantage: Common property, local    elites, and alternative approaches to fisheries management". <i>Society and    Natural Resources</i> 9(Special Issue), 1996: 251266.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000142&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">DURSTON,    J. "Building social capital in rural communities (where it does not exist):    Theoretical and policy implications of peasant empowerment in Chiquimula, Guatemala".    <i>Paper presented at XXI International Conference of Latin American Studies    Association</i>, Chicago, Illinois, September 2830, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000143&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">ELLEN, R.    F. <b>Environment subsistence and system: The ecology of small-scale social    formation.</b> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000144&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">FEARNSIDE,    P. M. "Deforestation in Brazilian Amazonia: The rates and causes of forest destruction".    <i>The Ecologist</i> 19(6), 1989: 214218.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000145&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">FUTEMMA,    C. <b>Collective action and assurance of property rights to natural resources:    A case study from the Lower Amazon region, Santar&eacute;m, Brazil</b>. PhD.    diss. Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000146&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    <b>Agriculture and caboclo household organization in the Lower Amazon basin:    Case studies</b>. Master thesis. Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana,    1995.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000147&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GIBSON,    C.C. &amp; KOONTZ, T. "When community is not enough: Communities and forests    in Southern Indiana". <i>Human Ecology</i> 26, 1997: 621647.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000148&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700017&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GIBSON,    C. C.; McKEAN, M. &amp; OSTROM, E. <b>People and forests: Communities, institutions,    and governance</b>. Cambridge: The MIT Press, 2000.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000149&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700018&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">GUILLET,    D. "Land tenure, ecological zone, and agricultural regime in the Central Andes".    <i>American Ethnologist</i> 8, 1981: 139156.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000150&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700019&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">HECHT, S.    "The logic of livestock and deforestation in Amazonia". <i>Bioscience</i> 43(10),    1993: 687695.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000151&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700020&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">INCRA (The    National Institute for Colonization and Agrarian Reform). Unpublished report.    Santar&eacute;m, Par&aacute;, 1994<font color="#0000ff">.</font></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000152&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700021&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">JUNK, W.    J. "Ecology of the <i>v&aacute;rzea</i>: Floodplain of Amazonia white-water    rivers". In: SIOLI, H. (ed.) <b>The Amazon limnology and landscape ecology of    a mighty tropical river and its basin</b>, Boston: Dr. W. Junk Publishers Dordrecht,    1984.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000153&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700022&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">LIMA-AYRES,    D. L. M. <b>The social category caboclo: History, social organization of the    rural population of an Amazonian region (the middle Solim&otilde;es)</b><i>.</i>    Ph.D. diss. University of Cambridge, 1992.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000154&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700023&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">LOPES, J.C.    A.; CARVALHO, J.O.; SILVA, J.N. &amp; COSTA, H.B. "Sociabilidade entre 18 esp&eacute;cies    comerciais ocorrentes na Floresta Nacional do Tapaj&oacute;s". <i>Proceedings    Anales</i>, Bel&eacute;m, Brazil: Departamento de Difus&atilde;o e Tecnologia,    1984.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000155&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700024&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">McCAY, B.    J.&amp; ACHESON, J.M. <b>The questions of the commons: The culture and ecology    of communal resources</b><i>.</i> Tucson: The University of Arizona Press, 1987.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000156&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700025&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">McCAY, B.J.    &amp; JENTOFT, S. "Market or community failure? Critical perspective on common    property research". <i>Human Organization</i> 57, 1998:2129.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000157&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700026&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">MORAN, E.    <b>Human adaptability: An introduction to ecological anthropology</b>. North    Scituate, Mass.: Duxbury Press, 1979.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000158&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700027&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">NETTING,    R. M. "What alpine peasants have in common: Observations on communal tenure    in a Swiss village". <i>Human Ecology</i> 4(2), 1976: 135146.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000159&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700028&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">OLSON, M.    1965. <b>The logic of collective action: Public goods and the theory of groups</b>.    Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1965.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000160&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700029&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">OSTROM,    E. "Social capital: A fad or a fundamental concept?" In: DASGUPTA, P. &amp;    SERAELDIM, I. (eds.) <b>S<i>ocial capital: A multifaceted perspective</i></b>,.    Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1999.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000161&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700030&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    "A behavioral approach to the rational choice theory of collective action".    <i>The American Political Science Review</i> 92, 1998:122</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000162&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700031&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">_______.    <b>Governing the commons: The evolution of institutions for collective action</b>.    Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000163&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700032&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">PINKERTON,    E. "Local fisheries co-management: A review of international experience and    their implications for salmon management in British Columbia". <i>Canadian Journal    of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</i> 51, 1994: 23632378.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000164&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700033&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">RADAMBRASIL.    <b>Levantamento dos recursos naturais</b>. Vol. 10. Folha SA-21-Santar&eacute;m.    Projeto RADAMBRASIL (Programa de Integra&ccedil;&atilde;o Nacional). Rio de    Janeiro: Minist&eacute;rio das Minas e Energias - Departamento Nacional de Produ&ccedil;&atilde;o    Mineral and Projeto RADAMBRASIL, 1976.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000165&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700034&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">SCHLAGER,    E. &amp; BLOMQUIST, W. "Resolving common-pool resource dilemmas heterogeneities    among resources users". <i>Paper presented at the Seventh Conference of the    International Association for the Study of Common Property, British Columbia,    Canada</i>, June 1014, 1998.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000166&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700035&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">SCHLAGER,    E.; BLOMQUIST, W. &amp; TANG, S. Y. "Mobile flows, storage, and self-organized    institutions for governing common-pool resources". <i>Land Economics</i> 70(3),    1994: 294317.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000167&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700036&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">SINGH, K.    &amp; BALLABH, V. 1994. <b>Role of leadership in cooperative management of natural    common-pool resources: A collective goods theoretic perspective.</b> Workshop    in Political Theory and Policy Analysis Working Paper No. 50. Bloomington: Indiana    University, 1994.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000168&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700037&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">SMITH, R.L.    <b>Ecology and field biology</b>. New York: HarperCollins College Publishers,    1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000169&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700038&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">UHL, C.    &amp; VIEIRA, I.C. "Ecological impacts of selective logging in the Brazilian    Amazon: Case study from the Paragominas region of the State of Par&aacute;".    <i>Biotropica</i> 21(2), 1989: 98106.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000170&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700039&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">VARUGHESE,    G. &amp; OSTROM, E. "The contested role of heterogeneity in collective action:    Some evidence from community forestry in Nepal". <i>World Development</i> 29(5),    2001: 747765<i>.</i></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000171&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700040&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">WHITE, T.    A. "Private exchange and social capital: Multiple functions common property    regimes in Haiti". <i>Paper presented at 6th Biannual Conference of the International    Association for the Study of Common Property</i>. Berkeley, California, June    58, 1996.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000172&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700041&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica-Normal, sans-serif" size="2">WHITE, T.    A. &amp; RUNGE, C. F. "Common property and collective action: Lessons from cooperative    watershed management in Haiti". <i>Economic Development and Cultural Change</i>    43(1), 1994:143.</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000173&pid=S1414-753X200200010000700042&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --> ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ANDERSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Use and management of native palm forest dominated by açai palm (Euterpe oleraceae) in the Amazon estuary]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Advances in Economic Botany]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<page-range>144-154</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ARIMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CHRISTOPHER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[U.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Ranching in the Brazilian Amazon in a national context: Economics, policy, and practice]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Society and Natural Resources]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<numero>5</numero>
<issue>5</issue>
<page-range>451-433</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BERKES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Common property: Ecology and community-based sustainable development]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[London ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Behaven Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BLAIR]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Democracy, equity, and common property resources management in the Indian subcontinent]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Development and Change]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<page-range>475-499</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BRONDIZIO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.S.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SIQUEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[From extractivists to forest farmers: Changing concepts of caboclo agroforestry in the Amazon estuary]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Research in Economic Anthropology]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<page-range>233-279</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CARDENAS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Real wealth and experimental cooperation: Evidence from field experiments]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[Eighth Conference of the International Association for the Study of Common Property]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>May 31-June 4, 2000</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Bloomington Indiana</conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CARVALHO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.O. P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Structure and dynamics of a logged-over Brazilian Amazonian rain forest]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CASTRO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Fishing accords: The political ecology of fishing intensification in the Amazon]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CERNEA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[User groups as producers in participatory afforestation strategies]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eD.C. D.C.]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[World Bank]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COLEMAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Norms as social capital]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RADNITZKY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BERNHOLZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Economic imperialism: The economic approach applied outside the field of economics]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<page-range>133-155</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Paragon House]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DAVIS]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BAILEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Common in custom, uncommon in advantage: Common property, local elites, and alternative approaches to fisheries management]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Society and Natural Resources]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<numero>^sSpecial Issue</numero>
<issue>^sSpecial Issue</issue>
<supplement>Special Issue</supplement>
<page-range>251-266</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DURSTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Building social capital in rural communities (where it does not exist): Theoretical and policy implications of peasant empowerment in Chiquimula, Guatemala]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[XXI International Conference of Latin American Studies Association]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>September 28-30, 1998</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Chicago Illinois</conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ELLEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Environment subsistence and system: The ecology of small-scale social formation]]></source>
<year>1982</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FEARNSIDE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Deforestation in Brazilian Amazonia: The rates and causes of forest destruction]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The Ecologist]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<numero>6</numero>
<issue>6</issue>
<page-range>214-218</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FUTEMMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Collective action and assurance of property rights to natural resources: A case study from the Lower Amazon region, Santarém, Brazil]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FUTEMMA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Agriculture and caboclo household organization in the Lower Amazon basin: Case studies]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B17">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GIBSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[KOONTZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[When community is not enough: Communities and forests in Southern Indiana]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Human Ecology]]></source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<page-range>621-647</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B18">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GIBSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McKEAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OSTROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[People and forests: Communities, institutions, and governance]]></source>
<year>2000</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The MIT Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B19">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GUILLET]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Land tenure, ecological zone, and agricultural regime in the Central Andes]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[American Ethnologist]]></source>
<year>1981</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<page-range>139-156</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B20">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[HECHT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The logic of livestock and deforestation in Amazonia]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Bioscience]]></source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<numero>10</numero>
<issue>10</issue>
<page-range>687-695</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B21">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<collab>INCRA</collab>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Santarém^ePará Pará]]></publisher-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B22">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JUNK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Ecology of the várzea: Floodplain of Amazonia white-water rivers]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SIOLI]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The Amazon limnology and landscape ecology of a mighty tropical river and its basin]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Boston ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Dr. W. Junk Publishers Dordrecht]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B23">
<nlm-citation citation-type="">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LIMA-AYRES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D. L. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The social category caboclo: History, social organization of the rural population of an Amazonian region (the middle Solimões)]]></source>
<year></year>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B24">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LOPES]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.C. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CARVALHO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.O.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SILVA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.N.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[COSTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Sociabilidade entre 18 espécies comerciais ocorrentes na Floresta Nacional do Tapajós]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Proceedings Anales]]></source>
<year>1984</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Belém ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Departamento de Difusão e Tecnologia]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B25">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McCAY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B. J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[ACHESON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The questions of the commons: The culture and ecology of communal resources]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Tucson ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The University of Arizona Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B26">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[McCAY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JENTOFT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Market or community failure?: Critical perspective on common property research]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Human Organization]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>57</volume>
<page-range>21-29</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B27">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MORAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Human adaptability: An introduction to ecological anthropology]]></source>
<year>1979</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[North Scituate^eMass Mass]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Duxbury Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B28">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[NETTING]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R. M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[What alpine peasants have in common: Observations on communal tenure in a Swiss village]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Human Ecology]]></source>
<year>1976</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>135-146</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B29">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OLSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[The logic of collective action: Public goods and the theory of groups]]></source>
<year>1965</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Harvard University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B30">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OSTROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Social capital: A fad or a fundamental concept?]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DASGUPTA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SERAELDIM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Social capital: A multifaceted perspective]]></source>
<year>1999</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington^eD.C. D.C.]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The World Bank]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B31">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OSTROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[A behavioral approach to the rational choice theory of collective action]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[The American Political Science Review]]></source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>92</volume>
<page-range>1-22</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B32">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OSTROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Governing the commons: The evolution of institutions for collective action]]></source>
<year>1990</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Cambridge ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Cambridge University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B33">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PINKERTON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Local fisheries co-management: A review of international experience and their implications for salmon management in British Columbia]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<page-range>2363-2378</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B34">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>RADAMBRASIL</collab>
<article-title xml:lang="pt"><![CDATA[Levantamento dos recursos naturais]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Projeto RADAMBRASIL: Programa de Integração Nacional]]></source>
<year>1976</year>
<page-range>SA-21</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Rio de Janeiro ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Ministério das Minas e EnergiasDepartamento Nacional de Produção MineralProjeto RADAMBRASIL]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B35">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SCHLAGER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BLOMQUIST]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Resolving common-pool resource dilemmas heterogeneities among resources users]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[Seventh Conference of the International Association for the Study of Common Property]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>June 10-14, 1998</conf-date>
<conf-loc>British Columbia </conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B36">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SCHLAGER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BLOMQUIST]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[TANG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[S. Y.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Mobile flows, storage, and self-organized institutions for governing common-pool resources]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Land Economics]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>294-317</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B37">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SINGH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BALLABH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[V.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Role of leadership in cooperative management of natural common-pool resources: A collective goods theoretic perspective]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[ Workshop in Political Theory and Policy Analysis]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>1994</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Bloomington </conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B38">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SMITH]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.L.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Ecology and field biology]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[New York ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[HarperCollins College Publishers]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B39">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[UHL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VIEIRA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Ecological impacts of selective logging in the Brazilian Amazon: Case study from the Paragominas region of the State of Pará]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Biotropica]]></source>
<year>1989</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>98-106</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B40">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VARUGHESE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[OSTROM]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[E.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The contested role of heterogeneity in collective action: Some evidence from community forestry in Nepal]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[World Development]]></source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>29</volume>
<numero>5</numero>
<issue>5</issue>
<page-range>747-765</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B41">
<nlm-citation citation-type="confpro">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WHITE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Private exchange and social capital: Multiple functions common property regimes in Haiti]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[]]></source>
<year></year>
<conf-name><![CDATA[6 Biannual Conference of the International Association for the Study of Common Property]]></conf-name>
<conf-date>June 5-8, 1996</conf-date>
<conf-loc>Berkeley California</conf-loc>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B42">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WHITE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T. A.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RUNGE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[C. F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Common property and collective action: Lessons from cooperative watershed management in Haiti]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Economic Development and Cultural Change]]></source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>1-43</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
