<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1414-753X</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Ambiente & Sociedade]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Ambient. soc.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1414-753X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[ANPPAS - Revista Ambiente e Sociedade]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1414-753X2012000300004</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1414-753X2012000300004</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Environmental impact assessment, from Rio-92 to Rio+20 and beyond]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Sánchez]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Luis E.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Croal]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Peter]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of São Paulo Escola Politécnica ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[São Paulo SP]]></addr-line>
<country>Brazil</country>
</aff>
<aff id="A02">
<institution><![CDATA[,Canadian International Development Agency Environmental Sustainability and Responsible Investment Strategic Policy and Performance Branch]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<fpage>41</fpage>
<lpage>54</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000300004&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000300004&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1414-753X2012000300004&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="en"><p><![CDATA[The 1992 Rio Earth Summit was of paramount importance in the consolidation and international dissemination of environmental impact assessment, officially recognized as a tool for informed decision-making towards sustainable development (Principle 17, Rio Declaration) and for protection of biodiversity (Article 14, Convention on Biological Diversity). A significant development afterwards was the strengthening of strategic environmental assessment in the design of policies, plans and programs. Both forms of impact assessment can establish the necessary connections between one goal of the Rio+20 Conference - reaching an agreement on the transition to a green economy - and the underpinning decision making processes. Although the Rio+20 Summit has faced challenges to acknowledge its potential, impact assessment should be strengthened in support of both government and business decisions.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="pt"><p><![CDATA[A Cúpula da Terra de 1992, no Rio de Janeiro, teve a maior importância na consolidação e disseminação internacional da avaliação de impacto ambiental, oficialmente reconhecida como uma ferramenta de auxílio a decisões rumo ao desenvolvimento sustentável (Princípio 17 da Declaração do Rio) e para a proteção da biodiversidade (Artigo 14 da Convenção da Diversidade Biológica). Um desenvolvimento posterior significativo foi o fortalecimento da avaliação ambiental estratégica na preparação de políticas, planos e programas. Ambas as formas de avaliação de impacto têm a capacidade de estabelecer os necessários vínculos entre o objetivo declarado da Conferência Rio+20 - alcançar um acordo quando à transição para uma economia verde - e os processos decisórios subjacentes. Embora a Rio+20 tenha encontrado dificuldades para reconhecer seu potencial, a avaliação de impactos deveria ser fortalecida em apoio a decisões governamentais e privadas.]]></p></abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="short" xml:lang="es"><p><![CDATA[La Cumbre de la Tierra de 1992 fue de la más grande importancia en la consolidación y diseminación de la evaluación de impacto ambiental, oficialmente reconocida como una herramienta para la toma de decisiones informada hacia el desarrollo sostenible (Principio 17, Declaración de Rio) y para la protección de la biodiversidad (Artículo 14, Convención de la Diversidad Biológica). Un avanzo posterior importante fue el fortalecimiento de la evaluación ambiental estratégica en la preparación de políticas, planos y programas. Ambas formas de evaluación de impacto son capaces de establecer los necesarios vínculos entre un objetivo declarado de la Conferencia Rio+2- - llegar a un acuerdo sobre la transición para una economía verde - y los procesos decisorios subyacentes. Aunque la Cumbre Rio+20 tenga encontrado dificultades en reconocer su potencial, la evaluación de impactos debería ser fortalecida en soporte de decisiones gubernamentales y privadas.]]></p></abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Impact assessment]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Strategic environmental assessment]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Rio+20 Conference]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="en"><![CDATA[Environmental decision making]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Avaliação de impacto]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Avaliação ambiental estratégica]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Rio+20]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="pt"><![CDATA[Decisões ambientais]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="es"><![CDATA[Evaluación de impacto]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="es"><![CDATA[Evaluación ambiental estratégica]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="es"><![CDATA[Conferencia Rio+20]]></kwd>
<kwd lng="es"><![CDATA[Toma de decisiones ambientales]]></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p><font face="Verdana" size="4"><b>Environmental impact assessment, from Rio-92    to Rio+20 and beyond</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font size="2" face="Verdana"><b>Luis E. S&aacute;nchez<sup>I</sup>; Peter    Croal<sup>II</sup></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><sup>I</sup>Escola Polit&eacute;cnica. University    of S&atilde;o Paulo. Address: Av. Prof. Mello Moraes, 2373. 05508-900. S&atilde;o    Paulo, SP, Brazil. E-mail: <a href="mailto:lsanchez@usp.br">lsanchez@usp.br</a>    <br>   <sup>II</sup>Canadian International Development Agency. Manager. Environmental    Integration. Environmental Sustainability and Responsible Investment (ESRI).    Strategic Policy and Performance Branch. Address: 200 promenade du Portage,    The opinions expressed by the author are personal and do not reflect the policies    and position of CIDA or the government of Canada</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>ABSTRACT</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The 1992 Rio Earth Summit was of paramount importance    in the consolidation and international dissemination of environmental impact    assessment, officially recognized as a tool for informed decision-making towards    sustainable development (Principle 17, Rio Declaration) and for protection of    biodiversity (Article 14, Convention on Biological Diversity). A significant    development afterwards was the strengthening of strategic environmental assessment    in the design of policies, plans and programs. Both forms of impact assessment    can establish the necessary connections between one goal of the Rio+20 Conference    - reaching an agreement on the transition to a green economy - and the underpinning    decision making processes. Although the Rio+20 Summit has faced challenges to    acknowledge its potential, impact assessment should be strengthened in support    of both government and business decisions.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Keywords:</b> Impact assessment. Strategic    environmental assessment. Rio+20 Conference. Environmental decision making</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>RESUMO</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A C&uacute;pula da Terra de 1992, no Rio de Janeiro,    teve a maior import&acirc;ncia na consolida&ccedil;&atilde;o e dissemina&ccedil;&atilde;o    internacional da avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o de impacto ambiental, oficialmente    reconhecida como uma ferramenta de aux&iacute;lio a decis&otilde;es rumo ao    desenvolvimento sustent&aacute;vel (Princ&iacute;pio 17 da Declara&ccedil;&atilde;o    do Rio) e para a prote&ccedil;&atilde;o da biodiversidade (Artigo 14 da Conven&ccedil;&atilde;o    da Diversidade Biol&oacute;gica). Um desenvolvimento posterior significativo    foi o fortalecimento da avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o ambiental estrat&eacute;gica    na prepara&ccedil;&atilde;o de pol&iacute;ticas, planos e programas. Ambas as    formas de avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o de impacto t&ecirc;m a capacidade de estabelecer    os necess&aacute;rios v&iacute;nculos entre o objetivo declarado da Confer&ecirc;ncia    Rio+20 - alcan&ccedil;ar um acordo quando &agrave; transi&ccedil;&atilde;o para    uma economia verde - e os processos decis&oacute;rios subjacentes. Embora a    Rio+20 tenha encontrado dificuldades para reconhecer seu potencial, a avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o    de impactos deveria ser fortalecida em apoio a decis&otilde;es governamentais    e privadas.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Palavras-chave:</b> Avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o    de impacto. Avalia&ccedil;&atilde;o ambiental estrat&eacute;gica. Rio+20. Decis&otilde;es    ambientais.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>RESUMEN</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">La Cumbre de la Tierra de 1992 fue de la m&aacute;s    grande importancia en la consolidaci&oacute;n y diseminaci&oacute;n de la evaluaci&oacute;n    de impacto ambiental, oficialmente reconocida como una herramienta para la toma    de decisiones informada hacia el desarrollo sostenible (Principio 17, Declaraci&oacute;n    de Rio) y para la protecci&oacute;n de la biodiversidad (Art&iacute;culo 14,    Convenci&oacute;n de la Diversidad Biol&oacute;gica). Un avanzo posterior importante    fue el fortalecimiento de la evaluaci&oacute;n ambiental estrat&eacute;gica    en la preparaci&oacute;n de pol&iacute;ticas, planos y programas. Ambas formas    de evaluaci&oacute;n de impacto son capaces de establecer los necesarios v&iacute;nculos    entre un objetivo declarado de la Conferencia Rio+2- - llegar a un acuerdo sobre    la transici&oacute;n para una econom&iacute;a verde - y los procesos decisorios    subyacentes. Aunque la Cumbre Rio+20 tenga encontrado dificultades en reconocer    su potencial, la evaluaci&oacute;n de impactos deber&iacute;a ser fortalecida    en soporte de decisiones gubernamentales y privadas.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>Palabras clave:</b> Evaluaci&oacute;n de impacto.    Evaluaci&oacute;n ambiental estrat&eacute;gica. Conferencia Rio+20. Toma de    decisiones ambientales.</font></p> <hr size="1" noshade>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Introduction</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The United Nations Conference on Environment    and Development (also known as Rio 92 or Earth Summit) was a landmark gathering    concerning the international consolidation and acknowledgement of environmental    impact assessment (EIA) as a universal approach to inform and influence decision-making    on crucial socio-environmental matters . Enforced by legislation in 191 countries    (Morgan, 2012), adopted by donors of international development projects, by    multilateral banks and by a growing number of private financial institutions,    EIA has been accepted as a solid decision support process.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">What, then, could be expected, in terms of EIA,    from the United Nations Conference on Sustainable Development (Rio+20 Conference)?    This paper intends to explore the rationale for a reaffirmation of the role    of impact assessment (IA) in sustainable development due to its uniquecontribution    to publicly accountable decision We start by highlighting the most significant    references to EIA in the main documents resulting from the Rio 92 Conference.    Then, we highlight a few key developments in the IA field that took place after    the Earth Summit, in particular the diffusion of strategic environmental assessment    (SEA). In the following section, we review one of the major conceptual assumptions    of the Rio+20 Conference, green economy. and its far from unanimous meanings    to argue, in the final section, that SEA, and other forms of IA, should play    a role in any possible transition to a greener economy. We endeavour to address    what we understand to be a major flaw a key gap in the Rio+20 process and its    outcome document: a linkage between its objectives and the decision-making process.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Environmental impact assessment in the Rio    92 outcomes</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Rio 92 Conference stimulated national governments,    international organizations, and the business sector to acknowledge the role    of impact assessment in the quest for sustainable development. In the run-up    period, a number of countries have reviewed or established their national environmental    protection legislation to include provisions for EIA. The Conference has resulted    in three documents very important for the consolidation of EIA:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(1) Principle 17 of the Rio Declaration on Environment    and Development states: <i>Environmental impact assessment, as a national instrument,    shall be undertaken for proposed activities that are likely to have a significant    adverse impact on the environment and are subject to a decision of a competent    national authority.</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(2) Article 14 of the Convention on Biological    Diversity, titled <i>Impact Assessment and Minimizing Adverse Impacts</i>, establishes    that:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">1. Each Contracting Party, as far as possible    and as appropriate, shall: (a) Introduce appropriate procedures requiring environmental    impact assessment of its proposed projects that are likely to have significant    adverse effects on biological diversity with a view to avoiding or minimizing    such effects and, where appropriate, allow for public participation in such    procedures; (b) Introduce appropriate arrangements to ensure that the environmental    consequences of its programs and policies that are likely to have significant    adverse impacts on biological diversity are duly taken into account; (...).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(3) Agenda 21 refers to EIA in several different    chapters.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A fourth document that arose from the Rio Conference,    the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, does mention impact    assessment, but not at the same level of prominence as the other three documents.    Under Article 4.1.f, Commitments, this Convention calls parties to <i>Take climate    change considerations into account, to the extent feasible, in their relevant    social, economic and environmental policies and actions, and employ appropriate    methods, for example impact assessments, formulated and determined nationally,    with a view to minimizing adverse effects on the economy, on public health and    on the quality of the environment, of projects or measures undertaken by them    to mitigate or adapt to climate change.</i></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Rio documents also have been influenced by    (?) spilled over other important preexisting international conventions. Both    the Ramsar Convention on Wetlands (1971) and the Bonn Convention on the Conservation    of Migratory Species of Wild Animals (1979) adopted in their respective Conference    of Parties recommendations and guidelines relative to the adoption of EIA as    a tool for helping parties to meet the conventions' goals.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">As well, the Rio 92 Conference created a momentum    that inspired other governmental, intergovernmental, nongovernmental, and business    initiatives. The World Bank first adopted its policy on environmental assessment    in 1989 and updated it in September 1991. The United Nations Economic Commission    on Europe and member states adopted, also in 1991, a Convention on Environmental    Impact Assessment in a Transboundary Context, known as the Espoo Convention.    This UN organization also promoted the Aarhus Convention on Access to Information,    Public Participation in Decision-Making and Access to Justice in Environmental    Matters, which came into force in 1998. The World Business Council for Sustainable    Development, which was founded on the eve of the Rio Conference "to ensure the    business voice was heard at the forum", as one of its first initiatives, publishing    in 1996 the brochure "Environmental Assessment: a Business Perspective" (WBCD,    1996).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In spite of this success story, it does have    shortcomings. One flaw gap in the outcomes of the original Rio Conference concerns    the governance of global commons - the atmosphere, the oceans and the poles.    Human activities in the Antarctica are addressed by the Madrid Protocol to the    Antarctic Treaty, which entered into force in 1998, though its effectiveness    remains unclear (Wood, 2003).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Another flawis found in the Framework Convention    on Climate Change, which does not consider EIA as a tool for promoting reductions    on the emissions of greenhouse gases but only as a consideration in designing    strategies of adaptation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Foremost, no convention signed at the Rio Earth    Summit or other international meeting fully tackles the fundamental challenge    put forward by the Brundtland Commission (WCED, 1987, p. 313):</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><i>The ability to choose policy paths that are    sustainable requires that the ecological dimensions of policy be considered    at the same time as the economic, trade, energy, agricultural, industrial and    other dimensions - in the same agendas and in the same national and international    institutions. That is the chief institutional challenge of the 1990s.</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Unfortunately this challenge has not been met    since 1992.. The reasons why it happens will be discussed below.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Development of environmental impact assessment    1992-2012</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The fact that EIA is legally (?) required in    most countries is an indicator of the concept's success and utility (nonetheless    its potential lack of effectiveness ). EIA has been evolving after the Earth    Summit. New countries added legislation on the matter and others reviewed or    updated their previous legislation.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">One significant development in impact assessment    was its adoption by financial institutions. As the World Bank pioneered the    use and promotion of environmental assessment, other multilateral development    banks followed it and progressively approved their own policies and procedures    largely influenced by the experience. A refinement of this EIA approach had    happened in the World Bank Group, when the branch which specializes in financing    private projects, the International Finance Corporation (IFC) launched guidelines    for the environmental and social assessment of private sector projects in 2006    (updated in 2011). In addition, commercial banks launched in 2003 the Equator    Principles, a set of voluntary commitments by financial institutions to systematically    incorporate the results of environmental and social assessments into certain    types of credit decisions. Initially supported by ten banks, in June 2012 more    than 70 private and public banks as well as export credit agencies supported    the Equator Principles.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Another important phenomenon was the emergence    and consolidation of strategic environmental assessment (SEA). Defined as the    assessment of policies, programs, and plans (PPPs), SEA has been tuned into    lawin the European Union, in China and in a number of other countries and is    being applied by donors of international cooperation projects and programs.    SEA has resulted in a burgeoning literature in the last decade (Partid&aacute;rio,    2011).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In the international arena, efforts to disseminate    and provide the bases of SEA's implementation are promoted by development agencies.    A recent noteworthy initiative is supported by the Development Assistance Committee    (DAC) of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">At the OECD DAC High Level meeting of 21 May,    2008, members adopted the <i>Policy Statement on Strategic Environmental Assessment    (SEA)</i>. DAC recognizes that poor people suffer more than everyone when policies,    plans, or programs are poorly designed and implemented. Such suffering is compounded    by the risks posed by environmental degradation and climate change. The inability    of central government planning normally amplifies the vulnerabilities imposed    on the poor due to existing environmental conditions. The quality of development    planning will be affected significantly unless careful attention is to be given    to the relationship between policy development and the environment. The achievement    of the Millennium Development Goals (MDG) as well as the yet uncertain Sustainable    Development Goals (SDG) can also be compromised if the principles of sustainable    development, through the application of SEA, are not made part of the development    policies and programs. Therefore, the DAC Policy Statement on SEA provides OECD    members with a series of commitments on SEA use in developing countries, especially    on topics as SEA capacity building, the application of SEA, the effects of SEA    on development planning, and the ways SEA could be used in climate change issues,    ecosystems goods and services, conflict prevention, and disaster management.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The SEA use in OECD member governments and partner    countries has been growing since development assistance is increasingly being    provided at the level of policies, plans, and programs, rather than through    individual projects. Partner country institutions and systems for the most part    are the proper place of these initiatives. Therefore, to respect this development    assistance trend, the <i>Paris Declaration of Aid Effectiveness</i> was adopted    by the donor community in 2005. The Declaration is very clear about how SEA    is to be used. It calls upon donors and their partners to <i>"...develop and    apply common approaches for strategic environmental assessment at sector and    national levels.".</i> Clearly, at the highest level of OECD governance, SEA    is recognized as an intrinsic planning tool to support development initiatives.    This recognition was backed by the publication in 2006 by the OECD of the <i>DAC    Guidance on Applying Strategic Environmental Assessment</i> (OECD, 2006). This    document was developed through extensive collaboration among DAC members, developing    country partners, United Nations Environment Program (UNEP), United Nations    Development Program (UNDP), and a host of different development institutions    and agencies.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">During the last ten years a growing number of    developing countries have enacted policy, legislation or regulations that dictate    how SEA is to be used in development cooperation. The publication of various    OECD SEA instruments such as the SEA policy and guidance has amplified the need    for SEA in partner countries. However, it is the recent activity in the extractive    and energy sectors in development countries, which have created the need for    applying SEA. More developing countries blessed with natural resource realize    that responsible and sustainable natural resource management are capable of    provide long term gains in social, economic, and environmental issues for their    respective societies through SEA's application. SEA will also help developing    countries to determine if policy and legislative gaps do exist in a particular    sector, or what kind of institutional capacity issues should be faced . SEA    also builds public support for policy making and can enable transboundary cooperation    around shared natural resources. Unique opportunities are now being created    for improving policy, plan, and program making by integrating environmental    and related social considerations into the highest levels of government decisions.    This also provides new ways to reach consensus on development priorities and    mechanisms among various development stakeholder groups.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Finally, at same token important developments    have occurred regarding public participation in the IA process,. The Principle    10 of the Rio Declaration calls for enhanced public involvement in environmental    matters, including decision-making. It goes hand in hand with Principle 17,    since public participation is one of the pillars of IA and promoting access    to information, one of its goals . According to Principle 10: <i>Environmental    issues are best handled with the participation of all concerned citizens, at    the relevant level. At the national level, each individual shall have appropriate    access to information concerning the environment that is held by public authorities,    including information on hazardous materials and activities in their communities,    and the opportunity to participate in decision-making processes. States shall    facilitate and encourage public awareness and participation by making information    widely available. Effective access to judicial and administrative proceedings,    including redress and remedy, shall be provided.</i></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Principle 10 was applied by the UN Economic Commission    for Europe in the design of the Aarhus Convention on Access to Information,    Public Participation in Decision-making and Access to Justice in Environmental    Matters, approved in 1998. Under this Convention, decision-making ought is to    be informed by environmental impact assessment which, in turn, needs to be coupled    with public consultation procedures.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The participation of indigenous peoples in the    process is a matter of particular concern and it brings specific challenges.    The International Labor Organization approved in1989 thought the Convention    169, a legally binding international instrument which deals specifically with    the rights of native and tribal peoples. it is open to ratification. In fact    it gained force in 1990 after Mexico, following Norway, had assigned it. However,    it has been ratified only by 20 countries, mostly in Latin America. It was followed    by the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, approved    by the General Assembly in 2007. Both documents advanced the need for Free,    Prior and Informed Consent to be obtained from indigenous people by governments    employing culturally appropriate consultation approaches. As applied to impact    assessment, requirements and guidance for taking seriously indigenous peoples    rights and interests, are the subject of a World Bank Safeguard Policy and an    IFC Performance Standard.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>The Rio+20 preparatory process and its outcomes:    implications for environmental impact assessment</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A first intergovernmental conference to assess    progress since Rio 1992 was held by the United Nations ten years after in Johannesburg.    Although another Conference ten years later was not initially planned, Brazilian    government advanced a proposal to the UN to host a new Summit to assess progress    towards sustainable development. Accepted by the UN, the meeting was named <i>UN    Conference on Sustainable Development</i> (UNCSD). This marked an interesting    shift in terminology since the 1972 UN Conference on the Environment held in    Stockholm -, which was the first major intergovernmental gathering on environmental    issues. Twenty years later, the Rio Conference was labeled "Environment and    Development". Then in 2012 the term "environment" disappeared and instead of    that the conference focus was on "sustainable development".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Although intending to attract dozens of heads    of state and several thousand participants, the Conference goals were extremely    ambiguous when compared to the 1992 Earth Summit. This is not surprising since,    to a large extent as a result of Rio 92, high-level intergovernmental meetings    on environmental issues multiplied enormously. Both the climate and the biological    diversity conventions engendered periodical official meetings or Conference    of Parties (CoPs). In these meetings negotiations take place to devise strategies    or to agree on rules to their respective objectives. The Kyoto Protocol, establishing    greenhouse gases emissions targets, was signed in one of those CoPs. The proliferation    of CoPs and other sorts of environmentally-oriented intergovernmental meetings    is a post-Earth Summit trend and unknown as such in international scale pre-1992.    Therefore, Rio+20 could not expect to have a similar effect on the international    environment and sustainable development agenda as did the 1992 Conference.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Notwithstanding this context, many environmental    stakeholders had high dreams. A strong political commitment to the protection    of the oceans and a new and strengthened global environmental governance structure,    including a higher status for the UN Environment Program (UNEP), were among    such expectations. Impact assessment scholars and practitioners also had expectations    that, in the final and official outcome document, the importance of EIA could    be reinforced and especially that SEA could be recognized as a tool for achieving    sustainable development or for supporting the transition to a green economy.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The International Association for Impact Assessment    (IAIA), a nongovernmental organization registered with the UN Economic and Social    Council (Ecosoc) compounded by a network of professionals and researches, submitted    a short document stressing the role of impact assessment as a contribution to    the "compilation document" - an initial aggregation of submissions intended    to contribute to the Conference's outcome document. Some key considerations    advanced by IAIA about the role of impact assessment in general and strategic    environmental assessment in particular are:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>&#149;</b> it helps to ensure that high level    policies, programs, and projects are designed and implemented with more sustainable    outcomes while also reducing poverty and advancing green economy objectives;</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>&#149;</b> it helps to ensure that development    activities of individual sectors complement each other rather than undermine    themselves by providing a systematic means for minimizing potential adverse    outcomes and maximizing benefits early in policy, program, and project design;</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2"><b>&#149;</b> it can alert decision makers to    risks, improve community engagement, incorporate traditional knowledge, and    facilitate cooperation across sectors and boundaries before strategic decisions    had been taken.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Governments and international organizations also    supported impact assessment, including Canada, Ghana, and the World Bank. However,    by no means has SEA or IA in general been recognized as such in the outcome    document.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">From an initial document, which gathered and    assembled contributions from governments, international organizations, and major    civil groups, a draft document has evolved thought several discussions. . In    the Rio Convention Centre, more than 20,000 people - government delegations,    UN staff, major groups' representatives and journalists - met from the 15th    to the 22nd of June, 2012. A special pavilion hosted side events promoted by    governments and major groups, while open and closed meetings took place in other    rooms. Hundreds of side events were also promoted by businesses, academia and    civil society, including a "People's Summit for Social and Environmental Justice"    held at the very same place of the "Global Forum" in 1992, the civil society    meeting.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">To many observers, especially from civil society    organizations, the outcome of the Rio+20 was disappointingly modest. The final    declaration entitled "The Future We Want" - a 53 page long document containing    283 paragraphs (<a href="http://www.uncsd2012.org/thefuturewewant.html" target="_blank">http://www.uncsd2012.org/thefuturewewant.html</a>)    (<a href="/img/revistas/asoc/v15n3/a04box1.jpg">Box 1</a>) - was considered by many a weak and uninspiring document. Indeed, NGOs    dubbed it as "The Future We Don't Want" (<a href="http://rio20.net/en/documentos/the-future-we-don%E2%80%99t-want-some-thoughts-after-rio20" target="_blank">http://rio20.net/en/documentos/the-future-we-don%E2%80%99t-want-some-thoughts-after-rio20</a>).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Disagreement is found regarding many key issues,    including "green economy" - a central concept at this Conference. Not only is    its meaning not widely agreed, but is its rationale not shared by a number of    CSOs (Bosselmann, Brown and Mackey, 2012) and even among UN bodies, as exemplified    by contrasting the relatively optimistic view and proposals of UNEP (2011) with    those advanced in UNRISD (2012), which calls upon careful consideration of its    social dimensions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Rio+20 outcome document repeats previous    commitments, as in the example of paragraph 99: <i>We encourage action at the    regional, national, subnational and local levels to promote access to information,    public participation and access to justice in environmental matters, as appropriate</i>.    This is a short version of Principle 10 of Rio Declaration. Other paragraphs    sound quite cynical, e.g. <i>We reaffirm that climate change is one of the greatest    challenges of our time, and we express profound alarm that emissions of greenhouse    gases continue to rise globally </i>(190), in face of the several decades of    sustained unsuccessful attempts to reach an agreement to curb greenhouse gases    emissions</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The outcome document has only one direct mention    to impact assessment, under the "Oceans and Seas" subsection (part of V. A.    Thematic areas and cross-sectoral issues): <i>We also commit to enhance actions    to protect vulnerable marine ecosystems from significant adverse impacts, including    through the effective use of impact assessments</i> (paragraph 168). A related    topic is the recognition of the importance of technology assessment, under the    "Means of Implementation" section: <i>We recognize the importance of strengthening    international, regional and national capacities in research and technology assessment,    especially in view of the rapid development and possible deployment of new technologies    that may also have unintended negative impacts, in particular on biodiversity    and health, or other unforeseen consequences</i>. (paragraph 275).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Technology assessment (TA) is one form of impact    assessment which, for many years, had been stimulated by the Office of Technology    Assessment of the US Congress. Although this office was closed in 1995 (see    <a href="http://www.princeton.edu/%7Eota/" target="_blank">http://www.princeton.edu/~ota/</a>)    and political support for TA dramatically decreased worldwide, it is still seen    by academics as a powerful tool for supporting decision-making procedures (Vanclay    and Porter, 2009).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Although these paragraphs are a welcome reaffirmation    of the importance and role of IA, they are extremely timid both in scope and    reach. In addition, the generic wording of these and other paragraphs of the    outcome document allows for multiple (though possibly contradictory) interpretations    that will have to be explored and debated.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">The Rio+20 outcome document lacks the desirableconnections    with the decision making processes. Governments and private agents take daily    decisions that impact our collective future. There are tools and procedures    for assessing to which extent those decisions advance sustainable development    objectives. Impact assessment provides such linkages in a structured and accountable    way.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Hence, one outcome of the Rio +20 Conference    that has potential implications to IA in general and SEA in particular is the    agreement to start a process of establishing Sustainable Development Objectives    (SDO). Although not a part of the initial set of goals of the Conference, SDO    were incorporated in the agenda after a proposal has been made by Colombia.    At a certain point during the pre-Conference period, there was some hope that    a set of core objectives could be adopted at the Conference, but the challenges    of reaching an agreement on the objectives that should have been pursued rapidly    became clear. Since the deadline to attain the Millenium Development Goals (MDG)    is 2015, there was time to agree on new sustainable development objectives.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">A key difference between the SDO and MDG process    - and a reason why agreement on the SDO is and will remain difficult - is that    the former are intended to apply to every country, while the latter are goals    for the developing countries only. SDO are potentially important to SEA because    policies, plans, and programs (or PPPs, the subject of strategic assessment)    could be assessed in terms of how do they converge to or deviate from reaching    the SDO.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>Impact assessment in the transition to a greener    economy and the way ahead</b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Regardless of an agreement on the meaning of    a green economy, or on the need and urgency to set out a shift from growth,    as the driver of development, to degrowth, as a means to reduce mankind's ecological    footprint (Jackson, 2011), changes in consumption patterns must also be made    (Munasinghe, 2012). Impact assessment and especially strategic environmental    assessment can tackle with the still unaddressed "chief institutional challenge    of the 1990s" (in the words of the Brundtland report) of choosing sustainable    policy paths. As the effectiveness of SEA is being better understood through    theoretical proposals and lessons from case studies (Loayza, 2010; Doren et    al, 2013), it has been proving valuable in providing fresher and contemporary    approaches to development.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">That the Rio+20 Conference has not acknowledged    the role and potential contribution of SEA to policy choices is something regrettable.    Notwithstanding, work is now being done in development agencies and developing    countries to show how SEA can increase (?)green growth initiatives. In three    cases, out of the six UNEP's "enabling conditions" to pave pathways to a green    economy (UNEP, 2011), SEA can be especially relevant:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(1) to prioritize government investment and spending    in areas that stimulate greening of economic sectors;</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(2) to limit government spending in areas that    deplete natural capital;</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(3) to employ taxes and market-based instruments    to promote green investment and innovation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">In addition, there is a growing business case    for both project EIA and SEA. Many companies, all over the world, both in developed    and developing countries, are struggling against obstacles in obtaining approval    for new projects, especially in the natural resources sector. The emerging concept    of "social license" conveys the idea that in some cases a government approval    is not enough and that the consent of host communities is needed to establish    long-term and strong relationships (Prno and Slocombe, 2012) that enables continuous    operation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Impact assessment aims at facilitating more accountable    and transparent decision-making thought building in its environmental, social    and economic consequences. The main challenges ahead are:</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(1) Maintaining acquired gains and building on    progress achieved to date by showcasing the many contributions of IA to better    decisions, i.e. decisions where IA makes a difference, as avoiding impacts and    achieving effective mitigation and compensation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(2) Expanding IA to encompass initiatives potentially    affecting global commons - in particular the oceans and seas beyond the coastal    zone.</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(3) Consolidating SEA in jurisdictions where    it has already proved successful and expanding its acceptance into places where    its contribution has not been yet fully appreciated.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">(4) Expanding both project and strategic assessments    beyond the perspective of "doing no harm" to "doing good" or "ensuring net gain".</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">But the biggest challenge of all remains what    the Brundtland Commission has expressed: mainstreaming sustainability into policy    making.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Conflict at all levels can no longer be accepted    as part of the development and decision-making process. The continuing global    economic crisis and the fast deterioration of ecosystem's goods and services,    call for all actors in the decision-making and development process to use impact    assessment and strategic environmental assessment more aggressively. The use    of IA or SEA is no longer about protection of the environment; rather it represents    a shift in the way business and policy making that respect global realities    are made. SEA and IA should show that profits can be made, jobs created, and,    at same time, that a balance can be achieved among societal needs and the planet's    ability to provide them.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">BOSSELMANN, K.; BROWN, P.G.; MACKEY, B. Enabling    a flourishing Earth: Challenges for the green economy, opportunity for global    governance. Review of European Community &amp; International Law, v.21, n.1,    p. 23-30. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000089&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">DOREN, D. van; DRIESSEN, P.P.J.; SCHIJF, B.;    RUNHAAR, H.A.C. Evaluating the substantive effectiveness of SEA: Towards a better    understanding. Environmental Impact Assessment Review, v. 38, p. 120-130, 2013.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000091&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">JACKSON, T. Societal transformations for a sustainable    economy. Natural Resources Forum, v. 35, n.3, p. 155-164. 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000093&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">LOAYZA, F.. Strategic environmental assessment    in policy and sector reform : conceptual model and operational guidance. Washington:    The World Bank. 2010.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000095&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400004&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MORGAN, R.K. Environmental impact assessment:    the state of the art. Impact Assessment and Project Appraisal, v. 30, n.1, p.    5-14. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000097&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400005&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">MUNASHINGHE, M. Millenium Consumption Goals (MCGs)    for Rio+20 and beyond: A practical step towards global sustainability. Natural    Resources Forum, v. 36, p. 201-212. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000099&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400006&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">OECD, Organization for Economic Cooperation and    Development. Applying Strategic Environmental Assessment: Good Practice Guidance    for Development</font> <font face="Verdana" size="2">Cooperation. Paris: Organization for Economic    Cooperation and Development. 2006.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000101&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400007&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">PARTID&Aacute;RIO, M. Strategic Environmental    Assessment. Key Citation Series. Fargo: IAIA. 2009.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000103&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400008&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">PRNO, J.; SLOCOMBE, D.S. Exploring the origins    of 'social license to operate' in the mining sector: Perspectives from governance    and sustainability theories. Resources Policy v. 37, n.3, p. 346-357. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000105&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400009&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">THIAW, I.; MUNANG, R. Rio+20 outcomes recognize    the value of biodiversity and ecosystems: Implications for global, regional    and national policy. Ecosystem Services, v. 1, p. 121-122. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000107&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400010&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">UNEP, United Nations Environment Program. Towards    a Green Economy. Pathways to Sustainable Development and Poverty Eradication.    A Synthesis for Policy Makers. Nairobi: UNEP, 2011.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000109&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400011&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">UNRISD, United Nations Research Institute for    Social Development. Social Dimensions of Green Economy. Geneva: UNRISD. 2012.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000111&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400012&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">VANCLAY, F.; PORTER, A. Technology Assessment.    Key Citation Series. Fargo: IAIA. 2009.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000113&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400013&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">WBCSD, World Business Council for Sustainable    Development. Environmental Assessment: A Business Perspective. Geneva, WBCSD.    1996.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000115&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400014&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">WCED, World Commission on Environment and Development.    Our Common Future. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1987.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000117&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400015&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana" size="2">WOOD, K. The Uncertain Fate of the Madrid Protocol    to the Antarctic Treaty in the Maritime Area. Ocean Development &amp; International    Law, v. 34, n. 2, p. 139-159. 2003</font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000119&pid=S1414-753X201200030000400016&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --><p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana" size="2">Submetido em: 15/08/2012    ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<br>   Aceito em: 11/09/2012</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BOSSELMANN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BROWN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.G.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MACKEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Enabling a flourishing Earth: Challenges for the green economy, opportunity for global governance]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Review of European Community & International Law]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>23-30</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DOREN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D. van]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DRIESSEN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[P.P.J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SCHIJF]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[B.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[RUNHAAR]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[H.A.C.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Evaluating the substantive effectiveness of SEA: Towards a better understanding]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Environmental Impact Assessment Review]]></source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<page-range>120-130</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[JACKSON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[T.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Societal transformations for a sustainable economy]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Natural Resources Forum]]></source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>155-164</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B4">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[LOAYZA]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Strategic environmental assessment in policy and sector reform: conceptual model and operational guidance]]></source>
<year>2010</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Washington ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[The World Bank]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B5">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MORGAN]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Environmental impact assessment: the state of the art]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Impact Assessment and Project Appraisal]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<numero>1</numero>
<issue>1</issue>
<page-range>5-14</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B6">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MUNASHINGHE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Millenium Consumption Goals (MCGs) for Rio+20 and beyond: A practical step towards global sustainability]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Natural Resources Forum]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<page-range>201-212</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B7">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>OECD, Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Applying Strategic Environmental Assessment: Good Practice Guidance for Development Cooperation]]></source>
<year>2006</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Paris ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B8">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PARTIDÁRIO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[M.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Strategic Environmental Assessment]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Fargo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[IAIA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B9">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PRNO]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[J.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SLOCOMBE]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[D.S.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Exploring the origins of 'social license to operate' in the mining sector: Perspectives from governance and sustainability theories]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Resources Policy]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>346-357</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B10">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[THIAW]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[I.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MUNANG]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[R.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Rio+20 outcomes recognize the value of biodiversity and ecosystems: Implications for global, regional and national policy]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ecosystem Services]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<page-range>121-122</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B11">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>UNEP, United Nations Environment Program</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Towards a Green Economy: Pathways to Sustainable Development and Poverty Eradication]]></source>
<year>2011</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Nairobi ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[UNEP]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B12">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>UNRISD, United Nations Research Institute for Social Development</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Social Dimensions of Green Economy]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Geneva ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[UNRISD]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B13">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[VANCLAY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[F.]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[PORTER]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Technology Assessment]]></source>
<year>2009</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Fargo ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[IAIA]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B14">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>WBCSD, World Business Council for Sustainable Development</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Environmental Assessment: A Business Perspective]]></source>
<year>1996</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Geneva ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[WBCSD]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B15">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<collab>WCED, World Commission on Environment and Development</collab>
<source><![CDATA[Our Common Future]]></source>
<year>1987</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Oxford ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Oxford University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B16">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WOOD]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[K.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The Uncertain Fate of the Madrid Protocol to the Antarctic Treaty in the Maritime Area]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[Ocean Development & International Law]]></source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<issue>2</issue>
<page-range>139-159</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
