<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1981-3821</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Brazilian Political Science Review]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Bras. Political Sci. Rev.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1981-3821</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Associação Brasileira de Ciência Política]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1981-38212013000200011</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1981-38212013000200011</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Back to basics]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Vieira]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Marco Antonio]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Birmingham Department of Political Science and International Studies ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>UK</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>178</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200011&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200011&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200011&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    <b>BOOK REVIEW</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><a name="top"></a>Back    to basics&nbsp;</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Marco Antonio    Vieira</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Department of Political    Science and International Studies, University of Birmingham, UK</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">(FINNEMORE, Martha    and GOLDSTEIN, Judith (eds.). <i>Back to Basics: State Power in a Contemporary    World.</i> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013)</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The increasing    cross-border use of drones, the transnational and elusive phenomenon of cyber    espionage and warfare and the ineffectiveness of conventional states' responses    to non-traditional security threats such as international terrorism highlight    some of the complexities involved in understanding state power in the 21<sup>st</sup>    century. In the straightforward realist narrative, states are the main players    in world politics and power is a reflection of states' material capabilities.    Military capacity, in particular, is the ultimate source of states' power. Yet,    notwithstanding the still solid appeal of the hard power-based realist definition,    it does not seem to fit with contemporary international phenomena. The growing    number, diversity and relevance of non-state actors, such as international organisations,    networked global communities of activists, failed states, multinational corporations    and private individuals with a global reach, have fundamentally challenged the    state-centric ontology of realism. Likewise, the inability of the United States,    still the mightiest state in the world, to translate its economic and military    capabilities into desired foreign/defence policy outcomes suggests that conceiving    power simply in terms of tangible resources is limiting of a complete understanding    of the concept.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>Back to Basics</i>    evaluates the multiple dimensions of state power in the contemporary world.    It pays due homage to Stephen Krasner's groundbreaking and wide-ranging scholarship    on the sources and effects of state power in international politics. The volume's    editors specifically ask some of the most renowned scholars in the field of    International Relations theory "to reflect on the role of state power plays    in contemporary politics and how a power politics approach is still relevant    to theoretical issues in political science today" (pp. ix). The volume sets    out to advance three major areas which underlie Krasner's work: (i) it engages    with the question of what state power actually is and how it impacts on contemporary    world politics; (ii) it conceptually broadens the analytical scope of the international    (structural) environment wherein state power is applied and creates effects    and, finally; (iii) it discusses the contemporary malleability of sovereignty    which makes the exercise of state power extremely complex to understand.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><i>Back to Basics</i>    is a challenging book to review given that state power in contemporary politics,    in itself a complex subject to conceptually grasp, has been approached by the    volume's authors from quite different theoretical and empirical angles. The    underlying message in all contributions is quite simple though: traditional    material-based explanations of power in international relations scholarship    are still useful yet largely insufficient. The book is structured in five sections.    In the first section, the editors set the stage by laying out the volume's central    puzzles and comprehensively discussing the varied conceptualisations of power    in the realist literature and beyond. Keohane's essay, provocatively titled    'Stephen Krasner: Subversive Realist', develops an interesting argument about    Krasner's profound contribution and self-identification to, yet combative relationship    with, the realist tradition in the discipline of International Relations. Drawing    on Krasner's and his own previous work, Keohane suggests that the concept of    persuasion provides an interesting analytical basis for understanding the operation    of non-material sources (institutions, information, ideas and identity) of state    power.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The chapters in    the second section of the book reflect on sovereignty and power, two central    notions in Krasner's work. Like Keohane with 'persuasion', Lake explores 'authority'    as an under-theorised concept in IR. Lake emphasises the relevance of authority    as a source of non-coercive power. Authority relations, he argues, are dependent    upon the collective and socially constructed acceptance by states of the authority    of others over different issue-areas. There is a clear connection here between    Lake's argument and well-established discussions on legitimacy, recognition    and authority. English School authors, particularly Ian Clark, have emphasised    similar social dynamics of legitimacy building while constituting and expanding    the 'society' of states. Also in the social constructivist camp, Katzenstien's    essay points to the pervasive power of civilizational ideas associated with    the United States. According to him, the American empire is first and foremost    constituted and maintained by firmly entrenched, albeit increasingly disputed,    ideas and values that shape international institutions and regulate the behaviour    of actors. Risse's chapter picks up from Krasner's famous discussion of sovereignty    as organised hypocrisy to suggest that limited statehood does not necessarily    leads to inefficient provision of public goods. The author analytically detaches    the often-entangled notions of statehood and governance to persuasively claim    that 'new modes of governance [involving a combination of state and non-state    actors] are often effective even in the absence of consolidated statehood' (pp.79).    The interesting essay by Solingen provides 'three scenes of sovereignty and    power' (pp.105). The author also draws from Krasner's idea of contradictory    or 'hypocritical' sovereignty to reveal three different situations (the ascent    of China, variation within and across regions and the global non-proliferation    regime) whereby the full exercise of 'sovereign rule' is consequential to and    dependent upon domestic, regional and global political dynamics.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In section three    of the book, Cohen, Steinberg and Gourevitch dissect the relationship between    state power and global economic forces with excellent pieces on currency politics,    international trade laws/regimes and the 2008 global financial crisis, respectively.    The fourth section, with chapters by Stein, Gruber and Drezner, is dedicated    to the phenomenon of globalization and its alleged 'subversive effects' on the    Westphalian (state-centred) global order. Finally, in section five, two chapters    by Jervis and Krasner wrap up the collection with reflections on state power    in an increasingly complex global system. Jervis discusses power as a type of    cause and effect relationship with cuts across all forms of social interactions.    His argument is tied with the notion of responsibility understood in terms of    how 'acts and actors caused various outcomes' (pp.332). Stephen Krasners' final    chapter draws on Barnett's and Duval's (2005) taxonomy of power to organise    the book's essays according to four kinds of power: compulsory, institutional,    structural and productive.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The book's most    glaring omission - albeit unsurprising given its predominantly North-American    intellectual orientation - is an alternative conceptual treatment of state power    drawing from post-positivist theoretical ideas. For instance, the many adaptations    of Foucault's and Gramsci's work to the discipline of International Relations    have provided useful insights for a critical understanding of the interconnectedness    between knowledge, power and hegemony in contemporary world politics. Sections    three and four of the book in particular would be analytically enhanced by a    Marxist/Gramscian theory of power focusing on how the structure of the global    capitalist system fundamentally determines both the material and non-material    power capabilities of states.<a name="top1"></a><a href="#back1"><sup>1</sup></a></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Furthermore, the    volume has only glossed over, or neglected altogether, very important and novel    global political/security dynamics with clear implications to the operation    of state power in contemporary world politics. The deployment of unmanned drones    -almost always used in sharp violation of sovereignty -, the growing challenge    posed by cyber warfare/espionage/terrorism and the increasing salience of global    networks of political activists are just a few examples of how perilous the    geopolitical power of states is in the early 21<sup>st</sup> century. Notwithstanding    the volume's largely conceptual and theoretical focus, it would benefit, and    be empirically enriched by an analytical engagement with at least some of these    issues. In fact, a more empirically and global security focused application    of Krasner's proposed conceptual framework might be an interesting follow on    collection by the editors.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The above criticisms    are not to detract at all from what is otherwise a fine contribution. We should    definitely welcome a volume that attempts to rigorously bring state power back    front and centre in international relations research. The main contribution    of the book is to thoroughly demonstrate how insufficient the traditional realist    approaches are to apprehend the complex dynamics of contemporary world politics.    In light of the arguments presented in <i>Back to Basics</i>, it seems quite    clear that analyses of state power in the 21<sup>st</sup> century necessarily    need to take seriously non-material sources of power. This collection will be    a valuable resource for students of international relations interested in critically    rethinking conventional conceptualisations of state power along the lines proposed    by the essays in the volume.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">BARNETT, Michael    and DUVALL, Raymond. (2005), Power in International Politics. <i>International    Organization</i>, vol. 39, pp. 39-75.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000023&pid=S1981-3821201300020001100001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">CLARK, Ian. (2005),    <i>Legitimacy in International Society.</i> Oxford: Oxford University Press.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000025&pid=S1981-3821201300020001100002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">SAULL, Richard.    (2008), Empire, Imperialism, and Contemporary American Global Power. <i>International    Studies Perspectives</i>, vol. 9, n&ordm; 3, pp. 309-318.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000027&pid=S1981-3821201300020001100003&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><b><font size="3">Notes</font></b></font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2"><a name="back1"></a><a href="#top1">1</a>    See, for example, Saull (2008).</font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[BARNETT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Michael]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[DUVALL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Raymond]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Power in International Politics]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Organization]]></source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>39</volume>
<page-range>39-75</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[CLARK]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Ian]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Legitimacy in International Society]]></source>
<year>2005</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[Oxford ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Oxford University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B3">
<nlm-citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[SAULL]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Richard]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Empire, Imperialism, and Contemporary American Global Power]]></article-title>
<source><![CDATA[International Studies Perspectives]]></source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<numero>3</numero>
<issue>3</issue>
<page-range>309-318</page-range></nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
