<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1981-3821</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Brazilian Political Science Review]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Bras. Political Sci. Rev.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1981-3821</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Associação Brasileira de Ciência Política]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1981-38212013000200010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1981-38212013000200010</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The new actors of Brazilian foreign policy]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Burges]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Sean W.]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,Australian National University Australian National Centre for Latin American Studies ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>Australia</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<fpage>171</fpage>
<lpage>174</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200010&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    <b>BOOK REVIEW</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><a name="top"></a>The    new actors of Brazilian foreign policy</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Sean W. Burges</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Australian National    Centre for Latin American Studies at the Australian National University, Australia</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">(PINHEIRO, Leticia    and MILANI, Carlos R. S. (eds.).&nbsp;<i>Pol&iacute;tica externa brasileira:    As pr&aacute;ticas da pol&iacute;tica e a pol&iacute;tica das pr&aacute;ticas</i>.    Rio de Janeiro: Editora FGV, 2012)</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Brazilian foreign    policy has reached a very interesting inflection point. The bureaucratic walls    of the Itamaraty Palace so stoutly erected by the Baron of Rio Branco in 1902    are cracking. Where foreign policy used to be neatly circumscribed by the world    of 'high politics' and external interaction by Brazilians limited to a small    group of clearly defined actors, the situation today is very different. Itamaraty    retains pride of place for the grand geopolitical thinking that often preoccupies    the study of foreign policy, but the aspects of international affairs touching    the lives of citizens everywhere are increasingly becoming the concern of line    ministries, subnational governments, state agencies and private actors.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This is a bold    claim with respect to Brazilian foreign policy, but one which accurately reflects    the extent to which the technocratic minutia of specialist policy areas have    not only internationalized, but increasingly interact with other areas of 'low'    and 'high' politics. The immediate value of the individual chapters in this    book is that they highlight the absurdity of any attempt to claim that Brazil's    international affairs should remain the sole preserve of Itamaraty. Each of    the five diverse sections of the book - human rights, culture, education, health,    and paradiplomacy - immediately suggest that it is unreasonable to expect any    relatively small organization, no matter how brilliant its staff, to retain    mastery across such a wide range of sometimes highly technical specialties.    Indeed, this is the very challenge with which Itamaraty is currently grappling.    A more subtle approach is needed, one which involves complex bureaucratic positioning    and intra-departmental coordination by Itamaraty to retain influence while also    allowing Brazilian interests in these diverse areas to be advanced by the experts.    Each of the chapters in this volume does an excellent job of describing what    has happened.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Leticia Pinheiro    and Carlos R. S. Milani introduce the book by focusing on the importance of    technocratic expertise in many areas of contemporary international affairs.    Their question then is whether or not it is reasonable to expect Itamaraty to    have mastery over the diverse range of technical issues that are consequently    found in foreign affairs, and if not, how are decisions made and policies pursued?    In other words, the sharp distinction that Rio Branco drew between foreign and    domestic policy is pointed out as being an increasingly artificial and unhelpful    line. This in turn creates some issues for how we approach foreign policy analysis    today, casting into doubt such accepted tricks as sharp divisions between levels    of analysis and a tendency to oversimplify the nature and ambitions of actors.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The first section    on human rights immediately takes up the theme of seeking a more complicated    picture of how decisions are made and which actors are involved. Milani starts    with a chapter looking at actors and agendas in Brazil's human rights foreign    policy. He paints a picture of shifting understandings of what Brazil's position    should be. While Itamaraty may ultimately remained the external voice expressing    the national position, it certainly was not driving internal discussions or    limiting how domestic politics drove policy change. The following chapter by    Thiago Melamed de Menzes, a career diplomat with human rights experience in    the UN system, pairs well with Milani's chapter, setting out how Itamaraty sought    to adapt its practices to a contemporary scenario where a more participatory    democratic process to issues like human rights policy is the norm. A careful    tracing through the subtext paints a picture of bureaucratic attempts to control,    direct, and defuse, but all done in a manner within the new bounds of having    to allow outsiders into formerly exclusive policy consideration processes.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In section two    attention is turned to the role of culture in foreign affairs. M&ocirc;nica    Leita Lessa, Miriam Gomes Saraiva and Dhiego de Moura Mapa begin with a chapter    looking at the international cultural policies of the Lula government. Identity    becomes an important consideration here with culture being used not only to    present a desired and palatable Brazilian identity to the outside world, but    also to reinforce a positive self-image to Brazilians and increase their comfort    with the country's growing global presence. Itamaraty was intimately involved    in this process, but in a sense more as the institution managing the external    application of the policy; much of the formulation and pursuit of the underlying    programs and policies came from the Ministry of Culture with a strong push from    the presidency. The chapter by Minique Badar&oacute; on the State of Bahia's    international cultural policies examines the extent to which sub-national governmental    units are working to advance their specific agenda and interests distinct from    the larger program run by Itamaraty. As Badar&oacute; points out, cultural promotion    is an excellent method of raising a country's or state's international profile    in a positive manner, making it something of a hotspot that can drive a multitude    of activities ranging from tourism through foreign investment and trade to inter-departmental    cooperation and collaboration.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Leticia Pinheiro    and Gregory Beshara start the third section on education with a chapter examining    how education policies have been used to help drive regional integration processes.    As they point out, cooperation in the field of education plays an important    role in efforts to build Mercosul and a wider South American space, which in    turn points to the importance of education on identity formation and the solidification    of national, let alone regional projects. The line between educational and foreign    policy thus blurs, putting further implicit pressure on Itamaraty's attempts    to direct Brazilian foreign policy. In some respects this chapter is more interesting    for the questions it raises about foreign policy formulation than the role of    education in foreign affairs, which neatly presages the compelling conclusion    to the book. A more technical approach to education is taken by Alessandro Candeas,    who effectively opens up interesting questions of South-South cooperation and    the strengthening of educational and national capacity by looking at process    of inter-state university cooperation.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Andr&eacute; de    Mello e Souza opens the fourth section by looking at Brazil's response to the    AIDS epidemic. While this story is well known, the author aptly uses it to demonstrate    not only how the line between national and international policy has blurred,    but also how traditional realist views of international relations focused on    the state as actor collapse when faced with pressure from multinational corporations    and rising coalitions acting through organizations such as the WTO. Further    blurring of policy division lines is introduced by discussion of how Brazil's    successful anti-AIDS programming has evolved into something of a foreign policy    engagement device across the global South. Paulo Marchiori Buss and Jos&eacute;    Roberto Ferreira build on this theme in the next chapter, discussing Brazil's    experience with South-South cooperation in the health field, pointing out that    while it has significantly enhanced Brazil's international engagement, much    of the work has been driven from outside Itamaraty and is based in national    principles such as a constitutional right to health that stand distinct from    the realm of foreign policy.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The final section    on paradiplomacy in some ways delivers the coup de grace to the notion of Itamaraty    controlling Brazil's foreign policy. Two chapters, one by M&oacute;nica Salom&oacute;n    and the other by Alberto Kleiman, get to a very disturbing question for Itamaraty    diehards: technically, only Itamaraty has the constitutional authority to engage    in foreign negotiations, but what can be done if other levels of government    decide to ignore this 'rule'? As is made clear in the two chapters, Brazil's    states and municipalities are increasingly building their own sets of foreign    relationships for a variety of reasons, including seeking development assistance,    marketing themselves as a business and tourist destination, and collaborating    with other like-minded areas to share policy and program experiences. While    these are not questions of 'high' politics, they do fall into the realm of an    active foreign affairs agenda.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">This returns us    to the point at the core of this important book. As Pinheiro and Milani note    in their conclusion, the world of foreign affairs has become increasingly complicated,    encompassing a far more diverse array of actors and issues than were at play    during Rio Branco's time. This means that while Itamaraty is still central to    Brazil's foreign policy, it can no longer be an isolated monopolistic voice;    it has to actively and frequently engage with many other actors in policy areas    that diplomats might formerly have considered irrelevant. As the editors conclude,    foreign policy is now a public policy area with real domestic ramifications,    not the apolitical sphere of national interest that Rio Branco saw as needing    to be held above the daily political fracas. This suggests scholars should rethink    some of the founding assumptions underlying their research agendas. This excellent    volume provides us with a detailed explanation why and offers series of compelling    questions for future research.</font></p>      ]]></body>
</article>
