<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id>1981-3821</journal-id>
<journal-title><![CDATA[Brazilian Political Science Review]]></journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title><![CDATA[Bras. Political Sci. Rev.]]></abbrev-journal-title>
<issn>1981-3821</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Associação Brasileira de Ciência Política]]></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id>S1981-38212013000200009</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1981-38212013000200009</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[The unavoidable instability of politics]]></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Vieira]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Vinícius Rodrigues]]></given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A01">
<institution><![CDATA[,University of Oxford Nuffield College ]]></institution>
<addr-line><![CDATA[ ]]></addr-line>
<country>United Kingdom</country>
</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="pub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>00</day>
<month>00</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<numero>2</numero>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>170</lpage>
<copyright-statement/>
<copyright-year/>
<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_abstract&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_pdf&amp;pid=S1981-38212013000200009&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso"></self-uri></article-meta>
</front><body><![CDATA[ <p align="right"><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">    <b>BOOK REVIEW</b></font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="4"><a name="top"></a>The    unavoidable instability of politics</font></b></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><b><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Vin&iacute;cius    Rodrigues Vieira</font></b></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nuffield College,    University of Oxford, United Kingdom</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">(SNYDER, Jack.    <i>Power and Progress: International Politics in Transition</i>. New York: Routledge,    2012)</font></p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Nothing can be    taken for granted, says a popular dictum phrased in different languages and    manners. Such obvious statement, however, seems to have been forgotten by both    professionals and researchers of politics. Whereas professionals have been surprised    by social upheavals in societies where recent material progress seemed to have    had successfully accommodated contentious political grievances-as in Brazil    and Turkey-, researchers are have been caught by a wave that prioritizes hypothesis-testing    over concept- and theory-building. Yet if nobody can avoid the political and    the inherent conflictive nature of social life, how can any politician or bureaucrat    feel safe in the iron-cage of institutions? In such a context, should political    and other social scientists not revisit traditional concepts before putting    forward large-N observational and experimental research designs?</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In <i>Power and    Progress: International Politics in</i> Transition, Jack Snyder reminds us of    those sins as he flags out the very unstable nature of politics in both domestic    and international levels. In turn, that nature posits a serious challenge to    strictly institutionalist standpoints and approaches in Comparative Politics    and International Relations, as well as their methodological correlates. Within    12 chapters-most of them already published as articles in the last two decades    and co-authored with names such as Robert Jervis and Edward Mansfield-, Snyder    defies in theoretical and empirical terms the validity of a type of research    that seek of unfold the "effects of causes" without paying much attention to    the "causes of effects", to use a conceptual distinction recently advanced by    two renowned methodologists, Gary Goertz and James Mahoney (2012). Also, Snyder    and his co-authors master the difficult yet very much needed task to bridge    the gap between the literature in Comparative Politics and International Relations-a    crucial step for political scientists and policy-makers in a more and more interdependent    and unstable world that witnesses a power transition from the West to the East,    and an expansion of the standards of living in most of the old Third World.    The final result consists of a book that is useful for both research and teaching    purposes given the clarity of argumentation and the level of conceptual precision.    Yet Snyder incurs in a crucial pitfall: the defense-not always explicit-of a    normative agenda that may not result in stable world as it is often argued,    but certainly meet American and Western interests in general, and in part limits    his own conclusions.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">As Snyder himself    writes in the introduction, "...the logic of power in anarchy and the logic    of progress through modernization are deeply intertwined. Together they have    shaped the main patterns of international relations from the early modern period    to the present day. The chapters selected for this collection address each of    these logics and how they interact" (pp. 4). In <i>Myths of Empire</i>, published    in 1991, he had already discussed that interaction, yet with focus on the domestic    and international trajectories of great powers only. Now Snyder expands his    theoretical contributions through the analysis of diverse cases in which there    where domestic changes that eventually impacted international affairs in various    regions of the world and in the international system as a whole. To accomplish    such a task, he deploys an arsenal of both quantitative and qualitative tools,    combining them without losing the focus. Nonetheless, the author and his colleagues    proceed through a manner in which the methods do not become more important than    the questions that are asked. Nor concepts are left aside for the sake of attaining    the oversold excuse of parsimony. Complex phenomena, such as interactions between    domestic and international levels in times of transition, cannot be simplified    as there is the risk of resulting in pedestrian analysis, although, as <i>Power    and Progress</i> shows, it is certainly feasible to clarify them without oversimplification.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The book is organized    in three parts, each of them containing four chapters. In the first, "Anarchy    and its Effects", the focus lies on the impacts of international factors on    domestic politics. Deserves attention the chapter 2, co-authored with Thomas    J. Christensen as an article published at <i>International Organization</i>    in 1990. Snyder and Christensen combine the structural realist literature with    the concept of security dilemma to demonstrate that both World Wars were shaped    by states' misperceptions of their own security within contexts of rising multipolarity.    Such mistake resonates as an alert in a time when even close democratic allies,    such as the US and the EU, still engage themselves in mutual surveillance through    intelligence notwithstanding the high level of political-economic cooperation.    Chapter 5 also must be praised, as it employs insights from anthropology to    provide a more accurate explanation of the causes of war than models that focuses    parsimonious explanations based on either material or cultural considerations.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The second part,    "The Challenges of Democratic Transition", unfolds the dynamics between democratizing    processes and the complicated task of state-building. Originally a book chapter    co-authored with Mansfield and published in 2007, chapter 6 concludes-based    on an insightful combination of statistical and qualitative analysis-that in    states without "... institutional infrastructure needed to manage democratization..."    (pp. 126) there is the risk that nationalist- and ethnic-based discourses trigger    either international or domestic conflict. In chapter 8-the only one written    specially for the book-Snyder and Mansfield elaborate more on the argument that    social fragmentation tends to result in conflict if a country has yet to consolidate    its institutions. Nonetheless, the mechanism they propose for constraining instability    in democratizing polities is controversial: the authors argue for the control    or even the temporary suspension of certain civil and political rights, such    as freedom of speech and open elections, in order to constrain the rise of nationalist-populist    groups, which often rely on hate for building-up a common identity, having then    the potential to trigger wars.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">The final section,    "Empire and the Promotion of a Liberal Order", makes explicit the US-based agenda    that permeates most of the previous chapters and has the potential to weaken    Snyder's mastery of the craft of researching and theorizing. To be fair, he    criticizes the Bush Doctrine foreign policy that prioritizes democracy-promotion    at any cost-even at the expanse of the strength of the empire. Therefore, Snyder    argues, even a superpower faces limits. In fact, the book attempts to provide    formulas to build what Snyder calls the right sequence of democratization, and,    then, reassure the supremacy of the liberal order put forward by the Anglo-Saxon    world. In normative terms, such claim is too pretentious, not to say dangerous.    Politics as practice has so many uncertainties-as the plethora of examples offered    in the book prove-that generalizable formulas for policymakers may contribute    to generate misperceptions as much limitative as the ones Snyder targets in    his analysis.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">Moreover, Snyder    posits but does not address in full the most exciting questions that surround    the current state of affairs in the global field of power. In the introduction,    he asks how rising powers, mostly notably China, will fit in an international    order dominated by liberal democracies, as well as how the latter, led by the    US, will react to what appears to be an emerging multipolar order. Furthermore,    the author wonders whether the demand for mass political participation in the    periphery will actually result in solid political institutions. The response    for these puzzles remains incomplete as the authors' bias in favor of an American-led    order eventually prevail over undisputable facts, such as the current lack of    a revisionist impetus from the emerging world.</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">In framing much    of what is addressed in the book in terms of the opposition between realists    and neoliberals in International Relations, Snyder also misses the chance to    make very explicitly what could help scholars to put forward more complex analysis    without sacrificing precision for the illusion of parsimony. In its more accurate    versions, constructivism, mainly neglected in the book, provides incipient tools    to capture the unavoidable instability of politics. To recast the introductory    paragraph, nothing can be taken for granted. Nonetheless, in the task of doing    and building science, one certainly has to rely on a minimum set of procedures    and concepts to conduct any kind of systematic investigation of observable phenomena.    The challenge then consists of being aware that in different cases a given concept    may mean different outcomes, as well as that all correlations depend on causal    linkages that are potentially <i>ad-hoc</i>. That is, one has to investigate,    prior to testing effects of causes, which are the most likely causes of effects.    In other words, the rationalist quest for <i>explanation</i> does not hold without    more work than that necessary to reach the constructivist goal of <i>understanding</i>.    One complements the other as neither rationalism nor constructivism is a substantive    theory (Fearon and Wendt 2002).</font></p>     <p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">International and    domestic processes show that politics as a practice is indeed unstable. So does    politics as a science that, as Snyder's work suggest, might not be anything    more than the defense of a normative agenda, which, of course, does not annihilate    the strengths of coherent theory and good research as present in most of <i>Power    and Progress</i>.</font></p>     <p>&nbsp;</p>     ]]></body>
<body><![CDATA[<p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><b>References</b></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">FEARON, James and    WENDT, Alexander. (2002), Rationalism v. Constructivism: a Skeptical View. In:    <i>Handbook of International Relations</i>, edited by Walter Carlsnaes, Thomas    Risse, and Beth A. Simmons. Thousand Oaks: Sage Publications. Pp. 57-72.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000024&pid=S1981-3821201300020000900001&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>     <!-- ref --><p><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="2">GOERTZ, Gary. MAHONEY,    James. (2012), <i>A Tale of Two Cultures: Qualitative and Quantitative Research    in the Social Sciences</i>. Princeton and Oxford: Princeton University Press.    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;[&#160;<a href="javascript:void(0);" onclick="javascript: window.open('/scielo.php?script=sci_nlinks&ref=000026&pid=S1981-3821201300020000900002&lng=','','width=640,height=500,resizable=yes,scrollbars=1,menubar=yes,');">Links</a>&#160;]<!-- end-ref --></font></p>      ]]></body><back>
<ref-list>
<ref id="B1">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[FEARON]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[James]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[WENDT]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Alexander]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[Rationalism v. Constructivism: a Skeptical View]]></article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Carlsnaes]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Walter]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Risse]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Thomas]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[Simmons]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Beth A.]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[Handbook of International Relations]]></source>
<year>2002</year>
<page-range>57-72</page-range><publisher-loc><![CDATA[Thousand Oaks ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Sage Publications]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="B2">
<nlm-citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[GOERTZ]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[Gary]]></given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname><![CDATA[MAHONEY]]></surname>
<given-names><![CDATA[James]]></given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source><![CDATA[A Tale of Two Cultures: Qualitative and Quantitative Research in the Social Sciences]]></source>
<year>2012</year>
<publisher-loc><![CDATA[PrincetonOxford ]]></publisher-loc>
<publisher-name><![CDATA[Princeton University Press]]></publisher-name>
</nlm-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
